<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xml" href="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/feed.xslt.xml"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/topics/computational-chemistry/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <updated>2024-03-26T14:39:37+00:00</updated>
  <id>https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/topics/computational-chemistry/feed.xml</id>
  <title>Galaxy Training Network - Computational chemistry</title>
  <subtitle>Recently added tutorials, slides, and FAQs in the computational-chemistry topic</subtitle>
  <entry>
    <title>Data management in Medicinal Chemistry</title>
    <link href="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/topics/computational-chemistry/tutorials/med-chem-data/tutorial.html"/>
    <id>https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/topics/computational-chemistry/tutorials/med-chem-data/tutorial.html</id>
    <updated>2024-01-08T09:55:32+00:00</updated>
    <category term="new tutorial"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The development of medicinal chemistry is advancing very rapidly. Big pharmaceutical companies, research institutes and universities are working on ground-breaking solutions to help patients combat all kinds of diseases. During that development process, tons of data are generated – not only from the lab environment but also from clinical trials. Given that the discovery of more potent, safer and cheaper drugs is the ultimate goal of all research bodies, we should all focus on making the data we gather FAIR: &lt;strong&gt;F&lt;/strong&gt;indable, &lt;strong&gt;A&lt;/strong&gt;ccessible, &lt;strong&gt;I&lt;/strong&gt;nteroperable, and &lt;strong&gt;R&lt;/strong&gt;eusable to push the boundaries of drug development even further.&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Protein target prediction of a bioactive ligand with Align-it and ePharmaLib</title>
    <link href="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/topics/computational-chemistry/tutorials/zauberkugel/tutorial.html"/>
    <id>https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/topics/computational-chemistry/tutorials/zauberkugel/tutorial.html</id>
    <updated>2022-02-15T13:56:40+00:00</updated>
    <category term="new tutorial"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Historically, the pharmacophore concept was formulated in 1909 by the German physician and Nobel prize laureate Paul Ehrlich (&lt;span class="citation"&gt;&lt;a href="#Ehrlich1909"&gt;Ehrlich 1909&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;). According to the &lt;a href="https://iupac.org/"&gt;International Union of Pure and Applied Chemistry (IUPAC)&lt;/a&gt;, a pharmacophore is defined as “an ensemble of steric and electronic features that is necessary to ensure the optimal supramolecular interactions with a specific biological target and to trigger (or block) its biological response” (&lt;span class="citation"&gt;&lt;a href="#Wermuth1998"&gt;Wermuth &lt;i&gt;et al.&lt;/i&gt; 1998&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;). Starting from the cocrystal structure of a non-covalent protein–ligand complex (e.g. Figure 1), pharmacophore perception involves the extraction of the key molecular features of the bioactive ligand at the protein–ligand contact interface into a single model (&lt;span class="citation"&gt;&lt;a href="#Moumbock2019"&gt;Moumbock &lt;i&gt;et al.&lt;/i&gt; 2019&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;). These pharmacophoric features mainly include: H-bond acceptor (HACC or A), H-bond donor (HDON or D), lipophilic group (LIPO or H), negative center (NEGC or N), positive center (POSC or P), and aromatic ring (AROM or R) moieties. Moreover, receptor-based excluded spheres (EXCL) can be added in order to mimic spatial constraints of the binding pocket (Figure 2). Once a pharmacophore model has been generated, a query can be performed either in a forward manner, using several ligands to search for novel putative hits of a given target, or in a reverse manner, by screening a single ligand against multiple pharmacophore models in search of putative protein targets (&lt;span class="citation"&gt;&lt;a href="#Steindl2006"&gt;Steindl &lt;i&gt;et al.&lt;/i&gt; 2006&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>High Throughput Molecular Dynamics and Analysis</title>
    <link href="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/topics/computational-chemistry/tutorials/htmd-analysis/tutorial.html"/>
    <id>https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/topics/computational-chemistry/tutorials/htmd-analysis/tutorial.html</id>
    <updated>2020-05-20T17:27:02+00:00</updated>
    <category term="new tutorial"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;This tutorial provides an introduction to using high-throughput molecular dynamics to study protein-ligand interaction, as applied to the N-terminal domain of Hsp90 (heat shock protein 90).&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Virtual screening of the SARS-CoV-2 main protease with rxDock and pose scoring</title>
    <link href="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/topics/computational-chemistry/tutorials/covid19-docking/tutorial.html"/>
    <id>https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/topics/computational-chemistry/tutorials/covid19-docking/tutorial.html</id>
    <updated>2020-03-27T13:26:13+00:00</updated>
    <category term="new tutorial"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;This tutorial provides a companion to the work performed in March 2020 by InformaticsMatters, the Diamond Light Source, and the European Galaxy Team to perform virtual screening on candidate ligands for the SARS-CoV-2 main protease (MPro). This work is described &lt;a href="https://covid19.galaxyproject.org/cheminformatics"&gt;in our dedicated site&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Protein-ligand docking</title>
    <link href="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/topics/computational-chemistry/tutorials/cheminformatics/tutorial.html"/>
    <id>https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/topics/computational-chemistry/tutorials/cheminformatics/tutorial.html</id>
    <updated>2019-10-19T00:16:01+00:00</updated>
    <category term="new tutorial"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Cheminformatics is the use of computational techniques and information about molecules to solve problems in chemistry. This involves a number of steps: retrieving data on chemical compounds, sorting data for properties which are of interest, and extracting new information. This tutorial will provide a brief overview of all of these, centered around protein-ligand docking, a molecular modelling technique. The purpose of protein-ligand docking is to find the optimal binding between a small molecule (ligand) and a protein. It is generally applied to the drug discovery and development process with the aim of finding a potential drug candidate. First, a target protein is identified. This protein is usually linked to a disease and is known to bind small molecules. Second, a ‘library’ of possible ligands is assembled. Ligands are small molecules that bind to a protein and may interfere with protein function. Each of the compounds in the library is then ‘docked’ into the protein to find the optimal binding position and energy.&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Analysis of molecular dynamics simulations</title>
    <link href="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/topics/computational-chemistry/tutorials/analysis-md-simulations/tutorial.html"/>
    <id>https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/topics/computational-chemistry/tutorials/analysis-md-simulations/tutorial.html</id>
    <updated>2019-06-03T07:41:49+00:00</updated>
    <category term="new tutorial"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Molecular dynamics simulations return highly complex data. The Cartesian positions of each atom of the system (thousands or even millions) are recorded at every time step of the trajectory; this may again be thousands to millions of steps in length. Therefore, some kind of further analysis is needed to extract useful information from the data.&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Running molecular dynamics simulations using GROMACS</title>
    <link href="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/topics/computational-chemistry/tutorials/md-simulation-gromacs/tutorial.html"/>
    <id>https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/topics/computational-chemistry/tutorials/md-simulation-gromacs/tutorial.html</id>
    <updated>2019-06-03T07:41:49+00:00</updated>
    <category term="new tutorial"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Molecular dynamics (MD) is a method to simulate molecular motion by iterative application of Newton’s laws of motion. It is often applied to large biomolecules such as proteins or nucleic acids.&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Setting up molecular systems</title>
    <link href="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/topics/computational-chemistry/tutorials/setting-up-molecular-systems/tutorial.html"/>
    <id>https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/topics/computational-chemistry/tutorials/setting-up-molecular-systems/tutorial.html</id>
    <updated>2019-06-03T07:41:49+00:00</updated>
    <category term="new tutorial"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;In this tutorial, we’ll cover the basics of molecular modelling by setting up a protein in complex with a ligand and uploading the structure to Galaxy. This tutorial will make use of CHARMM-GUI. Please note that the follow-up to this tutorial (located in &lt;a href="/training-material/topics/computational-chemistry/tutorials/md-simulation-namd/tutorial.html"&gt;Running molecular dynamics simulations using NAMD&lt;/a&gt;) requires access to NAMD Galaxy tools, which can be accessed using the &lt;a href="https://github.com/scientificomputing/BRIDGE"&gt;Docker container&lt;/a&gt; but are currently not available on any public Galaxy server.&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
  </entry>
</feed>
