<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xml" href="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/feed.xslt.xml"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2023-04-07T00:10:32+00:00</updated><id>https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Galaxy Training!</title><subtitle>A collection of tutorials generated and maintained by Galaxy Community Members across the world</subtitle><entry><title type="html">New Feature: Trainer Directory! (Add yourself today!)</title><link href="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/2023/03/21/galaxy-trainer-directory.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="New Feature: Trainer Directory! (Add yourself today!)" /><published>2023-03-21T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-03-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/2023/03/21/galaxy-trainer-directory</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/2023/03/21/galaxy-trainer-directory.html"><![CDATA[<p>Numerous other training groups keep “Trainer Directories” as a way to help students meet trainers in their area, especially for hosting workshops for their local community. There have been a handful of attempts at this in the past, both in <a href="https://github.com/galaxyproject/galaxy-maps">galaxyproject/galaxy-maps</a> and in <a href="https://www.google.com/maps/d/u/0/viewer?mid=1r8LJy6la-JeIrg23aZjpwVNjJDE">a Google Map</a> on the GTN homepage.</p>

<p>We will now store this data within the GTN itself, and trainers can manage this data themselves. If you are a trainer that offers training courses in your local area, or are interested in helping others teach in that region, please feel free to update your Contributors profile with the new metadata:</p>

<div class="language-yaml highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="na">hexylena</span><span class="pi">:</span>
    <span class="na">name</span><span class="pi">:</span> <span class="s">Helena Rasche</span>
    <span class="na">orcid</span><span class="pi">:</span> <span class="s">0000-0001-9760-8992</span>
    <span class="s">...</span>
    <span class="na">contact_for_training</span><span class="pi">:</span> <span class="no">true</span>
    <span class="na">location</span><span class="pi">:</span>
      <span class="na">country</span><span class="pi">:</span> <span class="s">NL</span>
      <span class="na">lat</span><span class="pi">:</span> <span class="m">51.91</span>
      <span class="na">lon</span><span class="pi">:</span> <span class="m">4.46</span>
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>And we’ll add a nice map to the GTN, and potentially the Galaxy Hub as well! The <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">contact_for_training</code> field is a true or false value which lets you indicate you’re open to being contacted regarding giving training. Other trainers in your region might use this if they’re looking for help giving a course or want experts in a field for a course they plan to host. We do not have plans currently expose this to “end users” looking for training, we will probably attempt to push them first to the existing events list.</p>]]></content><author><name>Helena Rasche, Lucille Delisle</name></author><category term="news" /><category term="new feature" /><category term="community building" /><category term="capacity building" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Numerous other training groups keep “Trainer Directories” as a way to help students meet trainers in their area, especially for hosting workshops for their local community. There have been a handful of attempts at this in the past, both in galaxyproject/galaxy-maps and in a Google Map on the GTN homepage.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What are the most used tools in the GTN?</title><link href="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/2023/02/08/top-tools.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What are the most used tools in the GTN?" /><published>2023-02-08T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-02-08T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/2023/02/08/top-tools</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/2023/02/08/top-tools.html"><![CDATA[<p>Did you ever wonder which was the number one most used tool in the GTN? There is a new page of <a href="/training-material/top-tools.html">Top Tools</a> where we list all of the top tools in the GTN, and which tutorials use them. We guessed “upload1”, but it seems like not every author annotates that step explicitly in their tutorial, and of course it doesn’t appear in the workflows which we also scan to create this tool listing.</p>

<p>This list is also <a href="/training-material/api/top-tools.json">available as a JSON API</a>. And additionally we have exposed them as individual page listings as well, e.g. if you wanted to link to “All GTN Tutorials Using My Tool”, you could do that with one of <a href="/training-material/by-tool/cat1.html">these pages like Cat1</a>, or <a href="/training-material/by-tool/iuc/multiqc.html">iuc/multiqc</a></p>

<p>We hope to connect this to the training materials in more places in the future, e.g. “Find other tutorials using this tool” type annotations automatically. Or even embedding it in the Galaxy tool form! If you have ideas, let us know!</p>]]></content><author><name>Helena Rasche</name></author><category term="news" /><category term="new feature" /><category term="gtn" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Did you ever wonder which was the number one most used tool in the GTN? There is a new page of Top Tools where we list all of the top tools in the GTN, and which tutorials use them. We guessed “upload1”, but it seems like not every author annotates that step explicitly in their tutorial, and of course it doesn’t appear in the workflows which we also scan to create this tool listing.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">GTN Celebrates Black History Month</title><link href="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/2023/02/02/black-history-month.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="GTN Celebrates Black History Month" /><published>2023-02-02T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-02-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/2023/02/02/black-history-month</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/2023/02/02/black-history-month.html"><![CDATA[<p>February marks <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Black_History_Month">Black History Month</a> in the United States. This year we want to celebrate that by introducing a new theme (<a href="#" onclick="setTheme('blm')">Click to Activate</a>), and taking a look at one of the most famous Black figures in Science: <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henrietta_Lacks">Henrietta Lacks</a> whose contribution to science went unremarked and unappreciated for decades while white scientists took credit for advancements built on her cell line.</p>

<p>Her cell line is the oldest and most commonly used human cell line <span class="citation"><a href="#Rahbari_2009">Rahbari <i>et al.</i> 2009</a></span>, and is the reason for large scale policy change, especially major regulatory changes in informed consent in the United States <span class="citation"><a href="#Beskow_2016">Beskow 2016</a></span>. Unfortunately none of these changes happened quickly, it took until 2013 before her descendants could have a say in how her genetic material is used in NIH research <span class="citation"><a href="#lacks_family_2013">University 2013</a></span>.</p>

<h2 id="johns-hopkins">Johns Hopkins</h2>

<p>Henrietta was a patient at Johns Hopkins Hospital; Johns Hopkins University employs many of the core Galaxy Developers.</p>

<p>Johns Hopkins has announced the construction of a new building named in her honor, specifically focusing on research around bioethics: “The building will support the Berman Institute of Bioethics, the Johns Hopkins University School of Medicine, and additional departments, as well as collaborative space for education, research, and meetings.” <span class="citation"><a href="#jhu_construction_announcement">University 2022</a></span></p>

<h2 id="bioethics">Bioethics</h2>

<blockquote class="quote">
  <p>Lacks’s case is one of many examples of the lack of informed consent in 20th century medicine. Communication between tissue donors and doctors was virtually nonexistent (i.e. cells were taken without patient consent, nor were they told what the cells would be used for). Johns Hopkins Hospital, where Lacks received treatment and had her tissue harvested, was the only hospital in the Baltimore area where African American patients could receive free care. The patients receiving free care from this segregated sect of the hospital often became research subjects without their knowledge. Lacks’s family also had no access to her patient files and had no say in who received HeLa cells or what they would be used for. Additionally, as HeLa cells were popularized and used more frequently throughout the scientific community, Lacks’s relatives received no financial benefit and continued to live with limited access to healthcare. <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/HeLa#Controversy">via Wikipedia</a></p>
</blockquote>

<p>We recommend the book <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Immortal_Life_of_Henrietta_Lacks">“The Immortal Life of Henrietta Lacks”</a> for further reading on the topic.</p>

<h2 id="gtn-connection">GTN Connection</h2>

<p>The GTN has four tutorials that make use of HeLa cell line data. After reading about Henrietta and her impact on science, you might be interested in following one of these tutorials to learn about the applications of her cells, two on imaging analysis:</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="/training-material/topics/imaging/tutorials/imaging-introduction/tutorial.html">Introduction to image analysis using Galaxy</a></li>
  <li><a href="/training-material/topics/imaging/tutorials/hela-screen-analysis/tutorial.html">Analyse HeLa fluorescence siRNA screen</a></li>
</ul>

<p>And two proteomics tutorials:</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="/training-material/topics/proteomics/tutorials/protein-id-oms/tutorial.html">Peptide and Protein ID using OpenMS tools</a></li>
  <li><a href="/training-material/topics/proteomics/tutorials/protein-id-sg-ps/tutorial.html">Peptide and Protein ID using SearchGUI and PeptideShaker</a></li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name>Helena Rasche</name></author><category term="news" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[February marks Black History Month in the United States. This year we want to celebrate that by introducing a new theme (Click to Activate), and taking a look at one of the most famous Black figures in Science: Henrietta Lacks whose contribution to science went unremarked and unappreciated for decades while white scientists took credit for advancements built on her cell line.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">New Tutorial: Pathogen detection from (direct Nanopore) sequencing data using Galaxy - Foodborne Edition</title><link href="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/2023/01/26/pathogen-detection-tutorial.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="New Tutorial: Pathogen detection from (direct Nanopore) sequencing data using Galaxy - Foodborne Edition" /><published>2023-01-26T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-01-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/2023/01/26/pathogen-detection-tutorial</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/2023/01/26/pathogen-detection-tutorial.html"><![CDATA[<p>Food contamination with pathogens are a major burden on our society. Globally, they affect an estimated 600 million people a year and impact socioeconomic development at different levels. These outbreaks are mainly due to <em>Salmonella spp.</em> followed by <em>Campylobacter spp.</em> and Noroviruses.</p>

<p>The evolution of techniques in the last decades has made possible the development of methods to quickly identify responsible pathogen using their <strong>DNA and without prior isolation</strong>. Long-read sequencing tehcniques like ONT make these methods even <strong>easier and more practical to identify strains quicker and with fewer reads</strong>.</p>

<p>In this tutorial, using direct Nanopore sequencing data, we show how to</p>
<ol>
  <li><strong>agnostically detect pathogens</strong> (what exactly is this pathogen and what is the degree of its severity (its virulence factors) from data extracted directly (without prior cultivation) from a potentially contaminated sample (e.g. food like chicken, cow, etc.,) and sequenced using Nanopore</li>
  <li><strong>compare different samples to track</strong> the possible source of contamination</li>
</ol>

<p>This tutorial is offered in 2 different version:</p>
<ul>
  <li>A short version, running already build workflows</li>
  <li>A long version, going step-by-step</li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name>Bérénice Batut, Engy Nasr</name></author><category term="news" /><category term="new tutorial" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Food contamination with pathogens are a major burden on our society. Globally, they affect an estimated 600 million people a year and impact socioeconomic development at different levels. These outbreaks are mainly due to Salmonella spp. followed by Campylobacter spp. and Noroviruses.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/topics/metagenomics/tutorials/pathogen-detection-from-nanopore-foodborne-data/images/FoodBorne-Workflow-updated.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/topics/metagenomics/tutorials/pathogen-detection-from-nanopore-foodborne-data/images/FoodBorne-Workflow-updated.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">New Feature: Prometheus Metrics endpoint</title><link href="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/2023/01/24/prometheus.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="New Feature: Prometheus Metrics endpoint" /><published>2023-01-24T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-01-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/2023/01/24/prometheus</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/2023/01/24/prometheus.html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://prometheus.io/">Prometheus</a> is an increasingly popular monitoring solution whereby sites expose a <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">/metrics</code> endpoint, and then a central Prometheus server can scrape it for data which is then plotted or visualised or alerted upon. We at the GTN are now testing out a prometheus endpoint for our completely static site which we’ll use to expose some maybe useful statistics about the GTN that others can then scrape and display in ways that are useful for them.</p>

<p>You can see the current GTN metrics endpoint at <a href="https://training.galaxyproject.org/metrics">/metrics</a></p>]]></content><author><name>Helena Rasche</name></author><category term="news" /><category term="new feature" /><category term="gtn" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Prometheus is an increasingly popular monitoring solution whereby sites expose a /metrics endpoint, and then a central Prometheus server can scrape it for data which is then plotted or visualised or alerted upon. We at the GTN are now testing out a prometheus endpoint for our completely static site which we’ll use to expose some maybe useful statistics about the GTN that others can then scrape and display in ways that are useful for them.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">New GTN Feature Tag-based Topics enables new SARS-CoV-2 topic</title><link href="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/2023/01/23/new-covid19-topic.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="New GTN Feature Tag-based Topics enables new SARS-CoV-2 topic" /><published>2023-01-23T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-01-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/2023/01/23/new-covid19-topic</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/2023/01/23/new-covid19-topic.html"><![CDATA[<p>The GTN has long struggled with the rigid hierarchy of a single level of classification: topics. All materials had to be organised into a single topic, even when their contents sometimes spanned multiple topics! We added subtopics a while back to help further organise these tutorials, but that still did not solve the issue of needing to collect multiple learn materials in a single location for people to access.</p>

<p>Thus we have finally built tag based topics; these are not topic folders inside the GTN repository, but instead a collection of every tutorial tagged with some specific tag, organised into a new topic. As a demonstration of this, <a href="/training-material/topics/covid19/">we have setup a Covid-19 topic.</a></p>

<p>We apologise for the long delay getting here, development time was quite limited for a long period during the pandemic, and we needed to re-organise some internal structures to better enable these new “views” into the GTN Materials.</p>]]></content><author><name>Helena Rasche, Wolfgang Maier</name></author><category term="news" /><category term="new topic" /><category term="new feature" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The GTN has long struggled with the rigid hierarchy of a single level of classification: topics. All materials had to be organised into a single topic, even when their contents sometimes spanned multiple topics! We added subtopics a while back to help further organise these tutorials, but that still did not solve the issue of needing to collect multiple learn materials in a single location for people to access.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">New GTN paper: “Galaxy Training: A powerful framework for teaching!”</title><link href="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/2023/01/10/gtn-paper.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="New GTN paper: “Galaxy Training: A powerful framework for teaching!”" /><published>2023-01-10T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-01-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/2023/01/10/gtn-paper</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/2023/01/10/gtn-paper.html"><![CDATA[<p>Our new paper about the Galaxy Training Network has been published this week in Plos Computational Biology: <a href="https://journals.plos.org/ploscompbiol/article?id=10.1371/journal.pcbi.1010752">“Galaxy Training: A powerful framework for teaching!”</a></p>

<p><strong>We would like to thank all contributors to the <a href="/training-material/hall-of-fame.html">GTN</a> and Galaxy ecosystem in general</strong>. Without you, we would not have able to build such a great platform and awesome material, and reach some many people! We would like to thank also to the reviewers for their valuable comments that helped improving the paper.</p>

<p><img src="/training-material/news/images/2023-01-10-gtn-paper-fig1.png" alt=" Statistics about training events organized by the Galaxy community and visits of the GTN website over years. (A) Number of events supported GTN materials, registered on the Galaxy Community Hub website [22], per year between 2018 and 2021. (B) Number of TIaaS events per year on Galaxy Europe (collected in May 2022). (C) Number of participants to TIaaS events per year on UseGalaxy.* (collected in May 2022). (D) Number of visits per year on the GTN website and per topics, initially tracked by Google Analytics and later with Plausible (collected in May 2022)." /></p>

<h2 id="abstract">Abstract</h2>

<p>There is an ongoing explosion of scientific datasets being generated, brought on by recent technological advances in many areas of the natural sciences. As a result, the life sciences have become increasingly computational in nature, and bioinformatics has taken on a central role in research studies. However, basic computational skills, data analysis, and stewardship are still rarely taught in life science educational programs, resulting in a skills gap in many of the researchers tasked with analysing these big datasets.</p>

<p>In order to address this skills gap and empower researchers to perform their own data analyses, the Galaxy Training Network (GTN) has previously developed the Galaxy Training Platform (<a href="https://training.galaxyproject.org">https://training.galaxyproject.org</a>), an open access, community-driven framework for the collection of FAIR (Findable, Accessible, Interoperable, Reusable) training materials for data analysis utilizing the user-friendly Galaxy framework as its primary data analysis platform.</p>

<p>Since its inception, this training platform has thrived, with the number of tutorials and contributors growing rapidly, and the range of topics extending beyond life sciences to include topics such as climatology, cheminformatics, and machine learning. While initially aimed at supporting researchers directly, the GTN framework has proven to be an invaluable resource for educators as well. We have focused our efforts in recent years on adding increased support for this growing community of instructors. New features have been added to facilitate the use of the materials in a classroom setting, simplifying the contribution flow for new materials, and have added a set of train-the-trainer lessons. Here, we present the latest developments in the GTN project, aimed at facilitating the use of the Galaxy Training materials by educators, and its usage in different learning environments.</p>]]></content><author><name>Bérénice Batut, Saskia Hiltemann, Helena Rasche</name></author><category term="news" /><category term="paper" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Our new paper about the Galaxy Training Network has been published this week in Plos Computational Biology: “Galaxy Training: A powerful framework for teaching!”]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/images/2023-01-10-gtn-paper-fig2.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/images/2023-01-10-gtn-paper-fig2.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">New Tutorial Suite: Deconvolution with MuSiC, from public data to disease interrogation!</title><link href="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/2022/11/29/deconvolution.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="New Tutorial Suite: Deconvolution with MuSiC, from public data to disease interrogation!" /><published>2022-11-29T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-11-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/2022/11/29/deconvolution</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/2022/11/29/deconvolution.html"><![CDATA[<p>The still new and shiny single-cell analysis topic now boasts a <a href="/training-material/topics/single-cell/index.html">deconvolution tutorial suite</a>! What does deconvolution do you ask? Well, in this context, it infers cell proportions from bulk RNA-seq data. You heard that correctly - instead of expensive new single-cell experiments, you can re-analyse old bulk RNA-seq data and estimate cell proportions. All you need is a reasonably good single cell dataset to use as a reference and you’re good to go! The tutorial suite shows you how to build your reference from publicly available single cell data, and apply analysis to some publicly available bulk RNA-seq data.</p>

<p>This suite was built by<a href="/training-material/hall-of-fame/nomadscientist/" class="contributor-badge contributor-nomadscientist"><img src="/training-material/assets/images/orcid.png" alt="orcid logo" /><img src="https://avatars.githubusercontent.com/nomadscientist?s=27" alt="Avatar" />Wendi Bacon</a>,<a href="/training-material/hall-of-fame/mtekman/" class="contributor-badge contributor-mtekman"><img src="https://avatars.githubusercontent.com/mtekman?s=27" alt="Avatar" />Mehmet Tekman</a>and we’d love to hear your thoughts, so do fill out the feedback form at the ends or give us a shout on the galaxy-single-cell Gitter/Matrix forums!</p>

<p>We are also planning to test this as potential undergraduate capstone projects, so <a href="https://forms.gle/jgfbz73FrvNkEywP6">please get in touch</a> if you’d like to be a help with such a study.</p>]]></content><author><name>Mehmet Tekman, Wendi Bacon</name></author><category term="news" /><category term="new tutorial" /><category term="single-cell" /><category term="transcriptomics" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The still new and shiny single-cell analysis topic now boasts a deconvolution tutorial suite! What does deconvolution do you ask? Well, in this context, it infers cell proportions from bulk RNA-seq data. You heard that correctly - instead of expensive new single-cell experiments, you can re-analyse old bulk RNA-seq data and estimate cell proportions. All you need is a reasonably good single cell dataset to use as a reference and you’re good to go! The tutorial suite shows you how to build your reference from publicly available single cell data, and apply analysis to some publicly available bulk RNA-seq data.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/images/heatmap.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/images/heatmap.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">New Topic: Single Cell Analysis!</title><link href="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/2022/11/18/singlecell.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="New Topic: Single Cell Analysis!" /><published>2022-11-18T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-11-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/2022/11/18/singlecell</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/2022/11/18/singlecell.html"><![CDATA[<p>Single-cell analysis now has <a href="/training-material/topics/single-cell/index.html">it’s own topic</a>! These tutorials were previously part of the <a href="/training-material/topics/transcriptomics/index.html">transcriptomics topic</a>, but due to the amazing efforts by<a href="/training-material/hall-of-fame/nomadscientist/" class="contributor-badge contributor-nomadscientist"><img src="/training-material/assets/images/orcid.png" alt="orcid logo" /><img src="https://avatars.githubusercontent.com/nomadscientist?s=27" alt="Avatar" />Wendi Bacon</a>,<a href="/training-material/hall-of-fame/mtekman/" class="contributor-badge contributor-mtekman"><img src="https://avatars.githubusercontent.com/mtekman?s=27" alt="Avatar" />Mehmet Tekman</a>and others, we now have so many single-cell analysis tutorials that they deserve their own dedicated topic! From introductory slides and practicals, to case study tutorials generating cell clusters and trajectories from raw sequencing files, and even a growing subtopic of smaller tips and tricks for adapting analysis to user needs, the single cell topic either has what you need or is working on it. Come learn or get involved!</p>

<p>Exciting new single-cell tutorials are also planned to be added in the near future, so keep your eyes on this hot topic!</p>

<p><a href="/training-material/topics/single-cell/index.html" class="btn btn-primary">View Topic</a></p>]]></content><author><name>Wendi Bacon, Mehmet Tekman</name></author><category term="news" /><category term="new topic" /><category term="single-cell" /><category term="new feature" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Single-cell analysis now has it’s own topic! These tutorials were previously part of the transcriptomics topic, but due to the amazing efforts byWendi Bacon,Mehmet Tekmanand others, we now have so many single-cell analysis tutorials that they deserve their own dedicated topic! From introductory slides and practicals, to case study tutorials generating cell clusters and trajectories from raw sequencing files, and even a growing subtopic of smaller tips and tricks for adapting analysis to user needs, the single cell topic either has what you need or is working on it. Come learn or get involved!]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/images/single_cell.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/images/single_cell.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">New Tutorial: Data Manipulation</title><link href="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/2022/09/11/data-manipulation-tutorial.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="New Tutorial: Data Manipulation" /><published>2022-09-11T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-09-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/2022/09/11/data-manipulation-tutorial</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/2022/09/11/data-manipulation-tutorial.html"><![CDATA[<p>Many analyses in Galaxy require small data manipulations in between tools as a sort of “glue” between analysis steps. For example, you may need to change the file format, re-order columns in a table, replace certain values, or perform some filtering operation, before you can proceed to the next step of your analysis. Galaxy offers a wide range of tools that can perform such generic data manipulation tasks, and mastering these types of operations in Galaxy can help you streamline your analysis and get the most out of Galaxy.</p>

<p>Using a dataset containing historical Olympics results, this tutorial walks you through how to use a wide range of such generic data manipulation tools in Galaxy. These tools can be useful in any analysis, regardless of scientific domain.</p>

<p>Each section of the tutorial is independent of the ones preceeding it, so you can jump directly to the section you are interested in.</p>]]></content><author><name>Saskia Hiltemann</name></author><category term="news" /><category term="new tutorial" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Many analyses in Galaxy require small data manipulations in between tools as a sort of “glue” between analysis steps. For example, you may need to change the file format, re-order columns in a table, replace certain values, or perform some filtering operation, before you can proceed to the next step of your analysis. Galaxy offers a wide range of tools that can perform such generic data manipulation tasks, and mastering these types of operations in Galaxy can help you streamline your analysis and get the most out of Galaxy.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/topics/introduction/tutorials/data-manipulation-olympics/images/cover.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/topics/introduction/tutorials/data-manipulation-olympics/images/cover.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>