<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xml" href="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/feed.xslt.xml"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-06-22T00:12:24+00:00</updated><id>https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Galaxy Training!</title><subtitle>A collection of tutorials generated and maintained by Galaxy Community Members across the world</subtitle><entry><title type="html">GTN Video Library 2.0: 107 hours of learning across 154 videos</title><link href="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/2024/06/14/gtn-video-library.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="GTN Video Library 2.0: 107 hours of learning across 154 videos" /><published>2024-06-14T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-06-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/2024/06/14/gtn-video-library</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/2024/06/14/gtn-video-library.html"><![CDATA[<p>Many GTN tutorials already have recordings. These recordings were made by members of the community for a variety of (online) training events.
Up until now, this video library were part of the <a href="https://gallantries.github.io/">Gallantries Project</a>.
We have now integrated this video library directly into the GTN, and made it even <strong>easier to add video recordings</strong> to GTN tutorials or slide decks! Just use a Google Form to submit your video recordings!</p>

<p>Want to record one of our tutorials? <strong>We welcome video recordings from everybody!</strong><sup id="fnref:1" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote" rel="footnote">1</a></sup></p>

<p>Please checkout out our FAQs with instructions for adding your own recordings:</p>

<p><a href="/training-material/faqs/gtn/recordings_add.html"><button type="button" class="btn btn-info">Submitting Recordings to the GTN</button></a></p>

<p><a href="/training-material/faqs/gtn/recordings_create.html"><button type="button" class="btn btn-info">Recording Tips &amp; Tricks</button></a></p>

<h2 id="what-this-means-for">What this means for…</h2>

<table class="table table-striped">
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th>Group</th>
      <th>What’s new?</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>Instructors</td>
      <td>Just fill out an updated Google Form and we’ll take care of the rest. The google form is now more easily discoverable, as are the recording instructions which provide a best practice guide for doing screen recordings of tutorials. We have updated documentation on recording best practices that are easy to follow.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Event Organisers &amp; Teachers</td>
      <td>Easily discover our large library of both human and automated video recordings to use in your training materials. All videos are licensed CC-BY so you can use them in your own training materials or even embed them in your course websites (Moodle, Blackboard, etc).</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>GTN Editors &amp; Maintainers</td>
      <td>When a recording is submitted, a pull request will be opened with the appropriate metadata in the correct location and an easy checklist to follow to make sure everyone’s video is processed efficiently with every step taken care of.</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<h2 id="video-library-10">Video Library 1.0</h2>

<p>This work is based on the work done during the <a href="/training-material/hall-of-fame/gallantries/" class="contributor-badge-inline contributor-gallantries">
  <img src="https://gallantries.github.io/assets/images/gallantries-logo.png" alt="Gallantries: Bridging Training Communities in Life Science, Environment and Health avatar" width="36" class="avatar" />
  Gallantries</a>
 project and the <a href="/training-material/news/2021/11/23/video-library.html">Video Library 1.0</a>. As that project ended, the features developed during that time have now been rolled into the GTN to ensure their long term sustainability</p>

<p>The number of videos and hours is slightly lower in the GTN version as we have not yet imported every recording, currently we are missing some recordings which are not directly associated with a GTN material (e.g. webinars).</p>

<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>They must be a recording of a GTN tutorial being taught. We are not accepting recordings of other training events at this time. <a href="#fnref:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>]]></content><author><name>Saskia Hiltemann, Helena Rasche</name></author><category term="news" /><category term="gtn" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Many GTN tutorials already have recordings. These recordings were made by members of the community for a variety of (online) training events. Up until now, this video library were part of the Gallantries Project. We have now integrated this video library directly into the GTN, and made it even easier to add video recordings to GTN tutorials or slide decks! Just use a Google Form to submit your video recordings!]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/assets/images/video-library.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/assets/images/video-library.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">From GTN Intern to Tutorial Author to Bioinformatician</title><link href="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/2024/06/13/from-gtn-intern-to-tutorial-author-to-bioinformatician.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="From GTN Intern to Tutorial Author to Bioinformatician" /><published>2024-06-13T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-06-13T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/2024/06/13/from-gtn-intern-to-tutorial-author-to-bioinformatician</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/2024/06/13/from-gtn-intern-to-tutorial-author-to-bioinformatician.html"><![CDATA[<p>With growing access and interest in sequencing data, Galaxy is a knight in shining armor for wet lab scientists hoping to analyze their own data. With long term intentions of increasing access to bioinformatic analyses, the Galaxy Training Network (GTN) creates a safe space where non-computer-scientists may analyze their own data and even learn to code: an invaluable skill in today’s scientific world. Galaxy introduced me to brand new skills as an undergraduate and ultimately changed the trajectory of my career. Here is my story as a biology undergraduate with no coding experience turned GTN contributor &amp;, eventually, coding bioinformatician: thanks to Galaxy.</p>

<p>My introduction to Galaxy came from Dr. Wendi Bacon of the Open University. Dr. Bacon has spearheaded efforts to expand upon the GTN’s currently available single-cell tools and tutorials. I was taken on as an intern in the fall of 2021 to support these efforts–mainly focused on the development of single-cell RNA sequencing (scRNA-seq) analysis tutorials using Seurat. Although I had officially become a bioinformatics intern, I still had little to no experience with coding and none with scRNA-seq data.</p>

<p>Dr. Bacon started me out kindly with introductory tutorials already available on the GTN while I learned what this data looks like and how to analyze it. While waiting for tools to become available, I began using RStudio and learned how to translate the Scanpy buttons tutorial into a Seurat RStudio one. This task proved to be more difficult than initially believed: me, with no coding experience, trying to translate wrapped Python tools into raw R code. After many months of trial and error, I drafted the first Seurat based tutorial hosted by the GTN. I quickly realized I had taught myself to code–or at the very least, learned to teach myself to code via pattern recognition and repetition.</p>

<p>The trajectory of my career thus far has been heavily driven by a love for bioinformatics that was founded thanks to Galaxy. I have since begun conducting research as a technician at the University of Utah (USA), and will soon begin a PhD program leveraging my computational skills and interests. I have spearheaded multiple scRNA-seq projects my current lab studying development of the diaphragm (an essential mammalian organ), a common birth defect associated with aberrant diaphragm development (CDH), and retinoic acid’s role in both. Leveraging what I learned via Galaxy, I am answering increasingly complex biological questions.</p>

<p>The GTN contributes to the scientific world something that is crucial for successful integration of bench and computational biology. The ability for scientists to produce and analyze their own datasets allows for more scientific hypotheses to be formed and questions to be answered. These facts have been integral to my success as a scientist and for that I am grateful for Galaxy, the GTN, and the community at large.</p>]]></content><author><name>Camila Goclowski</name></author><category term="news" /><category term="single-cell" /><category term="training" /><category term="education" /><category term="trajectory" /><category term="user" /><category term="contributor" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[With growing access and interest in sequencing data, Galaxy is a knight in shining armor for wet lab scientists hoping to analyze their own data. With long term intentions of increasing access to bioinformatic analyses, the Galaxy Training Network (GTN) creates a safe space where non-computer-scientists may analyze their own data and even learn to code: an invaluable skill in today’s scientific world. Galaxy introduced me to brand new skills as an undergraduate and ultimately changed the trajectory of my career. Here is my story as a biology undergraduate with no coding experience turned GTN contributor &amp;, eventually, coding bioinformatician: thanks to Galaxy.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Phylogenetics tutorial takes researchers back to basics!</title><link href="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/2024/06/13/phylogenetics-tutorial-takes-researchers-back-to-basics.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Phylogenetics tutorial takes researchers back to basics!" /><published>2024-06-13T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-06-13T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/2024/06/13/phylogenetics-tutorial-takes-researchers-back-to-basics</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/2024/06/13/phylogenetics-tutorial-takes-researchers-back-to-basics.html"><![CDATA[<p>A new Galaxy Training Network tutorial has been created to take researchers back to basics to uncover the principles of phylogenetics and how tree-building methods work. A longstanding collaboration between Professor Michael Charleston from the University of Tasmania and Australian BioCommons has delivered this self-guided tutorial featuring videos and hands-on exercises. To maximise its impact, the resource was tailored specifically to be shared globally via the Galaxy Training Network, and will form the basis of an upcoming live training workshop.</p>

<p>Using real-life data, tools available in Galaxy and SplitsTree, the tutorial demonstrates the principles behind a variety of methods used to estimate phylogenetic trees from aligned sequence data or distance data. With a conversational style Michael discusses why phylogenetics is important, unpicks phylogenetics terminology from the roots to the tips and explains concepts such as multiple sequence alignment, how alignments are used to build trees, and phylogenetic networks.</p>

<p>Try out the <a href="/training-material/topics/evolution/tutorials/abc_intro_phylo/tutorial.html">Phylogenetics: back to basics tutorial in the Galaxy Training Network</a>.</p>

<p>Read more about the collaboration and upcoming live workshop on the <a href="https://www.biocommons.org.au/news/phylo-gtn">BioCommons website</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name>Melissa Burke</name></author><category term="news" /><category term="Phylogenetics" /><category term="Tutorial" /><category term="GTN" /><category term="Australian BioCommons" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A new Galaxy Training Network tutorial has been created to take researchers back to basics to uncover the principles of phylogenetics and how tree-building methods work. A longstanding collaboration between Professor Michael Charleston from the University of Tasmania and Australian BioCommons has delivered this self-guided tutorial featuring videos and hands-on exercises. To maximise its impact, the resource was tailored specifically to be shared globally via the Galaxy Training Network, and will form the basis of an upcoming live training workshop.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/images/darwin_tree.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/images/darwin_tree.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Open Call for Trainers for the Galaxy Training Academy</title><link href="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/2024/06/11/GalaxyTrainingAcademy-Call-Contribution.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Open Call for Trainers for the Galaxy Training Academy" /><published>2024-06-11T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-06-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/2024/06/11/GalaxyTrainingAcademy-Call-Contribution</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/2024/06/11/GalaxyTrainingAcademy-Call-Contribution.html"><![CDATA[<p>We are happy to announce the Galaxy Training Academy 2024, a global online training event, where learners can get to know Galaxy and learn how to analyze data for various research topics.</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Dates</strong>: October 07-11, 2024</li>
  <li><strong>Location</strong>: Global online</li>
  <li><strong>Registration deadline</strong>: July the 12th</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="the-event">The event</h2>

<p>The event will provide a self-paced online learning experience for learners who would like to dive into the depths of Galaxy data analysis. The event is similar to the Smörgåsbord, but the program will be more structured. On Monday learners can get to know Galaxy and its tremendous functionality. Between Tuesday and Thursday, learners can choose from different Tracks that they are interested in. This can help learn to either get onboarded or understand fassates of one research area more in-depth. It is still up to the learnes to choose there program for the week but the track will give them guidance on what order will help to achieve their individual learning goals. In there self-paced learning endevers they will be supported via chat by us.</p>

<h3 id="initial-program">Initial Program:</h3>

<table class="table-striped">
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th>Day</th>
      <th>Program</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>Monday</td>
      <td>Galaxy Introduction</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Tuesday-Thursday   </td>
      <td>Different Tracks(*)</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Friday</td>
      <td>Choose from a variety of different topics </td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p>(*)<strong>Tracks</strong>: Proteomics, Assembly, Transcriptomics, Microbiome, Machine Learning, BY-COVID</p>

<h2 id="your-contribution">Your contribution</h2>

<p>We want to provide a high-quality learning experience and are seeking out for contributors, who will help to make this experience possible. We offer three distinct ways for you to contribute:</p>

<ol>
  <li><strong>Host Your Tutorial</strong>: Develop and share your own tutorial to enrich the learning experience.</li>
  <li><strong>Assist in existing Tutorial Setups</strong>: We can propose a tutorial or connect you with other contributors to set up an existing Tutorial.</li>
  <li><strong>Provide Event Support</strong>: Offer assistance by answering questions and guiding participants during the event.</li>
</ol>

<p>Even if you don’t have a tutorial in mind, your support in any of the above capacities is highly valued. Simply choose the second or third option, and we’ll connect you with fellow contributors eager for assistance.</p>

<p><strong>To ensure the highest quality of the tutorials you should do:</strong></p>
<ol>
  <li><strong>Review</strong> and update the GTN tutorial</li>
  <li><strong>Test</strong> the tutorial on at least 1 Galaxy instance</li>
  <li><strong>Check</strong> that the workflow is in sync with the written instructions</li>
  <li><strong>Record</strong> a video of yourself teaching the tutorial</li>
</ol>

<p>Are you interested? <a href="https://forms.gle/B554dNtN5HEuC5XY9">Register now</a></p>

<p>We leave the call open until July the 12th.</p>]]></content><author><name>Teresa Müller</name></author><category term="news" /><category term="gtn" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[We are happy to announce the Galaxy Training Academy 2024, a global online training event, where learners can get to know Galaxy and learn how to analyze data for various research topics.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Celebrating the Milestone: 400 Tutorials on the Galaxy Training Network!</title><link href="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/2024/06/06/400-tutorials-milestone.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Celebrating the Milestone: 400 Tutorials on the Galaxy Training Network!" /><published>2024-06-06T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-06-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/2024/06/06/400-tutorials-milestone</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/2024/06/06/400-tutorials-milestone.html"><![CDATA[<p>The Galaxy Training Network (GTN) has reached an exciting milestone: <strong>our 400th tutorial</strong>! This achievement is a testament to the dedication and hard work of our community of educators, researchers, and developers over the last 9 years.</p>

<p>The GTN was established to provide comprehensive and accessible training materials for users of the <a href="https://galaxyproject.org/">Galaxy</a>, a widely-used, open-source platform that empowers researchers worldwide to conduct data analysis. Over the years, the network has massively grown, both in content and community engagement, reflecting the dynamic nature of scientific research and the continuous need for up-to-date training resources.</p>

<p><a href="/training-material/news/images/2024-06-06-contributions.png" rel="noopener noreferrer"><img src="/training-material/news/images/2024-06-06-contributions.png" alt="2 graphs representing the increase over times of (left) Materials (Tutorials + Slides) and (right) Contributors to the Galaxy Training Network. each grow from ~50 in 2017 to ~500 and ~350 respectively, today. " width="2242" height="570" loading="lazy" /></a></p>

<h2 id="a-journey-of-knowledge-and-collaboration">A Journey of Knowledge and Collaboration</h2>

<p>From its inception, the GTN has been driven by the goal of making high-quality, user-friendly tutorials available to everyone. The diverse range of tutorials covers topics from basic Galaxy usage to advanced bioinformatics analyses, catering to both beginners and seasoned researchers.</p>

<p>This 400th tutorial represents more than just a number; it embodies the collaborative spirit and the shared pursuit of knowledge that defines the Galaxy community. Each tutorial was contributed by experts who not only have a deep understanding of their subject matter but also a passion for teaching and community building.</p>

<h2 id="highlights-of-our-tutorials">Highlights of Our Tutorials</h2>

<p>Our tutorials span a wide array of scientific domains and technical skills (30+ topics), including but not limited to:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Genomics</strong>: Explore the fundamentals of sequence analysis, variant calling, and genome assembly.</li>
  <li><strong>Proteomics</strong>: Dive into protein identification, quantification, and functional analysis.</li>
  <li><strong>Ecology</strong>: Learn to analyse Ecological data through Galaxy.</li>
  <li><strong>Machine Learning</strong>: Understand the integration of machine learning techniques in biological data analysis.</li>
  <li><strong>Data Visualization</strong>: Master the art of presenting your data in clear and informative ways.</li>
</ul>

<p>Each tutorial is designed to be interactive, with hands-on exercises that allow users to apply what they’ve learned in real-world scenarios. Moreover, the tutorials are continuously updated to incorporate the latest advancements and tools in the field.</p>

<h2 id="the-power-of-community">The Power of Community</h2>

<p>The GTN’s success is a direct result of the vibrant and collaborative Galaxy community. Contributors from around the globe share their expertise, review content, and provide feedback to ensure the tutorials remain accurate and relevant. This collective effort has created a rich repository of knowledge that is freely accessible to anyone, anywhere. <strong>We thank everyone who contributed!</strong></p>

<h2 id="looking-ahead">Looking Ahead</h2>

<p>As we celebrate this milestone, we remain committed to expanding and enhancing our training materials. We have recently expanded beyond Galaxy into Data Science and command line analyses, and we look forward to expanding to even more new life science topics going forward.</p>

<p>Here’s to the next 400 tutorials and beyond—together, we are advancing science and education, one tutorial at a time!</p>]]></content><author><name>Bérénice Batut, Helena Rasche, Saskia Hiltemann</name></author><category term="news" /><category term="gtn" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The Galaxy Training Network (GTN) has reached an exciting milestone: our 400th tutorial! This achievement is a testament to the dedication and hard work of our community of educators, researchers, and developers over the last 9 years.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/images/2024-06-06-400-tutorials.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/images/2024-06-06-400-tutorials.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">New Galaxy training: Building an amplicon sequence variant (ASV) table from 16S data using DADA2</title><link href="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/2024/06/06/dada2-tutorial.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="New Galaxy training: Building an amplicon sequence variant (ASV) table from 16S data using DADA2" /><published>2024-06-06T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-06-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/2024/06/06/dada2-tutorial</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/2024/06/06/dada2-tutorial.html"><![CDATA[<p>The GTN hosts its <a href="/training-material/news/2024/06/06/400-tutorials-milestone.html">400th tutorial</a>: <strong>Building an amplicon sequence variant (ASV) table from 16S data using DADA2</strong></p>

<p>The investigation of environmental microbial communities and microbiomes has been revolutionized by the development of high-throughput amplicon sequencing. In amplicon sequencing a particular genetic locus, for example the 16S rRNA gene (or a part of it) in bacteria, is amplified from DNA extracted from the community of interest, and then sequenced on a next-generation sequencing platform. This technique removes the need to culture microbes in order to detect their presence, and cost-effectively provides a deep census of a microbial community.</p>

<p>This new Galaxy training explores 16S amplicon data processing using <strong>DADA2</strong> and exploration using <strong>Phyloseq</strong>.</p>]]></content><author><name>Bérénice Batut</name></author><category term="news" /><category term="new tutorial" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The GTN hosts its 400th tutorial: Building an amplicon sequence variant (ASV) table from 16S data using DADA2]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Standards compliant™ training news via RSS/Atom</title><link href="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/2024/06/04/gtn-standards-rss.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Standards compliant™ training news via RSS/Atom" /><published>2024-06-04T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-06-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/2024/06/04/gtn-standards-rss</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/2024/06/04/gtn-standards-rss.html"><![CDATA[<!-- GTN:IGNORE:003 -->

<p>The GTN loves leveraging existing standards for both old and new purposes. One of our favourite standards that we adhere to is providing an RSS/Atom news feed for sharing news and events and updates!</p>

<p><strong>Update 2024 Jun 18</strong>: We’ve added a new home page for all of our feeds: <a href="/training-material/feeds/index.html">GTN feeds home</a></p>

<h2 id="why-rssatom">Why RSS/Atom?</h2>

<p>RSS feeds provide access to the latest news and updates from websites. They are a great way to keep up to date with your favourite websites without having to visit them every day, and without having to sign up for a mailing list or social media account. You can subscribe to feeds using a <a href="https://aboutfeeds.com/">feed reader</a>, which will automatically check for updates and display them for you.</p>

<p>There are some other benefits of RSS feeds however:</p>

<h3 id="privacy">Privacy</h3>

<p>Our feed subscriptions are completely private! We do not need a mailing list or any other personal information to send you updates. You can subscribe to our feed and receive updates without us knowing anything about you. You can subscribe or unsubscribe at any time.</p>

<h3 id="standards">Standards</h3>

<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Atom_(web_standard)">Atom feeds</a> (similar to the more well known RSS feeds) are a well-established standard (<a href="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/html/rfc4287">IETF RFC 4287</a>) for ‘news’ type feeds. This means that we can easily integrate with other systems that understand Atom feeds! Any feed reader you choose will be able to understand our feed.</p>

<p><a href="http://validator.w3.org/feed/check.cgi?url=http%3A//training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/feed.xml">
  <img src="/training-material/assets/images/valid-atom.png" alt="[Valid Atom 1.0]" title="Validate my Atom 1.0 feed" />
</a></p>

<h3 id="environmental-friendliness">Environmental Friendliness</h3>

<p>Feeds are small, lightweight, and easily cached by servers. Our feeds are generated at least once a day and cached aggressively with support for features like ETags and Last-Modified headers. This means that you can subscribe to our feed and receive updates without causing any additional load on our servers. Additionally checking if our feed is updated does not require any computation on our part! We just serve a static file to you.</p>

<h3 id="syndication">Syndication</h3>

<p>This is one of the <em>coolest</em> benefits of standard RSS feeds, we believe: how many other systems interoperate with them! For instance if you wanted to subscribe to GTN news in your Slack channel, you could use the existing <a href="https://slack.com/help/articles/218688467-Add-RSS-feeds-to-Slack">RSS integration</a> to do so without any additional coding or customisation required. Just run</p>

<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>/feed subscribe http://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/feed.xml
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>If you wanted to see the same news in your Matrix channel, you can use one of the <a href="https://gitlab.com/imbev/matrix-rss-bridge">RSS bridges</a> to do so. You’ll get notified of every new post!</p>

<p>We even use this feed to post our updates to the Galaxy Hub</p>

<h2 id="whats-in-a-feed">What’s in a feed?</h2>

<p>If you’ve never looked at our feed before, we recommend you do, <a href="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/feed.xml">it’s a bit fancier than the average RSS feed</a>! Each news item provides a short preview to let you decide if you’re interested in reading more. If you are, you can click through to the full post on our website.</p>

<h2 id="gtn-feeds">GTN Feeds</h2>

<p>We actually produce a large number of RSS feeds which can let you subscribe to topics you’re interested in:</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/feed.xml">News</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/events/feed.xml">Events</a></li>
</ul>

<p>We also produce per-topic feeds if you are just interested in a single topic and want to be informed about new tutorials or slides added to that topic:</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/topics/galaxy-interface/feed.xml">Galaxy Interface Updates</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/topics/single-cell/feed.xml">Single Cell Updates</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/topics/fair/feed.xml">Fair Training Updates</a></li>
</ul>

<p>These feeds are updated every time we add new content to the GTN, so you can be sure you’re always up to date! You can find their links on every tutorial page.</p>

<h2 id="more-feeds-in-the-future">More Feeds in the Future</h2>

<p>We’re exploring the possibility for ‘tag’ based feeds, where you can subscribe to anything added to our site with a given tag. Say you were interested in genome annotation, with a tag based feed you’d get to hear about any new tutorials, slides, events, FAQs, or news posts added to the GTN with that tag.</p>

<p>On top of that we’re considering producing a ‘daily digest’ feed and potentially a ‘weekly digest’ like we currently create manually for posting to our chat channels in matrix. This would give us a lot more flexibility in how to share our news and updates with you. Perhaps we would also create those digests for specific topics, so you could subscribe to a weekly digest of all new single cell tutorials, for example.</p>

<p>Would you use <a href="https://github.com/galaxyproject/training-material/discussions/4999">these features</a>? Let us know in <a href="https://github.com/galaxyproject/training-material/discussions/5000">the discussions</a>!</p>]]></content><author><name>Helena Rasche</name></author><category term="news" /><category term="gtn infrastructure" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Integrating the Galaxy Training Network into the Tool Form</title><link href="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/2024/06/04/tool-form-integration.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Integrating the Galaxy Training Network into the Tool Form" /><published>2024-06-04T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-06-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/2024/06/04/tool-form-integration</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/2024/06/04/tool-form-integration.html"><![CDATA[<p>For many tools in Galaxy, the GTN offers a variety of guides, practical examples, and help throughout it’s many tutorials.
Often times when using a tool, such information can be very useful, but hard to discover.</p>

<p>Galaxy’s new GTN Tool-Form integration helps with this, by connecting Galaxy to the GTN, and displaying all tutorials which make use of the tool you are currently using, directly inside to Tool Form!
This way it is easy to discover practical examples and guides for Tools, general and domain-specific.
The list of tutorials referencing a specific tool can either be viewed on the GTN, or browsed from within the Tool Form.</p>

<p>For an example check out the <a href="https://usegalaxy.eu/?tool_id=cat1">Concatenate Datasets tool</a> hosted on the EU Galaxy server.</p>

<p>If this section does not appear on your Galaxy server, there may be no tutorials available for the tool you are currently using, or this feature may not be enabled.</p>

<p>The GTN integration doesn’t need to use the official GTN. Configuration settings are available to allow it to link to an internal help site or wiki.</p>]]></content><author><name>Laila Los</name></author><category term="news" /><category term="gtn" /><category term="new feature" /><category term="already-on-hub" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[For many tools in Galaxy, the GTN offers a variety of guides, practical examples, and help throughout it’s many tutorials. Often times when using a tool, such information can be very useful, but hard to discover.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/images/2024-06-04-tool-form-integration.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/images/2024-06-04-tool-form-integration.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">All GTN training data are now automatically mirrored via Onedata</title><link href="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/2024/06/03/onedata.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="All GTN training data are now automatically mirrored via Onedata" /><published>2024-06-03T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-06-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/2024/06/03/onedata</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/2024/06/03/onedata.html"><![CDATA[<p>As part of the <a href="https://eurosciencegateway.eu/">EuroScienceGateway</a> and in cooperation with <a href="https://onedata.org">Onedata</a> and <a href="https://www.egi.eu/">EGI</a> we are providing all <a href="https://training.galaxyproject.org/">GTN</a> training data on a publicly accessible <a href="https://datahub.egi.eu/share/2697e33bd34f1870b0961414b8c77753chf583">cloud storage</a>.
Those training datasets are curated, small but meaningful for educational purposes and contain 1530 files with a total size of 170Gb.
An invaluable set of resources for everyone dealing with data science and training.
Please thank the more than <a href="/training-material/hall-of-fame.html">350 contributors to GTN</a>.</p>

<h2 id="what-does-this-mean-for-you">What does this mean for you?</h2>

<ul>
  <li>Teachers: if you’re a teacher contributing to the GTN, you can now be sure that the datasets you use in your materials are even more accessible and easier to use.</li>
  <li>GTN Users: When following training materials, it’ll now be easier to access those same datasets in new locations.</li>
  <li>Galaxy Admins: If you’re running a Galaxy server, you can now more easily integrate the GTN data into your server without taking up unnecessary storage space, and still making it available to all your users.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="accessing-gtn-data-in-the-cloud">Accessing GTN Data in the Cloud</h2>

<p>GTN training data is always accessible, annotated and linked for every tutorial. Usually, it’s stored in Zenodo, referenced via a DOI.
You can access all GTN training data using several methods:</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Onedata Share</strong> — access without authentication:</p>

    <p>a. Visit the <a href="https://datahub.egi.eu/share/2697e33bd34f1870b0961414b8c77753chf583">public share link</a>
    to browse and download the data via the Onedata Web UI.</p>

    <p>b. Use the public <a href="https://onedata.org/#/home/api/stable/onezone?anchor=operation/get_shared_data">REST API</a>
    to access the data; on the share page (see above) you will find ready-to-use <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">curl</code> examples by right-clicking on a file/directory and choosing the <strong>Information</strong> context menu.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Galaxy Server integration</strong>: access the data on the <a href="https://usegalaxy.eu/">European Galaxy server</a>. Go to the “Upload data” button, select “Choose remote files,” and navigate to the GTN repository.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Configure your own Galaxy server</strong>: to include the GTN data in your Galaxy server, use the following configuration:</p>

    <div class="language-yaml highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code> <span class="pi">-</span> <span class="na">type</span><span class="pi">:</span> <span class="s">onedata</span>
   <span class="na">id</span><span class="pi">:</span> <span class="s">gtn_public_onedata</span>
   <span class="na">label</span><span class="pi">:</span> <span class="s">GTN training data</span>
   <span class="na">doc</span><span class="pi">:</span> <span class="s">Training data from the Galaxy Training Network (powered by Onedata)</span>
   <span class="c1"># The following token is a public, read-only token that can be shared.</span>
   <span class="na">accessToken</span><span class="pi">:</span> <span class="s2">"</span><span class="s">MDAxY2xvY2F00aW9uIGRhdGFodWIuZWdpLmV1CjAwNmJpZGVudGlmaWVyIDIvbm1kL3Vzci00yNmI4ZTZiMDlkNDdjNGFkN2E3NTU00YzgzOGE3MjgyY2NoNTNhNS9hY3QvMGJiZmY1NWU4NDRiMWJjZGEwNmFlODViM2JmYmRhNjRjaDU00YjYKMDAxNmNpZCBkYXRhLnJlYWRvbmx5CjAwNDljaWQgZGF00YS5wYXRoID00gTHpaa1pUTTROMkl4WmpjMllXVmpOMlU00WWpreU5XWmtNV00ZpT1RKbU1ETXlZMmhoWTJReAowMDJmc2lnbmF00dXJlIIQvnXp01Oey02LnaNwEkFJAyArzhHN8SlXSYFsBbSkqdqCg"</span>
   <span class="na">onezoneDomain</span><span class="pi">:</span> <span class="s2">"</span><span class="s">datahub.egi.eu"</span>
</code></pre></div>    </div>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Onedata clients</strong> — access the data using the public read-only access token and
<a href="https://www.onedata.org/#/home/documentation/21.02/user-guide/oneclient.html">Oneclient</a> (local POSIX mount)
or <a href="https://onedata.org/#/home/documentation/21.02/user-guide/onedatafs.html">OnedataFS</a> 
(<a href="https://www.pyfilesystem.org/">PyFilesystem</a> interface), e.g.:</p>

    <div class="language-bash highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code> <span class="nb">mkdir</span> ~/oneclient
 oneclient <span class="se">\</span>
     <span class="nt">-H</span> plg-cyfronet-01.datahub.egi.eu <span class="se">\</span>
     <span class="nt">-t</span> MDAxY2xvY2F00aW9uIGRhdGFodWIuZWdpLmV1CjAwNmJpZGVudGlmaWVyIDIvbm1kL3Vzci00yNmI4ZTZiMDlkNDdjNGFkN2E3NTU00YzgzOGE3MjgyY2NoNTNhNS9hY3QvMGJiZmY1NWU4NDRiMWJjZGEwNmFlODViM2JmYmRhNjRjaDU00YjYKMDAxNmNpZCBkYXRhLnJlYWRvbmx5CjAwNDljaWQgZGF00YS5wYXRoID00gTHpaa1pUTTROMkl4WmpjMllXVmpOMlU00WWpreU5XWmtNV00ZpT1RKbU1ETXlZMmhoWTJReAowMDJmc2lnbmF00dXJlIIQvnXp01Oey02LnaNwEkFJAyArzhHN8SlXSYFsBbSkqdqCg <span class="se">\</span>
     ~/oneclient
 <span class="nb">ls</span> ~/oneclient/GTN<span class="se">\ </span>data
</code></pre></div>    </div>
  </li>
</ol>

<h2 id="what-is-the-gtn-downloader">What is the GTN Downloader?</h2>

<p><a href="https://github.com/usegalaxy-eu/gtn-downloader">GTN-Downloader</a> makes it easier for users to access and organize data from the <a href="https://training.galaxyproject.org/">Galaxy Training Network (GTN)</a>.
The GTN Downloader is a Python script that automates the download of data from GTN tutorials. It goes through the tutorials in the GTN repository, finds <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">data-library.yaml</code> files,
and creates a structured directory based on the tutorial names and file contents.</p>

<h3 id="key-features">Key Features:</h3>
<ul>
  <li><strong>Automated Data Download</strong>: The script finds <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">data-library.yaml</code> files in the GTN repository and downloads the associated data files.</li>
  <li><strong>Structured Organization</strong>: It creates directories based on the tutorial names and the information in the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">data-library.yaml</code> files, so the files are organized.</li>
  <li><strong>Download Summary</strong>: It generates a <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">download-summary.tsv</code> file, which includes metadata about the downloaded files, a download report (error, success, already downloaded), and the overall size of the files.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="seamless-integration-with-onedata">Seamless Integration with Onedata</h2>

<p>In addition to local downloads, the GTN Downloader can upload data to <a href="https://onedata.org">Onedata</a>, a distributed data management platform. This integration ensures that the latest GTN data is always available to users.</p>

<h3 id="automated-workflow-with-github-cicd">Automated Workflow with GitHub CI/CD:</h3>
<ul>
  <li><strong>Automated Workflow</strong>: A GitHub Actions workflow runs once a week on weekends to download the latest data from the GTN tutorials and upload it to Onedata.</li>
  <li><strong>Environment Setup</strong>: The workflow sets up necessary environment variables and installs dependencies, including Oneclient, the Onedata POSIX client.</li>
  <li><strong>Data Upload</strong>: After downloading the data, the workflow uploads it to Onedata, making it publicly accessible.</li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name>Polina Polunina</name></author><category term="news" /><category term="esg-wp4" /><category term="esg" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[As part of the EuroScienceGateway and in cooperation with Onedata and EGI we are providing all GTN training data on a publicly accessible cloud storage. Those training datasets are curated, small but meaningful for educational purposes and contain 1530 files with a total size of 170Gb. An invaluable set of resources for everyone dealing with data science and training. Please thank the more than 350 contributors to GTN.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/images/galaxy-data-upload.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/images/galaxy-data-upload.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Introducing GTN Event Pages</title><link href="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/2024/05/22/introducing-gtn-event-pages.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Introducing GTN Event Pages" /><published>2024-05-22T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-05-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/2024/05/22/introducing-gtn-event-pages</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/2024/05/22/introducing-gtn-event-pages.html"><![CDATA[<p>Are you organizing a training event using GTN materials? You can now add your event directly to the GTN!</p>

<p>View all upcoming and past events on the brand-new <a href="/training-material/events/index.html">GTN Events page</a>.</p>

<h2 id="what-you-will-get">What you will get</h2>

<ul>
  <li>Full featured event webpage complete with
    <ul>
      <li>Course overview</li>
      <li>Course handbook with your full program including links to all materials participants will need on the day</li>
      <li>Setup instructions for participants</li>
      <li>Instructor Zone page with handy links and tips for course organizers</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Your event is advertised on the GTN Event page</li>
  <li>We are happy to help announce your event on social media</li>
</ul>

<p>See <a href="/training-material/events/2024-04-01-example-event.html">this example event</a> to get an idea of what your event page could look like. Or check out one of the <a href="/training-material/events/2023-04-17-gat-gent.html">past events</a> to see the full capabilities of the event pages.</p>

<p>Our event pages are based on what we have learned from years of organizing and running training events. Additionally our experiences across the last three GTN Smörgåsbords significantly informed the event pages we present today, so we know they’re capable of everything you’ll want to do!</p>

<p><strong>Already have a course webpage?</strong> No problem! you can still add your event to the GTN and we will simply to your event webpage.</p>

<p><a href="/training-material/news/images/gtn-event-screenshot2.png" rel="noopener noreferrer"><img src="/training-material/news/images/gtn-event-screenshot2.png" alt="screenshot of a galaxy event page, showing the main page including a map, several sponsors, and more in an attractive tabbed layout. " width="1187" height="1668" loading="lazy" /></a></p>

<h2 id="adding-your-event">Adding your event</h2>

<p>GTN events are defined in similar was as learning pathways, just with some additional practical information (dates/times, location, registration etc)</p>

<p>Have a look at <a href="/training-material/faqs/gtn/gtn_event_create.html">this FAQ</a> for detailed instructions for adding an event.</p>

<p><a class="btn btn-primary" href="/training-material/faqs/gtn/gtn_event_create.html">Add your event now!</a></p>]]></content><author><name>Saskia Hiltemann</name></author><category term="news" /><category term="gtn infrastructure" /><category term="new feature" /><category term="events" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Are you organizing a training event using GTN materials? You can now add your event directly to the GTN!]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/images/gtn-event-screenshot.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/images/gtn-event-screenshot.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>