<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xml" href="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/feed.xslt.xml"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-06-04T16:16:06+00:00</updated><id>https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Galaxy Training!</title><subtitle>A collection of tutorials generated and maintained by Galaxy Community Members across the world</subtitle><entry><title type="html">All GTN training data are now automatically mirrored via Onedata</title><link href="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/2024/06/03/onedata.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="All GTN training data are now automatically mirrored via Onedata" /><published>2024-06-03T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-06-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/2024/06/03/onedata</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/2024/06/03/onedata.html"><![CDATA[<p>As part of the <a href="https://eurosciencegateway.eu/">EuroScienceGateway</a> and in cooperation with <a href="https://onedata.org">Onedata</a> and <a href="https://www.egi.eu/">EGI</a> we are providing all <a href="https://training.galaxyproject.org/">GTN</a> training data on a publicly accessible <a href="https://datahub.egi.eu/share/2697e33bd34f1870b0961414b8c77753chf583">cloud storage</a>.
Those training datasets are curated, small but meaningful for educational purposes and contain 1530 files with a total size of 170Gb.
An invaluable set of resources for everyone dealing with data science and training.
Please thank the more than <a href="/training-material/hall-of-fame.html">350 contributors to GTN</a>.</p>

<h2 id="what-does-this-mean-for-you">What does this mean for you?</h2>

<ul>
  <li>Teachers: if you’re a teacher contributing to the GTN, you can now be sure that the datasets you use in your materials are even more accessible and easier to use.</li>
  <li>GTN Users: When following training materials, it’ll now be easier to access those same datasets in new locations.</li>
  <li>Galaxy Admins: If you’re running a Galaxy server, you can now more easily integrate the GTN data into your server without taking up unnecessary storage space, and still making it available to all your users.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="accessing-gtn-data-in-the-cloud">Accessing GTN Data in the Cloud</h2>

<p>GTN training data is always accessible, annotated and linked for every tutorial. Usually, it’s stored in Zenodo, referenced via a DOI.
You can access all GTN training data using several methods:</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Onedata Share</strong> — access without authentication:</p>

    <p>a. Visit the <a href="https://datahub.egi.eu/share/2697e33bd34f1870b0961414b8c77753chf583">public share link</a>
    to browse and download the data via the Onedata Web UI.</p>

    <p>b. Use the public <a href="https://onedata.org/#/home/api/stable/onezone?anchor=operation/get_shared_data">REST API</a>
    to access the data; on the share page (see above) you will find ready-to-use <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">curl</code> examples by right-clicking on a file/directory and choosing the <strong>Information</strong> context menu.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Galaxy Server integration</strong>: access the data on the <a href="https://usegalaxy.eu/">European Galaxy server</a>. Go to the “Upload data” button, select “Choose remote files,” and navigate to the GTN repository.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Configure your own Galaxy server</strong>: to include the GTN data in your Galaxy server, use the following configuration:</p>

    <div class="language-yaml highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code> <span class="pi">-</span> <span class="na">type</span><span class="pi">:</span> <span class="s">onedata</span>
   <span class="na">id</span><span class="pi">:</span> <span class="s">gtn_public_onedata</span>
   <span class="na">label</span><span class="pi">:</span> <span class="s">GTN training data</span>
   <span class="na">doc</span><span class="pi">:</span> <span class="s">Training data from the Galaxy Training Network (powered by Onedata)</span>
   <span class="c1"># The following token is a public, read-only token that can be shared.</span>
   <span class="na">accessToken</span><span class="pi">:</span> <span class="s2">"</span><span class="s">MDAxY2xvY2F00aW9uIGRhdGFodWIuZWdpLmV1CjAwNmJpZGVudGlmaWVyIDIvbm1kL3Vzci00yNmI4ZTZiMDlkNDdjNGFkN2E3NTU00YzgzOGE3MjgyY2NoNTNhNS9hY3QvMGJiZmY1NWU4NDRiMWJjZGEwNmFlODViM2JmYmRhNjRjaDU00YjYKMDAxNmNpZCBkYXRhLnJlYWRvbmx5CjAwNDljaWQgZGF00YS5wYXRoID00gTHpaa1pUTTROMkl4WmpjMllXVmpOMlU00WWpreU5XWmtNV00ZpT1RKbU1ETXlZMmhoWTJReAowMDJmc2lnbmF00dXJlIIQvnXp01Oey02LnaNwEkFJAyArzhHN8SlXSYFsBbSkqdqCg"</span>
   <span class="na">onezoneDomain</span><span class="pi">:</span> <span class="s2">"</span><span class="s">datahub.egi.eu"</span>
</code></pre></div>    </div>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Onedata clients</strong> — access the data using the public read-only access token and
<a href="https://www.onedata.org/#/home/documentation/21.02/user-guide/oneclient.html">Oneclient</a> (local POSIX mount)
or <a href="https://onedata.org/#/home/documentation/21.02/user-guide/onedatafs.html">OnedataFS</a> 
(<a href="https://www.pyfilesystem.org/">PyFilesystem</a> interface), e.g.:</p>

    <div class="language-bash highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code> <span class="nb">mkdir</span> ~/oneclient
 oneclient <span class="se">\</span>
     <span class="nt">-H</span> plg-cyfronet-01.datahub.egi.eu <span class="se">\</span>
     <span class="nt">-t</span> MDAxY2xvY2F00aW9uIGRhdGFodWIuZWdpLmV1CjAwNmJpZGVudGlmaWVyIDIvbm1kL3Vzci00yNmI4ZTZiMDlkNDdjNGFkN2E3NTU00YzgzOGE3MjgyY2NoNTNhNS9hY3QvMGJiZmY1NWU4NDRiMWJjZGEwNmFlODViM2JmYmRhNjRjaDU00YjYKMDAxNmNpZCBkYXRhLnJlYWRvbmx5CjAwNDljaWQgZGF00YS5wYXRoID00gTHpaa1pUTTROMkl4WmpjMllXVmpOMlU00WWpreU5XWmtNV00ZpT1RKbU1ETXlZMmhoWTJReAowMDJmc2lnbmF00dXJlIIQvnXp01Oey02LnaNwEkFJAyArzhHN8SlXSYFsBbSkqdqCg <span class="se">\</span>
     ~/oneclient
 <span class="nb">ls</span> ~/oneclient/GTN<span class="se">\ </span>data
</code></pre></div>    </div>
  </li>
</ol>

<h2 id="what-is-the-gtn-downloader">What is the GTN Downloader?</h2>

<p><a href="https://github.com/usegalaxy-eu/gtn-downloader">GTN-Downloader</a> makes it easier for users to access and organize data from the <a href="https://training.galaxyproject.org/">Galaxy Training Network (GTN)</a>.
The GTN Downloader is a Python script that automates the download of data from GTN tutorials. It goes through the tutorials in the GTN repository, finds <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">data-library.yaml</code> files,
and creates a structured directory based on the tutorial names and file contents.</p>

<h3 id="key-features">Key Features:</h3>
<ul>
  <li><strong>Automated Data Download</strong>: The script finds <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">data-library.yaml</code> files in the GTN repository and downloads the associated data files.</li>
  <li><strong>Structured Organization</strong>: It creates directories based on the tutorial names and the information in the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">data-library.yaml</code> files, so the files are organized.</li>
  <li><strong>Download Summary</strong>: It generates a <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">download-summary.tsv</code> file, which includes metadata about the downloaded files, a download report (error, success, already downloaded), and the overall size of the files.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="seamless-integration-with-onedata">Seamless Integration with Onedata</h2>

<p>In addition to local downloads, the GTN Downloader can upload data to <a href="https://onedata.org">Onedata</a>, a distributed data management platform. This integration ensures that the latest GTN data is always available to users.</p>

<h3 id="automated-workflow-with-github-cicd">Automated Workflow with GitHub CI/CD:</h3>
<ul>
  <li><strong>Automated Workflow</strong>: A GitHub Actions workflow runs once a week on weekends to download the latest data from the GTN tutorials and upload it to Onedata.</li>
  <li><strong>Environment Setup</strong>: The workflow sets up necessary environment variables and installs dependencies, including Oneclient, the Onedata POSIX client.</li>
  <li><strong>Data Upload</strong>: After downloading the data, the workflow uploads it to Onedata, making it publicly accessible.</li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name>Polina Polunina</name></author><category term="news" /><category term="esg-wp4" /><category term="esg" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[As part of the EuroScienceGateway and in cooperation with Onedata and EGI we are providing all GTN training data on a publicly accessible cloud storage. Those training datasets are curated, small but meaningful for educational purposes and contain 1530 files with a total size of 170Gb. An invaluable set of resources for everyone dealing with data science and training. Please thank the more than 350 contributors to GTN.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/images/galaxy-data-upload.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/images/galaxy-data-upload.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Introducing GTN Event Pages</title><link href="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/2024/05/22/introducing-gtn-event-pages.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Introducing GTN Event Pages" /><published>2024-05-22T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-05-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/2024/05/22/introducing-gtn-event-pages</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/2024/05/22/introducing-gtn-event-pages.html"><![CDATA[<p>Are you organizing a training event using GTN materials? You can now add your event directly to the GTN!</p>

<p>View all upcoming and past events on the brand-new <a href="/training-material/events/index.html">GTN Events page</a>.</p>

<h2 id="what-you-will-get">What you will get</h2>

<ul>
  <li>Full featured event webpage complete with
    <ul>
      <li>Course overview</li>
      <li>Course handbook with your full program including links to all materials participants will need on the day</li>
      <li>Setup instructions for participants</li>
      <li>Instructor Zone page with handy links and tips for course organizers</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Your event is advertised on the GTN Event page</li>
  <li>We are happy to help announce your event on social media</li>
</ul>

<p>See <a href="/training-material/events/2024-04-01-example-event.html">this example event</a> to get an idea of what your event page could look like. Or check out one of the <a href="/training-material/events/2023-04-17-gat-gent.html">past events</a> to see the full capabilities of the event pages.</p>

<p>Our event pages are based on what we have learned from years of organizing and running training events. Additionally our experiences across the last three GTN Smörgåsbords significantly informed the event pages we present today, so we know they’re capable of everything you’ll want to do!</p>

<p><strong>Already have a course webpage?</strong> No problem! you can still add your event to the GTN and we will simply to your event webpage.</p>

<p><a href="/training-material/news/images/gtn-event-screenshot2.png" rel="noopener noreferrer"><img src="/training-material/news/images/gtn-event-screenshot2.png" alt="screenshot of a galaxy event page, showing the main page including a map, several sponsors, and more in an attractive tabbed layout. " width="1187" height="1668" loading="lazy" /></a></p>

<h2 id="adding-your-event">Adding your event</h2>

<p>GTN events are defined in similar was as learning pathways, just with some additional practical information (dates/times, location, registration etc)</p>

<p>Have a look at <a href="/training-material/faqs/gtn/gtn_event_create.html">this FAQ</a> for detailed instructions for adding an event.</p>

<p><a class="btn btn-primary" href="/training-material/faqs/gtn/gtn_event_create.html">Add your event now!</a></p>]]></content><author><name>Saskia Hiltemann</name></author><category term="news" /><category term="gtn infrastructure" /><category term="new feature" /><category term="events" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Are you organizing a training event using GTN materials? You can now add your event directly to the GTN!]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/images/gtn-event-screenshot.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/images/gtn-event-screenshot.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Open Galaxy Position at Galaxy Europe Team, University of Freiburg</title><link href="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/2024/05/15/galaxy-europe-freiburg-job.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Open Galaxy Position at Galaxy Europe Team, University of Freiburg" /><published>2024-05-15T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-05-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/2024/05/15/galaxy-europe-freiburg-job</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/2024/05/15/galaxy-europe-freiburg-job.html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="description">Description</h1>

<p>The Department of Computer Science is opening a position for a <a href="https://uni-freiburg.de/universitaet/jobs/00003737/">Systems Engineer / DevOps Engineer (m/f/d)</a>, bridging development and operations functions within one of the most popular and well-​established data analysis platforms for life science. The engineer will be responsible for implementing, supporting, and documenting several large-​scale application systems. This role includes but is not limited to, the installation, modification, testing, and upgrades of applications, operating systems, file systems, hardware, and cloud environments. The work will be carried out together with other administrators. </p>

<h2 id="who-we-are">Who we are</h2>

<p>The European Galaxy team is a core group within the worldwide <a href="https://galaxyproject.org/">Galaxy</a> project. We are an open, passionate, and supportive research group at the University of Freiburg highly involved in many software projects related to the global Galaxy community, including leading the <a href="https://bioconda.github.io/">Bioconda</a> and <a href="https://biocontainers.pro/">BioContainers</a> projects and developing state-​of-the-art computational workﬂows for genomics, metagenomics, transcriptomics, and pharmacogenomics data.</p>

<p>Based in Freiburg, <a href="https://usegalaxy.eu/">usegalaxy.eu</a> is the science gateway, providing an open-​access computational infrastructure for accessing and running a vast catalog of data resources, tools, and workflows. It is used by nearly 100,000 users worldwide.</p>

<h2 id="your-opportunities">Your opportunities</h2>

<p>This position will allow the postholder to interact with an interdisciplinary bioinformatics, data science, and software development team, working with cutting-​edge cloud infrastructure across Europe and engaged in advanced topics such as <a href="https://pulsar-network.readthedocs.io/en/latest/">distributed heterogeneous computing</a>, encrypted data processing, or smart scheduling of jobs across federated resources. </p>

<h2 id="your-tasks">Your Tasks</h2>

<ul>
  <li>Development &amp; maintenance of the Galaxy server and related infrastructure, e.g., TIaaS (Training Infrastructure as a Service), Pulsar-​Network, and the Beacon Service</li>
  <li>Work within the team of Admins to design and improve developed software and deployment pipelines</li>
  <li>Conceptualization of update procedures and software integrations in the running system</li>
  <li>Implementing and maintaining best security practices and adhering to our information security policies and industry standards</li>
  <li>Staying current with industry trends and emerging technologies, e.g., virtualization and infrastructure technologies, automatization, and CI/CD pipelines</li>
  <li>Proactively identifying opportunities to enhance the Galaxy Europe instance as well as general deployment guides for other Galaxy instances</li>
  <li>Integrating infrastructural components like various storage systems and special-​purpose computation nodes containing accelerators like GPUs</li>
  <li>Community support and training
    <ul>
      <li>Development of documentation and training material for Galaxy admins and automation workflows</li>
      <li>support of services administrators</li>
      <li>give workshops and train other administrators in live sessions</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<h2 id="your-profile">Your Profile</h2>

<p>We are looking for a dedicated and motivated team player with strong communication skills and a good command of the English language.</p>

<p>The successful applicant will be an expert Linux system administrator with proficient knowledge of Python, Git, and SQL databases and a Bachelor or Master in Informatics or equal qualification. He/she is an analytical thinker, problem-​solver and reliable, with a strong desire to learn and collaborate with the team.</p>

<p>Additional skills that are advantageous:</p>

<ul>
  <li>several years experience</li>
  <li>Experience building containerized applications</li>
  <li>Experience configuring continuous integration and continuous delivery (CI/CD) systems</li>
  <li>Proficiency using configuration management tools (Terraform, Ansible)</li>
  <li>Familiarity with cloud technologies (e.g. OpenStack)</li>
  <li>Experience in high-​performance computing environments</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="what-we-offer">What we offer</h2>

<p>Located in a region that connects Germany, France, and Switzerland, our institute offers an international research environment with outstanding infrastructure facilities and a positive working atmosphere that places a high value on work-​life balance.</p>

<ul>
  <li>A team of admins to work with</li>
  <li>Professional training and development opportunities</li>
  <li>Challenging tasks in European-​wide distributed projects in a modern working environment</li>
  <li>Flexible working hours and trust-​based working time</li>
  <li>30 days holiday a year</li>
  <li>Reduced-​cost public transport within the local area</li>
  <li>Family-​friendly offers (affiliated daycare center at the institute, family service)</li>
  <li>This position is open immediately and funded for two years, with the possibility of extension. The salary will be determined in accordance with TV-L up to E13 if the personal and collective bargaining requirements are met.</li>
</ul>

<p>More information about the European Galaxy project is available at <a href="https://galaxyproject.eu/">https://galaxyproject.eu</a>.</p>

<h2 id="ready-to-join-our-team">Ready to join our team?</h2>

<p>Please submit your complete application documents, including a 1-​page motivation summary, CV and contact details.</p>

<p>We are particularly pleased to receive applications from women for the position advertised here.</p>

<h1 id="application">Application</h1>

<p>Please send your application in English including supporting documents mentioned above citing the reference number 00003737, <strong>by June 10th 2024 at the latest</strong>. Please send your application to the following address in written or electronic form:</p>

<blockquote class="quote">
  <p>University of Freiburg<br />
Institut für Informatik, Bioinformatik<br />
Dr. Björn Grüning<br />
Head of Freiburg Galaxy Team<br />
Georges-​Köhler-Allee 106<br />
79110 Freiburg<br />
Germany<br />
Email: <a href="mailto:bioinf-​jobs@informatik.uni-​freiburg.de">bioinf-​jobs@informatik.uni-​freiburg.de</a></p>
</blockquote>

<p>For further information, please contact Dr. Anika Erxleben-​Eggenhofer on the phone number +49 761 203-​54130 or E-​Mail erxleben@informatik.uni-​freiburg.de.</p>

<h1 id="general-and-legal-remarks-privacy">General and legal remarks, privacy</h1>

<p>Full-​time positions may generally be split up into two or more part-​time positions, provided that there are no formal or legal barriers. Candidates are selected in accordance with the provisions of the AGG (Allgemeines Gleichbehandlungsgesetz - German General Equal Treatment Act).
Applicants with disabilities (Schwerbehinderte Menschen) will be given preferential consideration in case of equal qualification.
The department offering the position is liable for the content of this job posting. Textual errors do not constitute a basis for any claims or rights. The relevant human resources department has sole responsibility for all legal transactions made within the context of the selection and hiring process.
Please note that breaches in privacy and unauthorized access by third parties cannot be excluded in communication by unencrypted email.</p>

<p><a href="https://uni-freiburg.de/en/data-protection-applications/">Privacy Policy Scientific Employment</a></p>

<p>The original jopb posting on the website of the University of Freiburg can be <a href="https://uni-freiburg.de/universitaet/jobs/00003737/">found here</a></p>]]></content><author><name>Björn Grüning, Anika Erxleben, Sebastian Schaaf</name></author><category term="news" /><category term="jobs" /><category term="freiburg" /><category term="eu" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Description]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Perfectly FAIR Training!</title><link href="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/2024/05/13/fair.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Perfectly FAIR Training!" /><published>2024-05-13T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-05-13T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/2024/05/13/fair</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/2024/05/13/fair.html"><![CDATA[<p>We are happy to report that over the years of our fruitful collaboration with ELIXIR TeSS, all GTN materials should receive a perfect score on the <a href="https://fair-checker.france-bioinformatique.fr/check">FAIR-Checker</a>.</p>

<p>This achievement is a reflection of our long standing and ongoing commitment to ensuring all of the materials you share with others via the GTN are automatically FAIR: Findable, Accessible, Interoperable, and Reusable. Of course the GTN goes further meeting criteria for FAIR/O, as all of our resources are shared with the community under an Open License.</p>

<h2 id="why-the-gtn">Why the GTN?</h2>

<p>Amongst other competitors in the bioinformatics training material repository space the GTN is unique, we are the only one (which we’re aware of!) receiving a perfect score on the FAIR-Checker.</p>

<figure id="figure-1" style="max-width: 90%;"><img src="/training-material/news/images/FAIR-Checker-others.png" alt="two more radar plots, each receive approximately half the score. a few have axes they they are perfect on, but no one is perfect on all axes, unlike us." width="939" height="425" loading="lazy" /><a target="_blank" href="/training-material/news/images/FAIR-Checker-others.png" rel="noopener noreferrer"><small>Open image in new tab</small></a><br /><br /><figcaption><span class="figcaption-prefix"><strong>Figure 1</strong>:</span> Other platforms are still working towards FAIRness</figcaption></figure>

<h2 id="for-tutorial-authors">For Tutorial Authors</h2>

<p>We have made <em>no new requirements</em> for tutorial authors, simply by contributing a tutorial to the GTN which passes our linting, you can be sure it meets all relevant FAIR criteria due to our infrastructure and automation.</p>

<h2 id="for-trainers">For Trainers</h2>

<p>If you’re a trainer, you can be confident that all GTN materials you use in your training are FAIR. Please let your funders know you are meeting these criteria as well!</p>]]></content><author><name>Helena Rasche</name></author><category term="news" /><category term="gtn infrastructure" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[We are happy to report that over the years of our fruitful collaboration with ELIXIR TeSS, all GTN materials should receive a perfect score on the FAIR-Checker.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/images/FAIR-Checker-us.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/images/FAIR-Checker-us.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Open Galaxy Positions at Melbourne Bioinformatics</title><link href="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/2024/04/24/galaxy-australia-jobs.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Open Galaxy Positions at Melbourne Bioinformatics" /><published>2024-04-24T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-04-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/2024/04/24/galaxy-australia-jobs</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/2024/04/24/galaxy-australia-jobs.html"><![CDATA[<p>Melbourne Bioinformatics is expanding their team and recruiting three new roles to work on bioinformatics training, outreach, and research.</p>

<p>All three roles are full-time, continuing positions based at the University of Melbourne’s Parkville campus. Applications close <strong>15 May 2024</strong>. For more information, including application instructions, follow the links below.</p>

<p><strong>Please note</strong>: Unfortunately, <strong>visa sponsorship is not available</strong> for these positions. This role requires current valid work rights for Australia.</p>

<h2 id="senior-bioinformatician-bioinformatics-training-level-c">Senior Bioinformatician, Bioinformatics Training (Level C)</h2>

<p>This role will lead our training operations, overseeing a team of trainers and contributing to the development and delivery of bioinformatics content. This involves creating new training materials, delivering workshops, and establishing an online repository for easy access to resources. The Senior Bioinformatician will collaborate with external partners to enhance expertise and align training with national initiatives, ensuring content is comprehensive and of high quality. They will provide strategic oversight to ensure training targets are met effectively and efficiently.</p>

<p><a href="https://jobs.unimelb.edu.au/en/job/916660/senior-bioinformatician-bioinformatics-training">More information</a></p>

<h2 id="bioinformatician---galaxy-outreach-specialist-level-b">Bioinformatician - Galaxy Outreach Specialist (Level B)</h2>

<p>This role focuses on supporting life science researchers in utilising Galaxy Australia within the Parkville Precinct. This involves developing and delivering training materials, publicising Galaxy Australia, collaborating with researchers to develop workflows, and contributing to building the Galaxy Australia toolshed. The incumbent will work closely with Precinct stakeholders, national colleagues, and the broader Galaxy community to ensure effective utilisation of digital infrastructure and to facilitate research advancements in the life sciences.</p>

<p><a href="https://jobs.unimelb.edu.au/en/job/916668/bioinformatician-galaxy-outreach-specialist">More information</a></p>

<h2 id="bioinformatician-melbourne-bioinformatics-level-b">Bioinformatician, Melbourne Bioinformatics (Level B)</h2>

<p>This role offers a dynamic opportunity for a skilled bioinformatician to immerse themselves in the evolving landscape of life science research. In addition to contributing to high-impact research projects and collaborating with experts across various disciplines, the role involves a significant emphasis on teaching, training, and capacity-building within the bioinformatics field.</p>

<p><a href="https://jobs.unimelb.edu.au/en/job/916658/bioinformatician-melbourne-bioinformatics">More information</a></p>]]></content><author><name>Melissa Burke</name></author><category term="news" /><category term="jobs" /><category term="australia" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Melbourne Bioinformatics is expanding their team and recruiting three new roles to work on bioinformatics training, outreach, and research.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Learn to use MINERVA Platform’s COVID-19 Disease Map with Galaxy</title><link href="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/2024/03/28/by-covid-pathways.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Learn to use MINERVA Platform’s COVID-19 Disease Map with Galaxy" /><published>2024-03-28T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-03-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/2024/03/28/by-covid-pathways</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/2024/03/28/by-covid-pathways.html"><![CDATA[<p>As part of the work of <a href="https://by-covid.org/">BeYond COVID</a>, we have developed a new integration between the <a href="https://covid19map.elixir-luxembourg.org/minerva/">MINERVA Platform</a>’s COVID-19 Disease Map and Galaxy! Datasets created within Galaxy can now be seamlessly visualized in the MINERVA Platform, allowing you to explore your data in the context of the COVID-19 Disease Map.</p>

<p>This work generated a number of brand new WorkflowHub Workflows, which can now be launched more easily than ever in the GTN:</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <!--SNIPPET-->
    <div class="show-when-galaxy-proxy-active"> <span class="workflow" data-workflow="https://workflowhub.eu/ga4gh/trs/v2/tools/688/versions/1">Launch <strong>mRNA-Seq BY-COVID Pipeline: Counts</strong> <i class="fas fa-share-alt" aria-hidden="true"></i></span> (<a href="https://workflowhub.eu/workflows/688?version=1">View on WorkflowHub</a>) </div>
    <div class="hide-when-galaxy-proxy-active"> <a href="https://my.galaxy.training/?path=/workflows/trs_import%3ftrs_server=workflowhub.eu%26run_form=true%26trs_id=688%26trs_version=1">Launch <strong>mRNA-Seq BY-COVID Pipeline: Counts</strong> <i class="fas fa-share-alt" aria-hidden="true"></i></a> (<a href="https://workflowhub.eu/workflows/688?version=1">View on WorkflowHub</a>) </div>
    <p><!--END_SNIPPET--></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <!--SNIPPET-->
    <div class="show-when-galaxy-proxy-active"> <span class="workflow" data-workflow="https://workflowhub.eu/ga4gh/trs/v2/tools/689/versions/1">Launch <strong>mRNA-Seq BY-COVID Pipeline: Analysis</strong> <i class="fas fa-share-alt" aria-hidden="true"></i></span> (<a href="https://workflowhub.eu/workflows/689?version=1">View on WorkflowHub</a>) </div>
    <div class="hide-when-galaxy-proxy-active"> <a href="https://my.galaxy.training/?path=/workflows/trs_import%3ftrs_server=workflowhub.eu%26run_form=true%26trs_id=689%26trs_version=1">Launch <strong>mRNA-Seq BY-COVID Pipeline: Analysis</strong> <i class="fas fa-share-alt" aria-hidden="true"></i></a> (<a href="https://workflowhub.eu/workflows/689?version=1">View on WorkflowHub</a>) </div>
    <p><!--END_SNIPPET--></p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>And a few new GTN features like the ability to embed a workflow visualisation directly into a tutorial.
Go check it out!</p>]]></content><author><name>Helena Rasche, Marek Ostaszewski</name></author><category term="news" /><category term="by-covid" /><category term="pathways" /><category term="minerva" /><category term="gtn infrastructure" /><category term="new feature" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[As part of the work of BeYond COVID, we have developed a new integration between the MINERVA Platform’s COVID-19 Disease Map and Galaxy! Datasets created within Galaxy can now be seamlessly visualized in the MINERVA Platform, allowing you to explore your data in the context of the COVID-19 Disease Map.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/topics/transcriptomics/tutorials/minerva-pathways/images/4.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/topics/transcriptomics/tutorials/minerva-pathways/images/4.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">New Learning Pathway for FAIR Data Management developed by ELIXIR-UK Data Stewardship Fellows and Experts</title><link href="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/2024/03/26/FAIR-pointers.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="New Learning Pathway for FAIR Data Management developed by ELIXIR-UK Data Stewardship Fellows and Experts" /><published>2024-03-26T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-03-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/2024/03/26/FAIR-pointers</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/2024/03/26/FAIR-pointers.html"><![CDATA[<p>ELIXIR-UK’s Data Stewardship Fellowship is excited to announce a new learning pathway focused on FAIR Data Management! This program equips researchers and research support staff with the skills to effectively manage their research data.</p>

<p>By following FAIR principles, you ensure your data is discoverable by others, can be easily integrated with other datasets, and is readily available for future research. <strong>Together, let’s make FAIR data management a standard practice in research!</strong></p>

<p>You can find out more about the new lessons on the <a href="http://fellowship.elixiruknode.org/">ELIXIR-UK Fellowship site</a> and its <a href="https://fellowship.elixiruknode.org/training_materials/">recommended resources page</a>.</p>

<figure id="figure-1" style="max-width: 90%;"><img src="/training-material/news/images/2024-03-26-FAIR-pathway.png" alt="Picture of the training pathway form the GTN. " width="2440" height="1428" loading="lazy" /><a target="_blank" href="/training-material/news/images/2024-03-26-FAIR-pathway.png" rel="noopener noreferrer"><small>Open image in new tab</small></a><br /><br /><figcaption><span class="figcaption-prefix"><strong>Figure 1</strong>:</span> The FAIR Training Pathway on GTN for the FAIR Data Management and FAIR Pointers modules</figcaption></figure>]]></content><author><name>Katarzyna Kamieniecka, Khaled Jum&apos;ah, Krzysztof Poterlowicz</name></author><category term="news" /><category term="fair" /><category term="dmp" /><category term="data stewardship" /><category term="data management" /><category term="new learning pathway" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[ELIXIR-UK’s Data Stewardship Fellowship is excited to announce a new learning pathway focused on FAIR Data Management! This program equips researchers and research support staff with the skills to effectively manage their research data.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/shared/images/dash.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/shared/images/dash.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Cool URLs Don’t Change, GTN URLs don’t either.</title><link href="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/2024/03/18/url-persistence.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Cool URLs Don’t Change, GTN URLs don’t either." /><published>2024-03-18T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-03-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/2024/03/18/url-persistence</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/2024/03/18/url-persistence.html"><![CDATA[<p>At the Galaxy Training Network we are <em>really</em> committed to ensuring our training materials are <a href="/training-material/faqs/gtn/fair_training.html">Findable, Accessible, Interoperable, and Reusable</a>.
This means that we want to make sure that the URLs to our training materials are persistent and don’t change.
The GTN wants you to be able to rely on our URLs once you’ve added them to a poster or training material, without having to worry about them breaking in the future.</p>

<p>For a long time we relied on contributors ensuring that when files are merged, we add appropriate redirects to each moved file, however this isn’t a very reliable system.
We’d recently also introduced <a href="/training-material/news/2023/04/19/shortlinks.html">Persistent URLs (PURLs) to our lessons as well</a> but that only helps our users going forward, it doesn’t ensure we are meeting our earlier commitments.</p>

<p>So now we’ve added a new test to each GTN merge that checks URLs from the last 3 years to ensure that they are <em>all</em> still working.
If they aren’t, the merge will fail and the contributor will need to fix the URLs before the changes can be accepted.</p>

<p>We’ll be expanding how far back we check URLs in the future, but for now, this will help us ensure that our URLs are completely persistent!</p>

<p>By implementing this we discovered only 50 pages (out of ~5.3k GTN pages) that had been moved without proper redirections, and we’ve fixed them all!</p>]]></content><author><name>Helena Rasche</name></author><category term="news" /><category term="gtn infrastructure" /><category term="new feature" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[At the Galaxy Training Network we are really committed to ensuring our training materials are Findable, Accessible, Interoperable, and Reusable. This means that we want to make sure that the URLs to our training materials are persistent and don’t change. The GTN wants you to be able to rely on our URLs once you’ve added them to a poster or training material, without having to worry about them breaking in the future.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Lost in a topic? Try a Learning Pathway!</title><link href="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/2024/03/04/gtn-learning-path-highlights.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Lost in a topic? Try a Learning Pathway!" /><published>2024-03-04T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-03-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/2024/03/04/gtn-learning-path-highlights</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/2024/03/04/gtn-learning-path-highlights.html"><![CDATA[<p>We know the GTN has a <em>lot</em> of learning materials (<a href="/training-material/stats/index.html">400 and counting!</a>) which can make it quite difficult to figure out where to start in some topics.</p>

<p>In order to make it easier for you to find your way, we have started highlighting a number of our <strong>Learning Paths</strong> which are like guided tours through the GTN’s content. They are designed to help you learn a topic from start to finish, and are a great way to get a comprehensive understanding of a topic.</p>

<p>Check them out now!</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="/training-material/topics/single-cell/index.html">Single Cell</a></li>
  <li><a href="/training-material/topics/microbiome/index.html">Microbiome</a></li>
  <li><a href="/training-material/topics/admin/index.html">Admin Training</a></li>
</ul>

<p>👩‍🏫 for GTN topic maintainers, if you’d like to either create a learning path for your topic, or have an existing one highlighted, please get in touch with us in Matrix!</p>]]></content><author><name>Helena Rasche, Bérénice Batut</name></author><category term="news" /><category term="gtn infrastructure" /><category term="new feature" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[We know the GTN has a lot of learning materials (400 and counting!) which can make it quite difficult to figure out where to start in some topics.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">GTN ❤️ GMOD</title><link href="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/2024/02/29/new-gmod-topic.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="GTN ❤️ GMOD" /><published>2024-02-29T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-02-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/2024/02/29/new-gmod-topic</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/2024/02/29/new-gmod-topic.html"><![CDATA[<p>Building upon the work previously done for the <a href="/training-material/news/2023/01/23/new-covid19-topic.html">SARS-Cov-2 Topic</a> we have further expanded the ‘tag based topics’ to support a new GMOD topic.</p>

<h1 id="generic-model-organism-database">Generic Model Organism Database</h1>

<blockquote class="quote" cite="http://gmod.org/wiki/Main_Page">
  <p>the Generic Model Organism Database (GMOD) project, a collection of open source software tools for managing, visualising, storing, and disseminating genetic and genomic data.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Galaxy Project itself has long been a GMOD component, but you’ll recognise some other familiar faces there as well, if you are interested in Genome Annotation. JBrowse, used throughout the GTN in a number of tutorials to render genomic data, and Apollo are both members that you’ll find tutorials for within the GTN.</p>

<h2 id="current-state">Current State</h2>

<p>As such we’ve created a new topic to help aggregate all of the GMOD related material together. This currently includes tutorials on the use of <a href="/training-material/topics/gmod/#st-jbrowse1">JBrowse</a>, <a href="/training-material/topics/gmod/#st-apollo2">Apollo</a>, <a href="/training-material/topics/gmod/#st-intermine">InterMine</a>, and <a href="/training-material/topics/gmod/#st-maker">MAKER</a>!</p>

<p>For teachers, tag based topics now support a second level of organisation, in ‘subtopics’. We’ve used that to add a new topic, using subtopics to organise each GMOD component.</p>

<h2 id="future">Future</h2>

<p>For now the topic includes all GTN tutorials which use a GMOD component (that isn’t galaxy), all of these tutorials generally also include Galaxy based steps. In the future we may expand this to include tutorials for other GMOD components which don’t necessary interface with Galaxy. <a href="/training-material/hall-of-fame/hexylena/" class="contributor-badge-inline contributor-hexylena">
  <img src="https://avatars.githubusercontent.com/hexylena?s=36" alt="Helena Rasche avatar" width="36" class="avatar" />
  Helena Rasche</a>
 has some ideas about a Chado tutorial using the new <a href="https://github.com/electric-sql/pglite"><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">pglite</code></a> project, and perhaps <a href="/training-material/hall-of-fame/abretaud/" class="contributor-badge-inline contributor-abretaud">
  <img src="https://avatars.githubusercontent.com/abretaud?s=36" alt="Anthony Bretaudeau avatar" width="36" class="avatar" />
  Anthony Bretaudeau</a>
 will contribute a Tripal tutorial!</p>]]></content><author><name>Helena Rasche, Anthony Bretaudeau</name></author><category term="news" /><category term="new topic" /><category term="new feature" /><category term="genome annotation" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Building upon the work previously done for the SARS-Cov-2 Topic we have further expanded the ‘tag based topics’ to support a new GMOD topic.]]></summary></entry></feed>