<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xml" href="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/feed.xslt.xml"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-02-15T09:20:47+00:00</updated><id>https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Galaxy Training!</title><subtitle>A collection of tutorials generated and maintained by Galaxy Community Members across the world</subtitle><entry><title type="html">🪐📲 Hosting Galaxy at the Edge: Directly in Your Pocket!</title><link href="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/2024/01/31/postmarketos.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="🪐📲 Hosting Galaxy at the Edge: Directly in Your Pocket!" /><published>2024-01-31T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-01-31T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/2024/01/31/postmarketos</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/2024/01/31/postmarketos.html"><![CDATA[<p>Hey Galaxy admins! Have you ever wanted to administer your own instance from
the luxury of your pocket?</p>

<p>Now you can, with <strong>Galaxy In Your Pocket™!</strong></p>

<h2 id="why">Why?</h2>

<p>Run your instance without having to worry about the usual concerns: a
noisy server, too many cables, bad internet, or just a plain
unwillingness to spend time away from a screen.</p>

<p>Having <em>Galaxy In Your Pocket™</em>, you can run and administer your own
instance all from the same portable device that you use to ignore your
loved ones with!</p>

<h2 id="how">How?</h2>

<p>With <a href="https://gitlab.com/-/snippets/3644481">just a few steps</a>, you
can have Galaxy running on a mobile ARM device of your own.</p>

<figure id="figure-1" style="max-width: 90%;"><img src="/training-material/news/images/2024-01-31-postmarket-phone.jpg" alt="Galaxy running on an Alcatel Idol 347. " width="1816" height="1435" loading="lazy" /><a target="_blank" href="/training-material/news/images/2024-01-31-postmarket-phone.jpg" rel="noopener noreferrer"><small>Open image in new tab</small></a><br /><br /><figcaption><span class="figcaption-prefix"><strong>Figure 1</strong>:</span> Galaxy running on an Alcatel Idol 347</figcaption></figure>

<p>Above is an image of Galaxy running within
<a href="https://wiki.postmarketos.org/wiki/Phosh">Phosh UI</a> in <em>PostmarketOS</em> on an old
<a href="https://wiki.postmarketos.org/wiki/Alcatel_Idol_3_4.7%22_(alcatel-idol347)">Alcatel Idol 347</a>,
using a Quad-core 1.2 GHz Cortex-A53 CPU and 1.3GB of RAM, with a 5GB swap mounted.</p>

<p>Galaxy appears to use around ~1 GB RAM, and the phone still has enough
memory to spare to access the Galaxy UI via Firefox.</p>

<h2 id="really-why">Really, why?</h2>

<p>Just imagine: <em>Galaxy In Your Pocket™</em>! A united Galaxy Client and
Galaxy Server running on your phone 📲, which you can then access using
that same phone’s web browser.</p>

<p>It’s the perfect setup that only a <em>true and dedicated</em> Galaxy Admin
such as yourself can dream about.</p>

<p>Or if you’re not buying any of this, then it’s for those emergency
situations where you forgot your laptop and need to solve a bioinformatics crisis on the go 🧬🌄</p>]]></content><author><name>Mehmet Tekman</name></author><category term="news" /><category term="fun" /><category term="system administrators" /><category term="developers" /><category term="humour" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Hey Galaxy admins! Have you ever wanted to administer your own instance from the luxury of your pocket?]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/images/2024-01-31-postmarket-phone-cover.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/images/2024-01-31-postmarket-phone-cover.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">GTN in Discourse</title><link href="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/2024/01/30/oembed-testing.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="GTN in Discourse" /><published>2024-01-30T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-01-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/2024/01/30/oembed-testing</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/2024/01/30/oembed-testing.html"><![CDATA[<p>Howdy teachers and support staff! We are exploring displaying GTN content directly in the Galaxy Help site, furthering the integration between the GTN and the Galaxy community infrastructure.
When you paste a GTN <abbr title="FAQ">Frequently Asked Questions</abbr> URL into the Galaxy Discourse, it will now be rendered directly in Discourse!</p>

<figure id="figure-1" style="max-width: 90%;"><img src="/training-material/assets/images/oembed.png" alt="screenshot of a discourse post, a black and white box shows &quot;FAQ: Créer un nouvel history&quot; and the contents of the FAQ. " width="766" height="521" loading="lazy" /><a target="_blank" href="/training-material/assets/images/oembed.png" rel="noopener noreferrer"><small>Open image in new tab</small></a><br /><br /><figcaption><span class="figcaption-prefix"><strong>Figure 1</strong>:</span> Adding a GTN FAQ to your Galaxy Help answers can provide learners with a lot of context directly in the post, meaning they never have to leave the thread they're reading to understand what they need to do to resolve their issue.</figcaption></figure>

<p>This integration is currently in beta, and other infrastructure may be affected. If you see GTN FAQ URLs rendering poorly anywhere else, please let us know in the <a href="https://matrix.to/#/!Galaxy-Training-Network_Lobby:gitter.im">GTN Chat</a></p>]]></content><author><name>Helena Rasche, Jennifer Hillman-Jackson, Wendi Bacon, Martin Čech</name></author><category term="news" /><category term="gtn infrastructure" /><category term="new feature" /><category term="beta" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Howdy teachers and support staff! We are exploring displaying GTN content directly in the Galaxy Help site, furthering the integration between the GTN and the Galaxy community infrastructure. When you paste a GTN Frequently Asked Questions URL into the Galaxy Discourse, it will now be rendered directly in Discourse!]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Simplified GTN News submission via Google Form</title><link href="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/2024/01/29/simplified-gtn-news-submission-via-google-form.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Simplified GTN News submission via Google Form" /><published>2024-01-29T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-01-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/2024/01/29/simplified-gtn-news-submission-via-google-form</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/2024/01/29/simplified-gtn-news-submission-via-google-form.html"><![CDATA[<p>Based on user feedback of the difficulties of the GTN news submission process we have significantly simplified and removed the need for manually editing a YAML file by providing a quick and easy <a href="https://forms.gle/TqGTr6y46wrJDri7A">Google Form</a></p>

<p>Any news submitted via this form will be reviewed by the GTN maintainers, and, when linting is passing, merged.</p>

<p>So if you have some cool training news you want to share, then please let us know!</p>

<p><em>Fun Fact</em>: This news post was prepared in the new Google Form.</p>]]></content><author><name>Helena Rasche</name></author><category term="news" /><category term="gtn infrastructure" /><category term="new feature" /><category term="automation" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Based on user feedback of the difficulties of the GTN news submission process we have significantly simplified and removed the need for manually editing a YAML file by providing a quick and easy Google Form]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">FAIR Data management in single cell analysis</title><link href="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/2024/01/17/sc-fair-data.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="FAIR Data management in single cell analysis" /><published>2024-01-17T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-01-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/2024/01/17/sc-fair-data</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/2024/01/17/sc-fair-data.html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="new-single-cell-section-changing-data-formats--preparing-objects">New single cell section: Changing data formats &amp; preparing objects</h1>

<p>Now a nightmare of switching between single cell datatypes or importing the data is gone! With the new section on Changing data formats &amp; preparing objects, the users can now confidently jump into the analysis. Some of those tutorials were created in the framework of ELIXIR-UK: FAIR Data Stewardship training, which aims to improve Findable Accessible Interoperable Reusable (FAIR) data management in the life sciences.</p>

<p>We have developed the following tutorials:</p>
<ul>
  <li><a href="/training-material/topics/single-cell/tutorials/scrna-data-ingest/tutorial.html">Converting between common single cell data formats</a></li>
  <li><a href="/training-material/topics/single-cell/tutorials/EBI-retrieval/tutorial.html">Importing files for single cell analysis from public atlases</a></li>
  <li><a href="/training-material/topics/single-cell/tutorials/scrna-ncbi-anndata/tutorial.html">Converting NCBI Data to the AnnData Format</a></li>
  <li><a href="/training-material/topics/single-cell/tutorials/bulk-music-2-preparescref/tutorial.html">Creating a single-cell RNA-seq reference dataset for deconvolution</a></li>
  <li><a href="/training-material/topics/single-cell/tutorials/bulk-music-3-preparebulk/tutorial.html">Creating the bulk RNA-seq dataset for deconvolution</a></li>
</ul>

<h1 id="where-can-i-learn-more">Where can I learn more?</h1>

<p>You can find out more about the FAIR Data Stewardship training on the <a href="http://fellowship.elixiruknode.org/">ELIXIR-UK Fellowship site</a>. Also, keep an eye on the upcoming live trainings!</p>]]></content><author><name>Julia Jakiela, Morgan Howells, Wendi Bacon</name></author><category term="news" /><category term="single cell" /><category term="data management" /><category term="data import" /><category term="fair" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[New single cell section: Changing data formats &amp; preparing objects]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Galaxy Single-cell Community: Year in Review</title><link href="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/2023/12/22/single-cell.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Galaxy Single-cell Community: Year in Review" /><published>2023-12-22T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-12-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/2023/12/22/single-cell</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/2023/12/22/single-cell.html"><![CDATA[<p>🚀Embarking on a cosmic journey, the Galaxy Single-cell Community has clustered together to unveil a constellation of tools, making strides in RNA-stellar discoveries and creating out-of-this-world workflows. With a commitment to battling work duplication across the multiverse, this community is boldly charting a course for global domination, proving that when it comes to bioinformatics, the Galaxy is the limit!✨</p>

<h1 id="tools--workflows">Tools &amp; Workflows</h1>

<p>The past year has been a spectacular journey in advancing tools and workflows within the Galaxy Single-cell Community. Breaking free from the confines of scRNA-seq, we’ve expanded our horizons to include tools for analyzing data from other modalities such as single-cell ATAC-seq and CITE-Seq. Dive into our updated scRNA-seq analysis tools, now featuring more downstream analysis options for trajectory analysis. We’ve even thrown in advanced analysis tools for estimating cell type proportions from bulk RNA-seq data!</p>

<p><strong>RNA STARSolo</strong> just got a makeover to version 2.7.10b, boasting a revamped UI, Velocyto-like UMI counting, and nifty alternatives for quantifying single nuclei data. Analyzing single-cell ATAC-seq data on Galaxy is now a breeze with the introduction of the <strong>EpiScanpy</strong> tool suite, built on the renowned <strong>Scanpy</strong> toolkit. Plus, we’ve added some powerful tools from the <strong>Sinto</strong> toolkit for preprocessing scATAC-seq data on Galaxy. And that’s not all! The <strong>MuSiC</strong> tool suite in Galaxy now unveils deconvolution tools for discovering cell type composition in bulk RNA-seq using cell types within scRNA-seq. Multi-faceted comparisons are now at your fingertips with the <strong>MuSiC Compare</strong> tool.</p>

<p>Seurat fans, rejoice! Updates have rolled in, offering additional functionalities and optional CITE-seq capabilities at runtime.</p>

<h1 id="community-infrastructure">Community Infrastructure</h1>

<p>Our efforts in community building have seen the unification of single-cell subdomains into <a href="https://singlecell.usegalaxy.eu/">https://singlecell.usegalaxy.eu/</a>, the creation of the Single Cell Community of Practice hub page (<a href="https://galaxyproject.org/projects/singlecell/">https://galaxyproject.org/projects/singlecell/</a>), and a user-focused Matrix channel. Testing brilliant widgets, automated updates, and the latest addition of automated help request updates onto Matrix channels have made community collaboration a breeze.</p>

<h1 id="global-connections">Global Connections</h1>

<p>Down under, the Australian BioCommons launched their <a href="https://zenodo.org/records/10368976">Single Cell and Spatial Omics Analysis Infrastructure Roadmap for Australia</a>, complementing our endeavors to unite across timezones. Collaboration, including international tool adventures across three continents, proves that team work does, in fact, make the dream work.</p>

<h2 id="training">Training</h2>

<p>Get ready for a thrilling journey through the <a href="/training-material/topics/single-cell">Single Cell Training</a>’s latest updates! The <strong>Case Study Reloaded</strong> tutorial, fueled by three remote-working undergrads, introduces parallel trajectory analysis in R, Python, and the Galaxy GUI.</p>

<p>Sustainability shines as we’ve revamped numerous tutorials with hands-on and video re-recordings. New tools bring new tutorials, such as <a href="/training-material/topics/single-cell/tutorials/scatac-preprocessing-tenx/tutorial.html">Pre-processing of 10X Single-Cell ATAC-seq Datasets</a> and <a href="/training-material/topics/single-cell/tutorials/bulk-music-4-compare/tutorial.html">Comparing inferred cell compositions using MuSiC deconvolution</a>.</p>

<p>Tackling user hurdles, our data ingest and conversion tutorials in the <strong>Changing data formats &amp; preparing objects</strong> section await exploration.</p>

<p>Dive into the unique <strong>Tips, tricks &amp; other hints</strong> section, offering analysis options like <a href="/training-material/topics/single-cell/tutorials/scanpy_parameter_iterator/tutorial.html">parameter iteration</a> for swift optimization or <a href="/training-material/topics/single-cell/tutorials/scrna-case_cell-cycle/tutorial.html">Removing the effects of the cell cycle</a> for precise clustering analysis.</p>

<p>And don’t miss our inaugural <a href="/training-material/learning-pathways/intro_single_cell.html">Learning Pathway</a>, guiding Galaxy novices to becoming single-cell analysis experts!</p>

<h1 id="fighting-work-duplication">Fighting Work Duplication</h1>

<p>Our mission: No more work duplication! We’ve consolidated single-cell instances and are diligently preventing tool and infrastructure duplication, creating smoother pathways across servers. We value efficiency here at single-cell, so we’d like to thank ChatGPT (free version) for adding in Galaxy puns to this post, as per our request.</p>

<h1 id="what-a-year">What a Year!</h1>

<p>What’s next on our list? World domination or global collaboration? You decide. Stay tuned for another exciting year with the Galaxy Single-cell Community!</p>]]></content><author><name>Mehmet Tekman, Wendi Bacon, Pavankumar Videm</name></author><category term="news" /><category term="gtn" /><category term="communications" /><category term="single-cell" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[🚀Embarking on a cosmic journey, the Galaxy Single-cell Community has clustered together to unveil a constellation of tools, making strides in RNA-stellar discoveries and creating out-of-this-world workflows. With a commitment to battling work duplication across the multiverse, this community is boldly charting a course for global domination, proving that when it comes to bioinformatics, the Galaxy is the limit!✨]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/images/2023_dec_sc.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/images/2023_dec_sc.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">GTN Helper Bots Connect the Galaxy</title><link href="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/2023/12/20/matrix-bots.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="GTN Helper Bots Connect the Galaxy" /><published>2023-12-20T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-12-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/2023/12/20/matrix-bots</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/2023/12/20/matrix-bots.html"><![CDATA[<p>🤖💬 Bleep bloop! Good news everyone! We have deployed some bots to enable our Matrix regulars
to better engage with the contributions and questions of our users on
the non-Matrix side of the Galaxy-verse.</p>

<h2 id="galaxy-help-posts">Galaxy Help Posts</h2>

<p>The newest bot we’ve added looks through the <a href="https://help.galaxyproject.org/">Galaxy Help</a> forum for topics in need of
answering, and forwards those to the humans in Matrix channels related to those topics!</p>

<p>We are currently trialing this new integration to provide high quality human help with the Single Cell CoP. If it’s successful, our first expansion will be to the admin channel.</p>

<h2 id="gtn-contributions">GTN Contributions</h2>

<p>Our existing GTN bot summarizes the contributions to the GTN each day and delivers the great news to the
<a href="https://app.element.io/#/room/#Galaxy-Training-Network_Lobby:gitter.im">GTN Matrix Lobby</a>, as well as single-cell specific updates just to the <a href="https://app.element.io/#/room/#!yuLoaCWKpFHkWPmVEO:gitter.im">Single Cell User Community</a>.</p>

<p>Would your community like to receive these daily GTN updates for your community? Reach out to us on <a href="https://app.element.io/#/room/#Galaxy-Training-Network_Lobby:gitter.im">Matrix</a> or <a href="https://github.com/galaxyproject/training-material/issues/">GitHub</a>. Currently this integration is only available for Matrix but if it would be useful as an RSS feed please let us know.</p>

<h2 id="beep-boop">Beep Boop</h2>

<p>Thanks to these new ‘intergalactic’ communication methods, the world just got a little smaller!</p>]]></content><author><name>Mehmet Tekman</name></author><category term="news" /><category term="gtn" /><category term="communications" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[🤖💬 Bleep bloop! Good news everyone! We have deployed some bots to enable our Matrix regulars to better engage with the contributions and questions of our users on the non-Matrix side of the Galaxy-verse.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">User story: Where Galaxy meets medicinal chemistry</title><link href="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/2023/12/18/medchem-user.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="User story: Where Galaxy meets medicinal chemistry" /><published>2023-12-18T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-12-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/2023/12/18/medchem-user</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/2023/12/18/medchem-user.html"><![CDATA[<p>As a medicinal chemistry student, I undertook a semester project on natural products isolation and derivatisation. One of the compounds my group was working on was piperine, extracted from black pepper. Inspired by literature findings, we found out that the derivatives of piperine can inhibit monoamine oxidase-B and thus can be possibly used in Parkinson’s disease. As a novelty element in our project, we came up with new structures of derivatives that could act as inhibitors.</p>

<p>Before synthesising any new molecules, it would make sense to check if they correctly dock into the active site. As an enthusiastic user and developer of Galaxy, the idea of using GTN came straight to my mind. Even though molecular docking was beyond the scope of our project, I knew that Galaxy and GTN give such an amazing opportunity to do it in the blink of an eye that I wouldn’t be myself if I hadn’t tried! Therefore, by using the <a href="/training-material/topics/computational-chemistry/tutorials/cheminformatics/tutorial.html">tutorial on molecular docking</a>, I identified the pocket, then I studied the binding of the approved drugs such as Safinamide and Zonisamide and finally I checked how our proposed molecule fits within the pocket. After that, we were ready to synthesise the derivative we came up with!</p>

<figure id="figure-1" style="max-width: 90%;"><img src="/training-material/news/images/2023-12-18-medchem-user.jpg" alt="Picture of piperine derivative docking into MAO-B pocket." width="1509" height="842" loading="lazy" /><a target="_blank" href="/training-material/news/images/2023-12-18-medchem-user.jpg" rel="noopener noreferrer"><small>Open image in new tab</small></a><br /><br /><figcaption><span class="figcaption-prefix"><strong>Figure 1</strong>:</span> Piperine derivative as a potential inhibitor of MAO-B</figcaption></figure>

<p>This example shows how GTN and Galaxy can facilitate and accelerate the work of medicinal chemists before starting the synthesis. It is easy to follow the GTN tutorials, the results are reproducible, the datasets are stored in the history and can be easily shared with anyone on the team.</p>]]></content><author><name>Julia Jakiela</name></author><category term="news" /><category term="computational chemistry" /><category term="user story" /><category term="gtn" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[As a medicinal chemistry student, I undertook a semester project on natural products isolation and derivatisation. One of the compounds my group was working on was piperine, extracted from black pepper. Inspired by literature findings, we found out that the derivatives of piperine can inhibit monoamine oxidase-B and thus can be possibly used in Parkinson’s disease. As a novelty element in our project, we came up with new structures of derivatives that could act as inhibitors.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Tutorial Feature: Easier launching of WorkflowHub &amp;amp; Dockstore Workflows</title><link href="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/2023/12/12/tutorial-run-wfh-ds.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Tutorial Feature: Easier launching of WorkflowHub &amp;amp; Dockstore Workflows" /><published>2023-12-12T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-12-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/2023/12/12/tutorial-run-wfh-ds</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/2023/12/12/tutorial-run-wfh-ds.html"><![CDATA[<p>While most GTN tutorials include their associated workflow directly in the GTN, some may wish to write a tutorial about running workflows from WorkflowHub, e.g. leveraging the <a href="https://workflowhub.eu/projects/33">IWC workflow collection</a>.</p>

<p>We’ve added two snippets which make that easier than ever:</p>

<!--SNIPPET-->
<blockquote class="hands_on">   <div class="box-title hands_on-title" id="hands-on-importing-and-launching-a-workflowhub-eu-workflow"><i class="fas fa-pencil-alt" aria-hidden="true"></i> Hands-on: Importing and Launching a WorkflowHub.eu Workflow</div>   <div class="show-when-galaxy-proxy-active"> Click here to run <span class="workflow" data-workflow="https://workflowhub.eu/ga4gh/trs/v2/tools/248/versions/1"><strong>gromacs-mmgbsa/main</strong> <i class="fas fa-share-alt" aria-hidden="true"></i></span> </div>   <div class="hide-when-galaxy-proxy-active"> Click here to run <a href="https://my.galaxy.training/?path=/workflows/trs_import%3ftrs_server=workflowhub.eu%26run_form=true%26trs_id=248%26trs_version=1"><strong>gromacs-mmgbsa/main</strong> <i class="fas fa-share-alt" aria-hidden="true"></i></a> </div> </blockquote>
<p><!--END_SNIPPET--></p>

<p>And one for Dockstore:</p>

<!--SNIPPET-->
<blockquote class="hands_on">   <div class="box-title hands_on-title" id="hands-on-importing-and-launching-a-dockstore-workflow"><i class="fas fa-pencil-alt" aria-hidden="true"></i> Hands-on: Importing and Launching a Dockstore workflow</div>   <div class="show-when-galaxy-proxy-active"> Click here to run <span class="workflow" data-workflow="https://dockstore.org/api/ga4gh/trs/v2/tools/#workflow/github.com/jmchilton/galaxy-workflow-dockstore-example-1/mycoolworkflow"><strong>My Cool Workflow</strong> <i class="fas fa-share-alt" aria-hidden="true"></i></span> </div>   <div class="hide-when-galaxy-proxy-active"> Click here to run <a href="https://my.galaxy.training/?path=/workflows/trs_import%3ftrs_server=dockstore.org%26run_form=true%26trs_id=%2523workflow/github.com/jmchilton/galaxy-workflow-dockstore-example-1/mycoolworkflow"><strong>My Cool Workflow</strong> <i class="fas fa-share-alt" aria-hidden="true"></i></a> </div> </blockquote>
<p><!--END_SNIPPET--></p>

<p>You can read more about these snippets and how to use them yourself in your tutorials in the <a href="/training-material/topics/contributing/tutorials/create-new-tutorial-content/tutorial.html#workflows">GTN Contribution Guide section on Workflows</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name>Helena Rasche</name></author><category term="news" /><category term="feature update" /><category term="gtn" /><category term="tutorials" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[While most GTN tutorials include their associated workflow directly in the GTN, some may wish to write a tutorial about running workflows from WorkflowHub, e.g. leveraging the IWC workflow collection.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">GTN has left Twitter/X as of October</title><link href="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/2023/11/21/mastodon.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="GTN has left Twitter/X as of October" /><published>2023-11-21T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-11-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/2023/11/21/mastodon</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/2023/11/21/mastodon.html"><![CDATA[<p>We did not formally announce it at the time, but the Galaxy Training Network
has migrated from Twitter/X to Mastodon, as that platform no longer aligns with
the Galaxy Project Code of Conduct <a href="https://www.mediamatters.org/twitter/musk-endorses-antisemitic-conspiracy-theory-x-has-been-placing-ads-apple-bravo-ibm-oracle">nor our community values.</a></p>

<p>If you’d like to keep up to date with the GTN, we encourage you to <a href="https://mstdn.science/@gtn">follow us on mastodon</a>. The <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fediverse">fediverse and mastodon</a> are an open, standards compliant social network that is significantly more aligned with our community values and priorities of keeping community safe.</p>

<p>Are you not a fediverse user? Do you not have a mastodon account? That’s ok!
Every mastodon account has a built in <a href="https://mstdn.science/@gtn.rss">RSS feed which you can use to stay updated</a>,
and the GTN has an <a href="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/feed.xml">RSS feed as well for our news</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name>Helena Rasche</name></author><category term="news" /><category term="gtn" /><category term="communications" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[We did not formally announce it at the time, but the Galaxy Training Network has migrated from Twitter/X to Mastodon, as that platform no longer aligns with the Galaxy Project Code of Conduct nor our community values.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Feedback: Easy slide recordings</title><link href="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/2023/11/21/video.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Feedback: Easy slide recordings" /><published>2023-11-21T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-11-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/2023/11/21/video</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://training.galaxyproject.org/training-material/news/2023/11/21/video.html"><![CDATA[<p>I recently imported <a href="https://github.com/cxli233/FriendsDontLetFriends">Friends Don’t Let Friends Make Bad Graphs</a>, a fantastic and educational github repository showcasing some common visualisation mistakes, that was available under an open license, to the GTN. Then the GTN <a href="/training-material/videos/watch.html?v=visualisation/tutorials/bad-graphs/slides">automatically made a video for me.</a></p>

<blockquote class="quote" cite="https://matrix.to/#/%23Galaxy-Training-Network_Lobby%3Agitter.im/%247oeH_z7dGcO0T9z1BRk0HU6P2yTPBHNfdfzJBo0-WIM?via=matrix.org&amp;via=gitter.im" author="@hexylena">
  <p>[It was] really truly magical to be able to generate a 12 minute video in about the same amount of time that was spent importing the content + reformatting it</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Just by adding the slides, with good speaker notes made from the discussion that already existing
I simply had to add the slides, turn the discussion into speaker notes, and that was it. I was done.
Once the PR was merged, the video was created, and available to watch on the GTN.</p>

<p>The video has perfectly accurate subtitles for anyone who is hard of hearing or d/Deaf, the slides are also available in plain text formats for those who prefer them, all from my contribution of a single, reformatted, markdown file.</p>

<video id="player" width="100%" height="auto" controls="" preload="metadata" style="background: black" poster="https://training.galaxyproject.org/videos/topics/visualisation/tutorials/bad-graphs/slides.mp4.png">
	<source src="https://training.galaxyproject.org/videos/topics/visualisation/tutorials/bad-graphs/slides.mp4" type="video/mp4" />
	<track label="English" kind="captions" srclang="en" src="https://training.galaxyproject.org/videos/topics/visualisation/tutorials/bad-graphs/slides.en.vtt" default="" />
</video>]]></content><author><name>Helena Rasche</name></author><category term="news" /><category term="feedback" /><category term="testimonial" /><category term="gtn" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I recently imported Friends Don’t Let Friends Make Bad Graphs, a fantastic and educational github repository showcasing some common visualisation mistakes, that was available under an open license, to the GTN. Then the GTN automatically made a video for me.]]></summary></entry></feed>