great thanks so I'm to review I'm the
genomics director here at OU ACR and the
senior scientist
across the spider Cancer Center so my
role has always been right in the middle
of basic research and clinical
translation so my my lab and both
operation here oh I see are really right
at that interface where we try to take
research findings and put them at the
practice as possible I the other had I
where I'm a board-certified molecular
geneticist so really set it's like the
best kept secret in academic research
basically it's a career path for PhD
scientists to get poured certification
then essentially sign out I'm like the
pathology reports through through
pathology departments so I really would
I'm actually the fact that's on my CV
I'm actually a graduate also of the
canaima ranks or traps live so it took
the same program when I was a graduate
student at the BC Cancer Agency and that
skill set really held me well going
through especially the clinical genomics
world or really that skill set is really
an increasingly increasing need
especially to move from single genes to
Kochi from sequencing so that's sort of
a plug for that but certainly CBW really
got me started so my role in this
workshop is really to describe not
really the right down to the scripts and
codes and pipelines but really a
high-level overview of cancer genomics
and I've really tried to fill this talk
with as many data examples as possible
and links out to sort of landmark papers
in the fields really illustrate how does
the cancer genome go wrong and how we
use my informatics and computational
biology to measure and interpret it the
way the whole talk is set out is the
first 45 minutes to an hour is really a
little more didactic it's here's the
cancer genome here's what goes wrong
here's how we measure it's
computationally but the last 45 minutes
maybe 30 minutes is a case report
basically one of the first patients ever
to get whole genome when RNA sequencing
and how we went through at the Cancer
Agency at that time to interpret that
genome essentially manage that patient
over over a year and a half and so
that's the whole the learning objectives
of this module how is cancer genomes
different from healthy or normal genomes
how can we use bioinformatics
to define those differences what are the
many approaches you can tell there's
lots of ways lots of tools to do
things and bioinformatics so I'm really
not going to obsess over individual
tools that do certain things but really
the broad level concepts as to have
specific out specific algorithms are
useful for specific cancer types or
specific clinical questions and the last
part really that case report how do we
use genomics to understand or guide
patient care so any questions sort of on
that flyover overview background that
kind of thing happy to hear questions as
we as we go actually know several of you
in the audience oh that's good to see
so I really want to make a point we're
all made of cells and if you have a cell
it can become cancerous so really think
of cancer as starting from a single
healthy cell I'm asked all the time by
family like what about this cancer whoa
that cancer type there are really as
many cell types as there are there are
that many cancer types
genetically this is where really the you
can be very specific around types of
cancer and driver of cancer so I really
wanted to start the whole talk with what
does a normal genome look like this is
what one of my blood cells looks like if
you drop it on the glass slide at the
right point in the cell cycle you get
what is called a chromosome spread so
essentially these are all the
chromosomes from one cell and the
old-fashioned way
Kerra typing cytogenetics the the
clinical Enterprise the lab enterprise
is literally a scissors and glue to do a
paste up to take all these chromosomes
and line them up side by side purely
looking at the banding pattern so this
is what a paste up of that chromosome
look of the chromosome spread looks like
essentially looking for commonalities or
differences there shouldn't be any
necessarily in this normal blood cell
but the point of showing you this is to
compare and contrast this chromosome
this chromosome spread to cancer you can
tell by eye there are way too many
chromosomes here some chromosomes are
missing pieces if it problems an IP or
IP is missing here there's
translocations there's a huge list of
ways that the cancer genome can be
altered and you can see them even just
by eye looking yeah just the chromosomes
of course this is because it just
becomes more and more complicated as you
start to look at the essentially at the
base level resolution so hiding in here
are all the base pair changes mutations
other often
and alterations and the real challenge
especially with computational biologists
is not just making the list but also
linking that list to clinical actions so
this is a quote actually my previous
supervisor he loved this quote has it
pertained to cancer all happy families
or how all happy cells are like each
unhappy cell isn't happy in its own way
so really this idea of precision
medicine really came from the idea that
all the DNA in these cells can be
altered and different way they converge
on a relatively few relatively speaking
biological pathways but really the way
that those pathways are dysregulated
really is going to be unique to each
cell and each answer type and this is
essentially you always see a lot of
these this is a circo's diagram this is
another way to show chromosomes so in
this case instead of the sort of the
paint step I showed earlier all the
chromosomes are now ringed around the
outside and then what I've annotated he
actually might reverse see who runs the
software program that makes this these
types of plots is essentially annotated
in this inset all the different ways
that the cancer genome can be altered
mutations rearrangements of epigenetic
changes all the things you're going to
learn over the next week the other
aspect in cancer genomics is the
temporal aspect cancer genomes DNA cells
divide they change over time as a great
great review here by stratton and camera
stratton campbell and flu tree all
really showing how these mutations even
especially in pediatric cancers in fact
some of these kids are actually born
with cancer themselves in close not a
cancer diagnosis at some point they've
acquired these passenger mutations I
mean you can't in the case of adult
cancer it's essentially waiting for the
accumulation of mutations until you get
a mutation in the wrong spot in the
wrong cell at the wrong time those are
referred to as passenger mutation or
driver mutations rather so that's what's
listed here is as a star and then you
essentially see this again temporal
evolution acquisition of additional
somatic driver alterations
eventual diagnosis and even the active
treatment can actually introduce
additional mutations the most famous of
these team is all about brain cancer the
whole point of that treatment is to just
bombard the cancer genome with so many
mutations that those cells eventually
become unstable and die it actually does
not
extend life to a huge degree at least in
in brain cancer but it's one therapeutic
strategy and completely measuring
measurable using that music genomics so
just some key points on the slide
mutation frequency depends on cancer
type the pediatric cancers as they
haven't had the opportunity to pile up
these mutations are often the low
mutation rate tumors and the high
mutation rate tumors especially the ones
that have external environmental
exposure Sun and melanoma smoking and
lung cancer these are all the higher
mutation rate tumors and if you look at
those tumors about post team as Olamide
they're just peppered with hundreds of
thousands if not millions of mutations
in the most extreme case here's a plot
sort of the first date applause I really
have to talk really showing all this is
actually a great pan-cancer analysis by
GAD Getz his group led by Mike Mike
Lawrence at the Geno at the Broad
Institute in this case each dot and is
an individual cancer many of these
coming from the Cancer Genome Atlas
project but really to hammer home that
point of low meat the way to read this
re is y-axis and mutation rate x-axis is
cancer type the low mutaters and the
pediatric cancers down here the high
mutaters and the the environmentally
exposed cancers really on the other
extreme but the other important point on
this plot is really the huge dynamic
range within an individual cancer types
well you can say in general pediatric
cancers have low mutation rates I
circled this one here this neuroblastoma
this is actually from a project I worked
on as a postdoc this case very
interesting actually just as many meet
as mutations is a late stage lung cancer
and the reason for that was this is the
only neuroblastoma that had two
mutations mutation in each copy of mlh1
a DNA repair gene so it was really a
direct link between loss of the ability
of that cell to repair its DNA and just
piling up with additional mutations it
looked the same if you look this at the
cells built at the chromosome it looked
like neuroblastoma but if you really
squat down to the base level resolution
you could see all these mutations and we
see a molecular cause for the opposite
story here here's melanoma very famous
for very high mutation rate these these
tumors actually respond very well to
drugs that reactivate the immune system
because they're lots
potential antigens to be recognized in
in these tumors this one down here he
actually has just as many mutations as
pediatric cancers very unusual in this
case is the actually the only melanoma
in the TCGA cohort that was not some
expose this was actually a tumor on the
bottom of the patient's foot no sun
exposure whatsoever just extraordinarily
bad luck it was a driver mutation in a
melanocytes that resulted in bad cancer
and actually if you really squint you
can see here this sort of this the way
to read this bottom is here all the
different types of mutations and there's
one that's actually quite different this
little blue sliver it does not have any
of the sun exposure signature like all
of the others all the yellow mutations
here essentially are induced by a UV
exposure he's really the outlier both in
mutation counts but also a mutation
types
so really all hangs together another
famous slide just in general where these
mutations landing and general tumor
cells acquire abnormal activities and
you actually are they're not inventing
new abilities they're taking abilities
from other normal cells and turning them
on and cells where they shouldn't be
active so this is termed the hallmarks
of cancer are not you're really gonna
believe or what these are but
essentially you can been a lot of these
driver processes into not that many
biological processes and essentially
pretty much every cancer type has
co-opted or undermine these molecular
processes almost always do so to a
somatic alteration
I presentation that rearranged from the
car never change or often the collection
of all of these all of these at once the
other goal and challenge certainly by
informatics is or question action often
catches like what is a driver mutation
how do you differentiate that from the
passenger mutation they the way this was
done classically during the Cancer
Genome Atlas project was to grind up in
sequence 500 of every single examples of
every single cancer type and look for
mutations that we saw over and over and
over so it actually turns out specifics
cell of origins all depend on different
academic or regular normal signaling
pathways and therefore they're getting
mutations that often clusters specific
in those pathways specifically so I'm
just showing here those oncogenic
mutations are essentially targeting a
core set of biological functions
relevant to that cell type and this
just an example like this is a great
textbook just in general Thompson and
Thompson this sort of the Bible
certainly for the medical genetics field
sort of filled with a lot of these types
of concepts in this case having this
idea of a single cell activating
oncogenes these are sort of like the gas
or for a car so to have you drive the
cell cycle or cell growth turning off
the brake so often these tumor
suppressor genes you know we have two
chromosomes just like I showed on the
earlier slide you need two mutations to
knock these out one from each from each
each copy and then additional
accumulation of mutations over time
again undermining or either turning on
or turning off normal biological
processes and this is actually still a
challenge
TCGA actually did a great job to define
the high frequency recurrent mutations
across all cancer types in TCGA but as
we continue to test now thousands or
tens of thousands of tumors or continue
to identify even more sort of more
infrequently mutated but still
biologically meaningful somatic
mutations across virtually all all
cancer types really the context of this
talk is really not just finding
mutations that how do we do something
about them so I've just showed two of
the most important examples here really
this concept of targeted therapies and
this is really a change round so at
early 2000s 2004 2004 really the
understanding that yes there are driver
mutations specifically in cancer but
also the idea that if we know there's a
pathway that's turned on abnormally
selecting a therapy that can then
inhibit or block activation of that
pathway so two examples here lung
adenocarcinoma with now essentially
standard of care activating mutations of
EGFR these mutations activate the
epidermal growth factor receptor pathway
the therapeutic strategy is pretty
obvious just block EGFR and block EGFR
signal signaling and this paper here
really showing very dramatic responses
to inhibited inhibition of EGFR but only
effective in patients with those
specific mutations same story here
missed at melanoma in this case is poor
patient really just filled with multiple
metastatic lesions and then very very
dramatic responses to BEMER and when
those tumors have b-raf
600d mutations the problem with this
approach have made it obvious there's a
lot of genomic complexity to these
tumors and this therapeutic strategy is
just saying one of potentially hundreds
of other other driver mutations or other
pathways active in these cells
so using these targeted therapies that
the single mono therapy approach really
results inevitably in resistance there's
very very rarely that any of these M
single targeted agents result in cure
they certainly derive a very strong
survival benefit but really the paths
are made my opinion is that really the
need to identify multiple autogenic
pathways active at once and hit them
simultaneously or very close in time and
one piece of data that really support
that is this idea that tumors are almost
always or at least the majority of
tumors have mutations in multiple
targeted pathways so this is a big band
format it's exercise I'm published in
Nature Genetics going to read this plot
each column is a different cancer types
you'll get to know these little
four-letter codes or kind of the codes
that TCGA has used ethnic cancer kidney
cancer lung adenocarcinoma except etc so
that's how you read the columns each row
is a different driver driver mutation or
tumor suppressor and the three main
points from this paper were the first
druggable alterations cut across cancer
types in this case fgfr3 mutations being
seen in multiple tumors b-raf mutations
are another good example they're often
actually the reason I like this figure
they've mapped all the genes to specific
oxygen at pathways so the second story
is it's very common within a cancer type
to have two or more pathways implicated
so in this case these two cancer types
first of all share mutations in two
pathways but also two pathways are also
being mutated in individual tumors and
point three at least half of tumors have
at least two disrupted immediately
actionable or immediately targetable Pat
druggable pathways the other challenge
and actually main reason for resistance
is I've talked so far about cancer
so there are tumors this is one
amorphous blob of cells and it's
definitely not that so tumors are
actually a colony or micro environment
of cells actually really well
illustrated here in this review showing
in this case you started with a single
cell but as those cells to buy new just
like we saw over time new occupations or
new alterations essentially occur in
daughter cells and then those daughter
cells give rise to additional sub clones
so in this cartoon there are actually
three sub clones active and this is
actually a major challenge for molecular
testing because you may have your driver
mutation EGFR BRF what have you over
here but it may be actually absent where
these cells may no longer be dependent
specifically on having those pathways
those pathways activated and this is
really where mono they'll one potential
model for Y mono therapies may not be
effective long term we may be effective
against a single clone here but
additional clones may actually expand in
some cases to actually fill the niche
that's been left back sub Club Y and we
know that was at the at the single cell
level because if you actually take a a
sweating probe and probe for large
deletions or copy number alterations you
can even see by eye specific cells some
have the gains some of them don't some
have deletions some of them don't and
this is really the challenge generally
in genomics had we met all the driver
mutations not just to tumors but also
just subclones and ultimately single
cells and technology is just now coming
online it's actually enabling this idea
of precision medicine that single-cell
resolution essentially looking at the
DNA of its out of cells individually so
I foresee probably a single-cell
genomics workshop if there isn't one
already I'm sort of being in the works
in the next couple of years
I here's sort of a conceptual diagram of
what that can look like over time so a
single cell here driven by driver
mutations and loss of tumor suppressors
relatively short list here the expansion
of that highly heterogeneous mass to
hear all the different sub clonal
populations some share mutations so this
clone actually has two yellow they arose
from a single clone then you have a sub
clone of a sub clone and so on in this
case patient treated with chemotherapy
did a very good job debunking the tumor
in general so completely killed off
purple subclone but unfortunately great
Orange surviving and really the idea
especially upon relapse what are the
remaining drivers one of the features of
the relapse disease and how can you hit
that with a second targeted or
combination therapy and in this case
here this patient ultimately relapse
multiple new driver mutations unique to
a totally new clone that actually was
not even apparent at diagnosis I just
illustrates a few reasons and are a few
concepts one the power of longitudinal
sampling of these tumors over time and
often the disconnect between the
diagnostic sample and what you actually
see it relapse or really the need to
have access to tumor material or in some
cases cell-free DNA as close to the time
of clinical decision as possible here's
another example Peter Campbell again
looking at multiple metastatic tumors
from the same patient and really showing
how essentially a tumor can move around
the body and as it metastasizes then
founding its own micro environment with
its own clonal sub or its own subclonal
structure so idea of the primary tumor
metastasis hopping out here additional
sub clones metastasis seeding additional
who metastases and actually some really
nice work from scratch ah where he
showed even these tertiary metastases
can go back and reseed the other mad at
man metastatic site so really some great
molecular complexity all of it measured
and potentially actionable depending on
the types of mutations that were
encountering within these sub clubs so
you sort the list why would we do
molecular testing for cancer I've talked
a lot about targeted therapies and
treatments understand the drivers
understand the pathways implicated
measuring of drug resistance especially
in the mono therapy case when do we see
resistance have you direct a patient
towards a different targeted therapeutic
strategy I'm not going to talk a lot
about this but certainly in the germline
space inherited cancer syndromes these
are patients who are born with a cancer
predisposition variant and out
essentially waiting for loss of that
remaining allele and prognosis here's
the cancer type is it high-risk or not
is it a cancer venom primary can
molecular testing help refine specific
cell of origin for unusual cancers
so let's sort the general overview does
anyone have any questions about the
reasons for like you're testing genomics
in general okay seeing none so I'm gonna
really push into camera yeah so Romans
comment so as we can find mutations how
do we show that there's actually
interaction or I guess even interested
interdependence II this is really the
boom now it's really being able to link
a genomic readout to a functional
genomic readout because I would argue
certainly in clinical lab testing no
it's fine a mutation reported back this
is really where I think research has to
happen now is how do you model
especially multiple mutations or
multiple pathways active in single
tumors and then how do you come up with
therapeutic strategies against those I
mean I think there's a few bad from
Attucks algorithms that do that but to
me you essentially need a lab experiment
to show that yes these two axes are
critical one experiment we're doing with
Peter Dirk's now view sequence
cell lines in a dish define the clones
using single cell sequencing and then
predict drugs that will work on Multan
one clone but not the other
so we'll try a drug a will try to drug B
I'll try a plus B and see if it kills
everything that's still super research
isn't certainly not clinical grade but
it's one conceptual way to take
measurement of somatic mutation and
mapping that to function but yeah it's a
lab experiment yeah okay so I'm now
gonna move more from the fly over here
as the landscape of all cancers now to
the individual patient level so the
patient it really doesn't matter as I've
showed in that neuroblastoma and
melanoma example it's great to know this
type of meat of cancer has high or low
mutation but really the question for an
individual patients is one of the
targets in my cancer is but this
specific end of one tumor high mutation
low the said mutations are the
predisposing polymorphisms what is the
copy number landscape for an individual
person our viruses or bacteria involved
and what can be done about them so
really the point is always make a list
but also in
for what that list actually means just
running the pipeline is really just not
is not the endpoint so I'm gonna talk a
little bit about next-generation
sequencing this is essentially the
machine that we use to measure cancer
genomes currently the workflow is I've
just broken into four steps take a tumor
you extract DNA and RNA make a library a
library is essentially DNA that's
compatible to reading on a dmx device
which is the next-generation sequencer
so essentially you take the DNA or the
RNA put these little synthetic adapters
on that essentially makes them readable
by Illumina sequencing device and then
computational analysis which is
essentially tailored to either the
clinical or the scientific the
scientific question so I just showed
some data examples this is what comes
off an Illumina sequencer it's literally
just the text document you can open it
notepad if you want to every row is a
don't but you can each row is a is a
read a C's T's and G's I've just shown
25 here on a 2500 which is now a
increasingly obsolete machine one-lane
generates 600 million of these reads so
you get massive numbers of reads this is
not meant to be human readable of course
you need computational analysis to make
sense of just the raw reads so I'm sure
you've heard this concept of a pipeline
at essentially this idea that takes that
raw data and transforms it into a an
output with meaning the idea here at
least for us is to take that raw DNA
sequence in run it through a series of
pieces of software and really step one
is that list of variation pipelines
actually pretty good analogy all the
pieces have to fit together perfectly
without leaks they're relatively modular
so really the idea of taking reads
comparing them to the genome that may
result in a new data file that data file
can now be read by a variant caller
those variants can now be read by a
variant phil trader essentially this
idea of software being interoperable
really around file formats and data
standards the generic pipeline at least
for DNA genomics is alignment take you
of the reads I just showed you compare
them to the human genome reference how
do you QC or how do you
rather tidy up that alignment we use
liners they're very fast and sometimes
they make very minor mistake so step two
fixes that somewhat step three how do
you essentially assess the quality of
those alignments is your sample any good
your druvan quit DNA in does it look
like RNA is it human if you put human in
keep see is very very important
calling variants I put these four in
black because they're more or less
automated they're here at OIC our last
two steps are really not they're really
sort of the enterprise of computational
biology and the act of very
interpretation these really still need
humans to go through read by rebuild by
read variant by variant to really make
sense of an individual case and we'll go
through all of these during right talk
I'm so by far the most famous and widely
used pipeline is the genome analysis
toolkit SATs is the piece software
actually analysis framework from the
Broad Institute essentially the idea of
moving from raw reads moving through
essentially AI alignment to a comparison
to the human genome reference that QC
step I talked about their sort of
realigning around hard to align regions
fixing some of the quality of the bases
that came off the the sequencer running
variants and essentially doing
interpretation at the end they only
change really to this slide is I've just
put up some of the the tools we use for
cancer so gatk was actually built more
for germline analysis and now of course
been used by the cancer community as
well the reason we need cancer specific
tools is because of the types of site of
genetic events that we know happening
cancer we can't guarantee that cancer
have two copies of every chromosome so I
just showed you at the beginning that
doesn't happen they've got all their
genomes all the time you get these
awkward like three ployed you double and
then you lose a chromosome we need
collars that know that that can happen
they have a challenge with tumors is
they're not 100% cancer cells are always
a mixture of cancer cells and stromal
blood vessels immune cells we need
colors that know whether that can happen
you can't assume that half of your reads
will always have a variant than half the
reads always won't unique cancer where
or algorithms and this is really where
cancer bioinformatics or diverges from
conventional I guess I'd call it
germline
so step one is to take that yes yes
especially as your camels increase in
size as you look at more and more genes
it's essentially mandatory so anything
excellent above I would say always a
paired normal even four panels to the
500 genes we always run into a variant
that looks interesting but if we
sequence the normal that happens to be
there so yeah it's really worth the cost
if only in everyone's salaries trying to
figure out weird and rare variants to
just sequence the normal and settle this
as a question maybe a five gene panel I
could probably buy informatica Lee go
through five genes manually but yes I
really definitely encourage to build
that into your grants and budgets
sequence the normal so here's what step
one looks like it's actually the same
data I showed on the earlier slide just
aligned to the human genome reference
this is a piece of software I use pretty
much every day to look at
next-generation sequencing reads so the
way to use it here's the chromosome
along the top here's the region I've
zoomed into so I've zoomed in
extraordinary extraordinarily close just
in 292 basis here's the coverage this is
a histogram of how many reads align to
the next track which is the human genome
reference you can literally just
download this off the internet I usually
go to the UCSC genome browser there's
literally a link download the reference
so many three or four gigs it's not too
large and in gray are all of my reads so
essentially the question for cancer
genomics is how do our reads differ from
the reference and how they DIF differ
from match normal I've intentionally
chose in this case because there
shouldn't be any variation in this
region I think there are one or two
sharp-eyed students found one years ago
it's almost always the sequencing
artifact especially in sort of a sea of
non variation but there's there are some
technical questions really around what
does the sequencing artifact versus what
is it extraordinarily rare point
mutation I'm not going to go into that
too much in this talk and the other the
other quirk is there are many many many
ways to make
this slide there's a whole Wikipedia
article for short retold sequence
alignment on this slide we use bwa it's
like far the most widely used because
extraordinarily fast for its for the
quality of the alignment so there are
lots of other tools some of them pay for
you some of them not as it's probably
more than 50 now but there are lots of
ways to essentially transform your data
from raw which is past cue that's the
file format we use at least for data
coming off the Illumina sequencer and
transforming that into a BAM file which
is essentially a binary alignment file
and the nice thing about this i GV
software is if you have an in BAM format
essentially it will let you read and
look around at these at these reads this
is actually a cartoon of what I just
showed you so it's the same sort of
layout the reference genome is here
along the top so in this case to
reference chromosomes chromosome 1
chromosome 5 here all the reads I just
showed you this review is actually
really aged really well this is
basically the same types of cancer
genome variation that we still look at
to this day in this case looking for
reads that have a difference so in this
case a bunch of C's where there should
be an A those are point mutations in
bills very very small stretches
I think the formal definition now is up
to 50 base pair so a deletion or
insertion very very small a very very
small portion of DNA contrast at the
very very large deletion so sort of
things that you could have seen said in
genetically we actually infer that as
missing data so if you try to sequence a
region and your cell just doesn't have
that DNA it's leads to lead to that
chromosome that actually comes through
in the data as Lac in this case if you
have half as much data in that region as
you expect so sorry this is a to copy
deletion this is a one-of to copy
deletion so a single copy deletion you
have half as much data as you'd expect
if you have a copy number gain you have
more chromosomes than say a normal
diploid cell we see that as additional
number of reads we infer that as a gain
and translocation break point this is
where one end of the DNA fragment is
aligned to one chromosome and if you
sequence the other end of that DNA
fragment it aligns to a totally
different problem so this is actually
where there's been a breakage of
chromosomes the cells tried to repair it
yeah incorrectly put two chromosomes
together this often put two
often drive often put a driver gene next
under the control of an inappropriate
regulatory element so it's very powerful
way to up regulate or turn on a driver
mutation and since its DNA if you're
doing agnostic sequencing you just brand
up cells and sequence them that DNA or
RNA actually comes through as well so if
your tumor happens to be associated with
a virus EBV HPV that DNA sequence of
course comes through you needed a
special algorithm to take those reads in
line not just against the human
reference but against other non-human
references as well and here's sort of
this is more for test purposes or I
don't think it's part of this workshop
has really here the different waves
we've thought about whole genome secret
in sequencing a whole genome sequencing
no selection at all just take all the
material from a cell sequence it whole
exome sequencing this is essentially a
laboratory protocol modification where
you just use hybrid selection lab
protocol to essentially pull out only
the protein coding genes these are only
one percent of the whole human genome
but they are the part of the human
genome that encode proteins and there's
certainly the most well-studied so in
terms of linking anything to action
almost everything can be captured by a
whole exome sequencing that's becoming
less true now as regulatory elements and
right back regulatory mutations are
being discovered but today right the
second whole exome sequencing captures a
lot of that actionability
targeted gene sequencing this is more
done for cost so really narrowing in
specifically on genes that get you onto
a clinical trial or are very high
frequency sites of mutation target
aberrant gene typing even more specific
so we're only looking at one single
mutation if you're really only cared
about one site there's no need to
sequence the whole genome just sequence
that one spot and epigenome
modifications is actually a type of
change to DNA mold same as this time at
the cytosines essentially that's
invisible to conventional sequencing so
you have to do a chemical treatment of
the DNA to essentially unmask or mark
specific regions that have this this
epigenomic modification RNA sequencing
it's conceptually the exact same thing
very similar pathway to what I just
showed instead of extracting DNA from
cells retract RNA instead and run it
through
very similar pipeline in that case we're
not as interested the we're not as
interested necessarily in mutations but
we are interested in Quantico
if a cell is expressing genes at very
very high level we get many many reads
we infer that is highly expressed same
sort of thing if a gene is not expressed
we shouldn't see any reads from from
from those genes I'm not going to talk
about at all protein this is really
going to be a more or less a DNA or RNA
talk but this sort of field is really
starting to rise certainly even in the
the clinical profiling world especially
as it intersects with you know DNA
sequencing and RNA sequencing so I'm
gonna focus mostly on DNA and RNA I want
to show you some real data this is the
same sample using three strategies whole
genome sequencing exome sequencing RNA
sequencing this is an IG be screen shot
just like I showed you earlier but this
time we're zoomed way out instead of 90
two base pairs we're looking at 49
thousand base pairs you can see a whole
genome sequencing we have coverage
across essentially this entire region
and this 49,000 base pairs essentially
corresponds to the single K rash genes
very famous cancer gene a lot of hot
spot meet a very well understood hotspot
mutation specifically in k rats in this
case you can see whole genome sequencing
nice relatively even coverage across the
entire gene exome sequencing there's
that laboratory modification so you only
get reads on exons so you can see down
here here the regions that encode
protein and you only get read so you're
completely blind to what's happening on
the intranet sequences may be
interesting regulatory element
structural changes all sorts of things
you're not going to see them by exome
sequencing and RNA sequencing you let
the cell do the work cells the ones
splicing out the introns so again you
don't actually get reads happening
within the intronic sequences wait you
do get are these relationships between
exons this is actually very powerful
because you can actually see where every
it starts in one exon and begins in
another so if the next one is not being
used or it's being used in the abnormal
way RNA sequencing will actually you
look at the structure of how that RNA is
I'm sure you've heard the term whole
genome and whole exome sequencing it's
not whole does not mean 100% this is
actually a figure from page five paper I
worked on this postdoc our
really - this is actually a set of two
hundred and forty odd neuroblastomas the
way to read this plot each tiny tiny
slice here is a sample the color is our
ability to find mutations so one means
great coverage we're very well powered
to find mutations but down in black or
achievement at 50% essentially the
coverage is relatively low or just ain't
able to confidently map reads to those
two specific regions of the genome so
you can see by far most of the xon
genome is white we're pretty good at
calling mutations but there's sort of
this band down here where that ability
to call mutation breaks down either due
to problems and mapping reads to the
whole genome most frequently actually in
this project there were large-scale
deletions so that's actually resulted in
no coverage in those regions therefore
had low coverage so it wasn't
necessarily a problem with whole genome
sequencing was actually a feature of the
cancer genome you can't sequence DNA
that's not necessarily there but there
was through this band in black but
basically we could never find mutations
in any samples and why even using a
relatively G deep genomes at the time we
still had this inaccessible portion of
the genome and these are still
challenging to sequence with short read
sequencing technologies today these are
repetitive regions the telomeres
centromeres regions of the genome that
have been duplicated so we just can't
tell whether read goes to the original
copy or to a duplicated part of the
genome there are long read technologies
that that do allow you to access this
region of the genome there's new phase
link technologies but really hole does
not mean not 2% frenzies yeah so exome
is depending on the company you buy the
baits from will change so yeah I try not
to use a whole too often it sort of
entered the lexicon
but yeah hold is really not a hundred
percent the definition of the exon will
actually change depending on who
designed the bait set is it one
reference transcript is that every ISO
firm we've ever seen associated with
those genes is that the exome including
utrs or not especially as Brown
petitions this is extraordinarily
important to know especially as you
start to take data from multiple sources
many of which will abuse different
designs of the XL both over time so
newer newer exo-m's will include jeans
that may not have even been discovered
from on the earlier bait sets and the
exomes have also been overly annotated
over time sir was there are some exons
that are absolutely huge you make a
basis and actually the later versions
even from the same company I have now
shrank down to seventy or sixth mega
bases so it's really very important to
understand especially when you get an
exome data is how did they define the
excel because they're not in general the
genes are highly over laughing but
they're not a hundred percent consistent
and certainly not the same over time
yeah so sorry yeah yeah so Bates in this
case the way most excellent sequencing
is done is essentially you have a
synthetic piece of DNA based on human
genome reference you tether it to
magnetic bead and essentially use a
magnet to only pull out DNA that that's
tipped that bait and since it's
synthetic you can design that to be
whatever you want and that is the reason
for the change in the design of the
Excel yeah so you may hear a few terms
our next some sequencing Bates probes
targets they all essentially mean the
same thing they're all different
laboratory methods to pull out a
specific region of interest
I mentioned RNA sequencing in this case
RNA of course the dynamic range is much
different than DNA DNA should be one
copy to copy to copy for and above RNA
sequencing is much more continuous cells
been turned on and off RNA to divide a
variety of levels I try to make this
plot for almost all the RNA seek data I
looked at I just basically take all the
genes or all the exons and I just sort
them by how many reads match to them you
should basically always get this S curve
very very highly expressed off or very
very low expression but actually a lot
of the biological actions kind of in
this middle sort of this middle region
I just shown this example here we have
this patient i pressing a patient a
patient with breast cancer there's three
very important genes for subtyping
subtyping breast cancer and if you
basically color all the exons that
correspond to these genes you can see
there also
this kale trending to zero and then as a
reference set here's two totally
different patients one who's er positive
one who's er negative and you can see
the ER positive breast cancer is
basically expressing ESR one at a
relatively high level certainly compared
to the negatives and the negative
basically looks a lot more like this
patients are really a very simple
example of how you can use a reference
set to put your gene or your gene
expression level in context with other
genes from similar tumors of the cell
via of the same type the other data type
not nearly as widely used as as exome
genome RNA sequencing is is bisulfite
sequencing or really what's being
increasingly termed methyl seek so in
this case you essentially treat your DNA
with a chemical if your if your meth if
your essentially your C base your
cytosine base is protected by a chemical
modification it doesn't get changed but
if you don't have that modification this
chemical has ability to then change that
C to a T so here's what that data
actually looks like otherwise exactly
the same workflow is for whole genome
sequencing you just do that chemical
modification at the start in this case
we're looking specifically at mlh1 so
important DNA repair gene I talked about
context of neuroblastoma here the here
the exons here along the bottom in this
case were very interested in this first
exon because it has this little
regulatory region and that regulatory
region is under the control of of
promoter methylation so essentially what
we're looking for is if that stretch of
DNA essentially is painted or of all the
C's all have a methyl a methyl group it
shuts down expression them.the of this
and if those methyl groups are removed
or are not present that then allows the
gene to be transcribed sensitive it
looks like a normal tissue it's
unmethylated so all these C's don't have
the have they protecting protecting
methyl group essentially we know that
this normal tissue normally expressed
mlh1 so that normal healthy cell is able
to repair its DNA compare that to
endometrial cancer here all of the all
of the C's is specifically in that
region are completely methylated so all
the C's stay FC they were protected from
that chemical and essentially we can
tell in this case this is actually a
agnostic test only focused on the
promoter you can see even by eye though
that really that promoter is not
methylated and essentially mlh1 is not
active specific than this tumor the
reason you do this test in this tumor
this specific type is actually famous
for frequently having loss of DNA
mismatch repair and this is one
technology that allows you to look not
just that that one gene but a whole
cassette of genes associated with with
MMR this is also often serve a handy
checklist suspicious you're thinking of
how do you design a scientific
experiment here all the different types
of genome assays I've just talked about
and here all the ways that the cancer
genome can go wrong and I'm just gonna
spend a little bit of brief time just
showing data examples of what does a
mutation look like what does a copy
number variant look like in specific
types of data other than you start
questions up to this point just since we
got to calling before we go into detail
on each of these variant types okay
great okay so I just want to start with
somatic mutations I really encourage you
not to just trust the output of your
callers it's actually pretty
straightforward especially after this
workshop to get raw reads align them I
call mutations but really absolutely
must go that extra mile to actually look
at the underlying reads that support
those variant calls especially if
there's something biologically out of
place so it's very unusual for example
to get three mutations in the same gene
unless you're looking at all these
subclonal these subclonal variants so
option if i especially if I see three
mutations side by side I always just
open up the reads right away and ask the
quick question are those mutations next
to each other are they all on the same
read should they actually have been
treated as one very complex mutation
it's very hard to write a little script
that can go out and do this for you for
every single edge case from mutation
caller very powerful just to open up
reads and look at the man that GP so
here's what the real mutation or real
variant looks like so same sort of thing
coverage along the top here reads re
sort of a read stack and we're looking
for positions that look like this in
this case half the reads have a C have
two reads have a T in this case the
allele balance you actually hear a few
words that refer to leo balanced parent
allele frequency bath
mutation frequency is another one
mutation allele fractions these all mean
the same thing what fraction of your
reads have a non reference base so in
this case the Leo balance or BAFF I
would probably normally say is 0.47 or
47% there are a few I guess aspects of
cancer tissue that can cause that valve
to drift away from from 50% so the
reason this is so close to 50% is if you
have a perfectly pure cancer cell
population you have two copies of each
allele one of them is mutant one of them
it's not there for half of your DNA
should have a mutation so in theory and
a sort of a perfect sample certainly in
a germline variant where all the copies
of all the chromosomes are two
essentially you should have allele
balance very very very close to 50% just
by sampling error you can get up to you
know 60 maybe 65% or down to 40 maybe
35% but in general all of the your
variants in a totally pure hat like
diploid cell should be 50% this almost
never happens with a cancer sample for
all those other reasons double the
genome you have copy number changes you
have non cancerous cells the DNA
certainly we get in clinical labs are
very poor so the priority certainly in
pathology departments is to protect us
to collect and preserve tissue for
histology over everything else
obviously appropriate that's how you
actually get the cancer diagnosis so
essentially you get a tumor sample it's
essentially preserved in formalin and
embedded in a wax block this has the
benefit that you actually store these
tissues at room temperature you can then
take thin sections and look at from the
hardware microscope unfortunately as you
can see on this slide it results in
short on damaged DNA so in this case
this is a DNA ladder so this is high
molecular weight DNA that's more or less
intact this is highly fragmented
essentially from one of my first papers
ever but the lesson still has still held
even from formalin-fixed
paraffin-embedded tissues you can in
general get still get high molecular
weight DNA but I ordered these samples
essentially from good to bad
in fact in Maine twelve here this was a
metastases to bone and that that tissue
is essentially decalcified that Keith
decalcification process completely
destroyed the DNA so that one's pretty
much unusable but in general genomic
techniques have actually gotten better
and better at starting to use these
highly fragmented low-quality but still
pretty usable sources of DNA but this is
really a bit sort of number one question
is so should I get a sample I've never
seen before or the quality control is
not as good or I'm not finding mutations
it's always very helpful to go back to
understand what is the history of that
tissue prior to sequencing it's yeah so
Roma's question was really around is it
improvements in the lab processing of
the tissue and I guess maybe the
library's processing as well or the
analysis it's probably all of those but
I think the library construction is what
has improved the most how do you take
DNA like this and make a high-quality
library that represents all the DNA
fragments that were in the original
sample I think that's the layer that's
approved the most by our formatic
techniques certainly for quality control
have gotten better knowing that this is
an issue but still I mean the number one
thing I'm looking for in a new kit that
makes that library so that second step
and that workflow is how do you
effectively put those adapters onto
every piece of DNA because it's very
hard to capture especially this DNA
that's highly fragmented down here so if
anyone wants to make millions of dollars
a better ligates to put adapters on or
some well turns into that it's still a
big unsolved problem so we're still
you're doing very very well if half of
your DNA that you extract actually make
it into your next-generation sequencing
library it's still a very challenging
lab problem the other challenge is
tuners are not 100 percent cancer cells
so you notice I always try to
distinguish between tumors and cancer
tumors to me are all the cells in a mass
and cancer cells are the specific cells
that are cancer within the tumor
microenvironment so I'm just showing
here this is actually a planning diagram
for a laser capture microdissection this
is actually a lung adenocarcinoma
Matassa
sighs to a lymph node on this case that
have gone through circled out all the
tumors but you can see all the
intervening stroma and other types of
cells that are in here as well and in
this case essentially for every read of
cancer drive DNA we sequence there's a
second read corresponding to one of the
normal DNA and this is really why we
have to have very very deep sequencing
we need 100 I'm prompt in many cases
more than 100x coverage just because
half of those reads are just not going
to have any chance of having any somatic
mutations at all the other way to
distort of too
buzz words to describe this concept
tumor purity or to more content both of
these mean the same thing what fraction
of your tumor of your tumor cells are
truly cancer versus not the answers or
from a slide like this yeah I mean so
from histology essentially this is what
pathologists do you can look and
classify cells you can't really do it
using DNA sequencing video you know
they're all diploid in general they all
look they all look very similar to the
match normal so it's very hard using DNA
sequencing RNA sequencing has a
challenge so if you just take a sample
like this and grind it up you're now
looking at a mixture of gene expression
profiles cancer and lung cancer they're
actually whole algorithms now that rely
on that fact because you can look
specifically at transcripts from from
knowing immune cells and infer the
presence of immune cells the real the
only path as far as I know to actually
do this is to get down to single-cell
RNA sequencing to essentially digest the
tissue like this into free-floating
single cells and sequence them one by
one
Jim genomically that's really the only
true way to really pinpoint exactly the
cellular composition
flow cytometry is actually another good
way and so there are ways to do it but
just using conventional genomics which
is cotton extract
very very difficult so we talked about
tumor purity and tumor content the other
yeah I'm sure
so read-depth is just how many reads do
you have at the position so the read
depth here is 19 X so in this case this
variance very easy to find because half
of the 19 are gonna have a seat after
gonna have a tea roughly the challenge
actually have a slide on this later will
be what if only half of yourselves a
tumor so now we're looking at not at 10
sees we're actually looking at 5 sees of
5 out of 20 so if this was actually only
10x coverage now instead of 5 we're
looking at 2 so as your coverage goes
down it gets harder and harder to find
these rare variants I have a slide on
this a little bit later but yeah
coverage read that both of these mean
the same thing how tall is you reads
that at a given position and actually
you can see in the whole genome there is
some fluctuation to it so at each
position that's why we always report
read depth for coverages on average or
median because the stand deviation can
actually be pretty wide actually great
example here in the excel these two
exons are right next to each other this
guy probably has twice as many reasons
yeah they're purely for technical
reasons in the lab the other confounder
I showed the slide earlier is this idea
appointee or tumor copies so in this
case if you're looking for a mutation on
chromosome 7 if it's only on one of the
five chromosomes this is gonna be a very
challenging defying mutation because
first of all not all tumor cells or
cancer cells and even within the cancer
you're looking at one copy inside so
really this is we're finding these
extraordinarily rare mutations
especially if they're on an individual
chromosome that's been amplified are
very difficult very difficult to uncover
on the other hand if you had a mutation
on chromosome 7 before it was amplified
those mutations are very easy to find
because one tumor cells putting in five
copies of that of that needle so it sort
of has a bit of a double-edged
short-sword depending on the type of
variation that you're looking to find
looking just to your point here here's
that sort of that idea of coverage this
is actually the same sample sequence two
different ways at the time conventional
whole genome sequencing so I've zoomed
way out so all the reads look very small
in this case 15 X coverage no hint
whatsoever of a mutation contrast that
to the same sample using exome
sequencing this is important cancer gene
and we actually found six of the 100
39 reads actually did have the mutation
and this is purely sampling just
sequencing this 15 times is not enough
to essentially find even one read or to
have a chance to find even one read in
the very action in this case it was sort
of the combination of the worst possible
so a perfect storm of low tumor content
and there was a copy number game that's
not muted to this position so very very
difficult mutations defined hence the
read for increased read depth the other
benefit of whole genome yeah yeah
exactly so reads equals dollars so
essentially the question especially
designing experiment is where do you
want to spend your budget is it going
extraordinarily deep and relatively few
regions this is why clinical labs really
use the targeted panels because they're
using these clinical samples they just
put for the same budget go very very
deep on relatively few targets yeah and
this is where I'm a big proponent of
comprehensive testing as part of
clinical care because that actually
amplifies research as well and I'm
hoping the the case reports really gets
at this point as well there's also the
problem of what is the clinical
significance of it extraordinarily rare
you know three and or six and 139 Reed
sub-clause depends on the tissue
altogether yes
it really depends on your question so
usually if the experimental design needs
detection of variants of one and a
hundred then I would back calculate from
there so if I really need to have so a
good example of cell free DNA if I want
to find a piece of DNA of tumor DNA
that's circulating in blood let's say
for the experiment I need it down to one
percent sensitivity down to one percent
and then you can back calculate okay I
need one percent therefore I need this
depth to have a chance to even find one
in 100
because you actually have to sequence
right on 100 there's sort of a
statistical model we can sequence a
little bit more a little bit less
depending on your thyroid sensitivity
and then what genes do you need that
sensitivity is it literally just in one
spot is it a big panel do you need the
entire genome sensitivity down to 1%
extraordinarily expensive so there's
really no rule there's sort of
benchmarks that have been used so for
the Cancer Genome Atlas the target of a
hundred x median coverage across the
exome most genome studies the POG
program and in Vancouver where they're
clinically acting on genome sequence
they require 80 X coverage across the
whole genome gives them a certain
sensitivity nothing is ever perfect you
don't have infinite budget that it
there's really no lot really has to be
tied to science question first and then
back calculate it this is one example of
what can be done with whole exome
sequencing so in this case this is a 250
X exome sequencing experiment we did to
infer the tumor content of employee and
them to look at some subclonal
number variant or subclonal point
mutations as well so here's a tool here
it's called sequenza each little dot
here is a point in the genome that had a
germline snips we wanted to say is there
an are there differences in copy number
across the the entire genome so you just
focus here here's the coverage
normalized to a reference so if this was
just a normal blood cell all of these
tracks would perfectly line up at one
you can see they obviously don't
it's a copy number game here there's a
deletion here big huge copy of all of
chromosome 12 this tool essentially
infers from this data what the likely
tumor content and what the likely ploidy
is so when basically using this
algorithm and using this pattern of copy
number changes and losses it says it's
likely that 61% of your of your DNA come
from tumor cells and those tumor cells
have more gains than losses so a tumor
purity of two means they are no gains or
losses in this case there is a good
portion of the genome that is gained
it's not a complete genome double that
will give you a
boy these four in this case it's likely
just a diploid and then these very large
gains of chromosomes likely brought that
average up you can see there's actually
multiple solutions from this algorithm
so I've just shown the most likely one
here but this is really other it's very
important to work with especially the
pathology team that's working with the
tissue to really give you insight into
the tumor type what is the likely ploidy
do these genomes always double
themselves because maybe then you want
to change your your model for tumor
content tumor purity and also just
looking at the slide it says 61% but
there's 10% tumor cells or the whole
thing is just in the face lymph node
it's 100% tumor cells that really has to
go into the interpretation of this
mathematics result a second tool here
called PI clone in this case each little
stripe here is an individual mutation
this is the calibrated cellular
frequency so all these mutations here
essentially are in a hundred percent of
the tumor cells with the assumption that
the tumor content is 61 percent so
there's sort of some calibration of that
allele balance variant allele frequency
whatever you want to call it and
essentially this algorithm bins them
into clonal mutations using mutations
that are in every cancer cell sub-clonal
mutations and then actually extrude the
only reason we saw these extremely rare
mutations it's cuz we sequence these two
very high def so we actually have the
likelihood to pick up these variants
that are only have real fractions around
20% yeah so you know I'm sure you've
seen these beautiful like phylogenetic
trees they assume that all the copy
number variants or mutations at the same
allele frequency belong to the same cell
or population but you don't actually
know that
so the assumption here is all these
mutations have the same bath they at
least as published they belong on the
same cell of the same population you
can't actually know that without
sequencing individual cell and almost
definitely there may be you know
especially towards the end here these
are sort of starting to tail off there
might actually be an additional clone
here so
is really very challenging these axonal
pilo Janee or her
yeah these como had clonal phylogeny
reconstruction methods and actually
publish Osen Quaid Morris wrote a really
great talk where they essentially or
great paper where they essentially
compared all these different
reconstruction methods and they often
gave quite different in some cases
diverging results so it's really not a
solved problem certainly from the bulk
data and this is rather divided become
such a fan of single sale sequencing
approaches because you can really be
very quantitative around what subclones
are where and present at what frequency
because this is purely imprints of
statistical inference based on allele
fractions
yeah you really need some gold standards
and it actually turns out those
algorithms are very good in the author's
area of disease expertise so often you
really want to work in myeloma for
example with a group that knows how what
driver mutations are relevant most
frequently in that disease what are the
true clonal founder mutations because
they're not always the same across
cancer types and ultimately doing
experiment yourself taking two cell
lines putting them together or two cell
lines are two samples from the same
patient over time look at how those
phylogenetic trees over time those
change between the two time points you
really need some gold reference
standards it's just very hard to show up
and just run these tools on your own
data they really take a lot of care
stand them disease specific knowledge
around how complex should that clonal
heterogeneity be yeah it's not sort of a
plug and chug kind of tool
I've talked exclusively about Illumina
sequencing I'm going to continue to do
that but I did want to talk about some
other some other technologies one being
a bio sequencing this system actually
has the huge benefit
a little tiny 50 to 150 base pair reads
this can generate at ten or ten thousand
plus base pairs so I talked earlier
about that challenge of the unreadable
portion of the genome the PacBio and
nanopores actually several technologies
that could essentially allow your
sequence huge chunks of DNA with the
downside that they result they have a
very high artifact weight so you can see
just by eye there's a lot going on in
these reads the mutation of interest is
right here here's the Illumina
sequencing nice and clean very very low
error rate very obvious where the
mutations are both in point mutations
and in in Dells but don't discount these
technologies I mean obviously real
variants are coming through and
essentially bad formatting techniques
are needed to essentially normalize out
the background sequence or error from
other next-generation sequencing
technologies and very powerful certainly
as a cross-validation these longley
technology is especially powerful
certainly for pathogen sequencing
sequencing complete bacterial genomes
complete viral genomes the challenge
with them with clinical samples is you
saw a on that slide all the DNA comes
pre fragmented so it's really impossible
like you're never you don't even have a
fragment to even sequence to tens of
thousands of the sequence tens with
thousands of base pairs so it's been
really very challenging to applying
these long read sequencers to two
clinical samples this is really where
you want to think about where your
samples coming from what do you know
about them is the DNA even long enough
for the type of downstream experiment
that you're gonna do I'm gonna need you
talking a little bit about depth as well
so I just sort of double down on that
mutation detection sensitivity is
dictated by your depth or your coverage
and it's limited by your sequencer and
your background sequence or air so this
is essentially a plot from a paper we
published a couple years ago essentially
looking at the allele fraction
detectable and then your total overall
coverage so exilim sequencing TCGA we
usually sequenced 200x coverage I guess
pretty good detection down to a certain
probability
around 10% maybe a little bit lower to
be very confident in a clinical ably
about 555 gene panel that sequence to a
thousand
coverage gives you a pretty robust
mutation calling down 1% but certainly
if you want to get to highly complex
mixtures like circulating tumor DNA
you're really looking at 10,000 to
25,000 x coverage and this is sort of
the rationale at least for this study
does sequence to a very very high depth
because we wanted to detect these very
very low allele fraction variants
essentially diluted by normal DNA in the
blood stream so essentially the concept
is exactly the same so cell free DNA is
very attractive
essentially a 2's tumor cells die they
shed their DNA into the blood stream we
can use all the concepts i've just
talked about to find those very very
rare mutations in this basically in DNA
extracted from the liquid portion of
blood so i'm not going to talk very much
about circulating tumor cells but
specifically the application here at DNA
that's been shed and diluted into that
liquid portion we showed them all to
myeloma this actually worked very well
in fact almost better than bone marrow
aspirates we're able to find not just
mutations from the primary tumor itself
but also additional mutations from other
masses present within that patient the
other benefit of blood of course you can
take it much more frequently than you
can a solid tumor a solid tumor biopsy
this is what the data look like they're
actually two big methods out there one
is PCR based so you put a primer on
either side of your exon of interest in
this case and sequence them the method
we use and I talked about on the
previous slide was based on this cat
seed paper of Scott Bratton section out
here in Toronto a hybrid capture panel
basically pulls down DNA sitting on your
exons the downside with having captures
you actually also pull down all the DNA
sequences immediately adjacent so while
most your coverage is right on top of
your exon of interest you do have this
sort of off target problem reads our
dollars so this is slightly more it's
more expensive to get coverage
specifically on your target of interest
but essentially the data look the same
you're looking for mutations you're
looking for a very low allele fraction
reads amongst the whole pile of normal
reads
Scott well he was a postdoc at Stanford
showed very nice correlation between
size of tumor and amount of cell free
DNA circulating in blood still very hard
to find very early stage disease at that
point
certainly a tumor burden grew you had a
good a good ability to find tumor
derived DNA and as tumors grow and
shrink during clinical trial very tight
correlation between cell-free DNA and
red and tumor volume measured
radiographically so this tumor shrank
you got less cell free DNA and so on and
so forth really the ability to do some
pretty innovative monitoring and
tracking of patients as homer total
tumor burden that cells turning over
dump their DNA into blood and be
contracted you don't so this is the
other big challenge at least of
mutations in this case you have a single
mass that's coming and going certainly
had that problem in Multan myeloma we
had one aspirin and we saw the same
mutation over and over we could not find
it in that iliac crest aspirant but
there must have been another mat
somewhere else in the body that was
putting that DNA but there's starting to
change a little bit with a new antibody
based method so when fans of Carvalho's
lab has invented an antibody against
5-methylcytosine it pulls down all
methylated DNA from blood very powerful
to look at cell of origin but you can't
really tell the difference between a
metastatic site where a primary site
yeah because the same cell of origins
just move to different part of the body
just a few brief comments on somatic
copy number alterations we've talked
about this a lot this is actually a
relatively old technology called Skye
where essentially you have a probe
against each different region of the
genome gives you different color but you
can see really how complicated some of
these cancer derived chromosomes can be
as they rearrange and essentially stick
them cell or become rearranged or and
have increased copy or essentially stick
themselves together in that and
different combinations essentially the
whole way to find copy number variation
is by coverage so as you have more reads
that corresponds to a copy number gain
and the point of this slide really
showing the same results from old
microarray technology
exome sequencing and whole genome
sequencing they're actually really
robust copy number profiles available
even from targeted methods
here's an example from a clinical
clinical panel in this case not that
many exons baited in EGFR but all of
them have extraordinarily high coverage
so even from a targeted panel
actually abstract relatively robust copy
number profiles purely by looking at the
number of reads aligned to individual
genes in this case p10 totally deleted
even on the small panel p10 it's much
sorry much larger than this but they
only baited five of the exons no reads
whatsoever from all five of them and for
that as a copy never change and on the
larger panels basically just fill in
more dots so as you move from a targeted
panel to excel mark or genome
essentially get more data to support the
evidence of the game or a copy number
loss or amplification fusions
essentially look like this so in this
case when you have a breakpoint your
reads hits the breakpoint but instead of
continuing on like it would in normal
DNA essentially jumps the breakpoints
you get this sort of read that has a
very unusual mapping structure in this
case all the deletions were different
had different breakpoints in these
tumors but they always stuck out the
exact same the exact same exons are the
C term all DNA so really what we saw by
looking at large numbers of tumors
essentially you have all these sort of
raggedy breakpoints but you always took
up the same functional units and that
was really a key to discovering
essentially the importance of deletions
specifically in the C terminal region of
EGFR as is what real data looks like so
you have reads that very nicely aligned
to the reference and then they look
totally different the reason they look
totally different because they belong to
the partner gene in the fusion so
essentially they're numerous algorithms
now that go through and look for these
translocation breakpoints unfortunately
the false positive rate is very high
with these algorithms because really
additional needs to validate these
algorithms but also to to essentially
cross validates often what we'll do my
lab will run to fusion callers and look
at the overlap between the two methods
these gonna be extraordinarily complex
so Mike Berger when he wrote this
prostate cancer paper essentially on a
huge white board mapped out all the ways
that these genes all linked to each
other so he was able to show by hand
tempera surgeon but also tempera Stu
this middle-of-nowhere region that was
fused tooth rat 3 and that was fused
back there there is no bio from Attucks
algorithm in the world that knew that
this could happen
walk through all these breakpoints so at
some point it is pen and paper work
knowing this now of course people have
now written algorithms like this but
cancer does bizarre and crazy things and
it's obsession in this case to really
just go after a pretty simple fusion
which is just as temperature bridge of
fusion very important in prostate cancer
but there was this whole constellation
of other changes happening around this
one oncogenic advantages
just like mutations you can have very
quiet very arrangement genomes
extraordinarily rearranged genomes and
sort of everywhere in between this is a
very interesting case from there
blastoma nothing going on except for
this shattering of chromosome 5 so this
is an event called chromothripsis
essentially chromosome 5 blew itself
apart and then was stitched back
together resulting in the hyper
rearrangement only of that single
chromosome very important in prostate
cancer hasn't been seen very much since
in pediatric cancer but if it could
happen in one cancer type it can happen
in another I see him I think I've failed
10:30 is that right Michelle oh good ok
I thought I was unusually behind ok so
that sort of the DNA spatial answer
questions on copy number changes
rearrangements fusions things that
happen in DNA in general ok so the run
out to the talk is really in sort of the
RNA and sort of functional space I
talked earlier about really the power of
RNA to find relationships or linkages
between exons so in this case this is a
published paper basically looking at
this gene that's important to resistance
the 5-fluorouracil and what they did
basically had this cell line called myth
101 and then they treated that myth cell
line with 5-fluorouracil and the
question was what happens to this gene
at the transcriptional level they knew
from being a sequencing it wasn't
mutated there wasn't a copy number
change there was no structural
alteration but this gene has really been
linked to resistance 5 3 or 5 floor of
your cell what on earth is going on so
what they did here was they did hold
whole transcriptome sequencing looked at
the reads that map dumps and basically
counted the number of reads that map to
exon but also each exon exon boundary so
focus on the blue line first so
essentially read the line 2x on one you
should have reads from on the junction
from one to two like they did X on one
two three is unusual you shouldn't be
skipping from one to three whoops and
that does not happen and nor with a
normal cell line normal number of exon
to the two three junctions intact three
three four junctions attacked all the
pieces make sense in untreated dumps
totally different when you treat it with
five per year so basically what happens
is it starts to use this unusual exon
one exon three so essentially it's
completely skipping exon two here and
you can see essentially the levels you
know downstream on the gene are pretty
much the same really the only change
upon five four years so treatment is
this use of X out of this exon one to
exxon three and a slight depletion of
the use of exon 2 like you'd expect
consistent with that with that skipping
event totally invisible using DNA
sequencing something you really could
only see looking at the functional video
to the cell using RNA sequencing other
than more conventional use of RNA
sequencing is gene expression profiling
I think there's a whole session on this
essentially the idea of taking a huge
met matrix of genes by samples and
comparing them looking for basically
differences in gene usage between two
states the states can be pre true post
treatment tumor a tumor be there however
you want to dream up a way to compare
samples so you can do that using RNA
sequencing the other challenge is how
many genes are you looking at to be
different between two states is it 100
is a five thousand is a two thousand
essentially that's a power question and
there's a statistical design question I
think you're gonna be covering that in
additional workshop as well the other
use at least if I used as I've used RNA
sequencing is trying to get a tissue of
origin so in this case we looked at this
very unusual pediatric lung cancer
almost never happens in kids we really
want to know actually only a cure some
women a very strange feature so we
really wanted to know where are these
cells coming from
is to Trulia lung cancer it's coming
from somewhere else we took RNA
sequencing data from the that tumor and
compared it to a whole host of healthy
normals so this is a this is um how the
color data here are all individual
tissue sequence by a gene tech gtex the
gene do you know tight tissue expression
project and their entire project was
just grind at normal tissues and
sequence them not for cancer necessarily
but it turned out to be a great
reference resource for us so here all
different parts of the brain from
multiple donors they all clustered
together like you'd expect same with
lungs skin heart everything heart and
muscle heart just bulk muscle are
clustering nearer each other than brain
you know all the biology kind of makes
sense as well and then surprising to us
these lung tumors actually all clustered
specifically with muscles notice I've
been very smooth muscles specifically
and actually turns out that the tumor of
origin for these or the cell board term
for these is actually the endometrial
lining during development explains the
female only source of these tumors and
essentially they leave the endometrium
and they populate the lung and they
become this very unusual long sarcoma so
extraordinary rare totally new high our
hypothesis or explanation for potential
cell of origin and kicked off a whole
nother series hypothesis comes Ella's
experiment and kicked off a whole nother
series of lab experiments to validate
that that finding but really shows the
power of using public RNA sequencing
data to augment your own research
because really we only had you know five
of her own of our own locally generated
data they're augmented by probably
10,000 plus normal reference tissues now
scroogie text yes it's called gtex GTEs
so the website is GTE export elorg it's
grown much more since I this project you
can essentially search for any tissue
type
you can also subset by age and it's also
very interactive portals for you help I
talked a bit about nonhuman sequences
earlier in this case taking all the
reads from an RNA sequencing experiment
and we align them against
a base of basically all known pathogens
curated by NCBI NCBI and this case
you're actually able to totally
unexpected this is a lung adenocarcinoma
project we're able to reconstruct the
entire EBV genome epstein-barr virus
very unusual and lung cancer especially
for our lung adenocarcinoma diagnosis
that spurred a validation experiment
where we had in sexual hybridization of
EB V transcripts there are truly only
tumor specifics all the normal
surrounding cells were were negative for
EBV and this actually turns out to be
this very unusual lympho epithelial
alike lung cancer essentially the lung
adenocarcinoma was not the correct
diagnosis was actually this more rare
entity something that just you know flew
through in the RNA sequencing experiment
not something that's nice oh yeah
obviously I I did talk a little bit
about RNA sequencing and the many
technologies to do this get a limiting
dilution put one one droplet per cell
one well per cell all the concepts we've
just talked about completely cold at the
single cell level depth matters RNA
sequencing is basically counting number
of reads aligning each gene so really
there are many technological ways to get
to genomics at single-cell resolution
but all the ideas we've just talked
about are basically exactly the same all
those concepts genome doubling subclones
coming going all that is now directly
measurable with single cell sequencing
this is one technology ten economics in
this case there's basically a
microfluidic chip in this case you have
beads that contain here you have your
cells you have beads that contain
reagents those both get encapsulated in
the oil droplet you then burst the cell
and then you deliver those cells
specific barcodes to the RNA for that
for the individual cell so that gives
you bar coded CT DNA and each of those
barcodes is different so you can
actually tell each cell differently from
one another you then burst all the oil
droplets and sequence all the molecules
in your in your mixture but now you have
the benefit and that you can look at all
those much your barcodes and map the
Tartan a back to the individual cells
you can still analyze this like
conventional RNA sequencing
day-day just ignore the barcodes and
treated as a bulk they have the
additional ability to go much deeper
into individual cells or individual
populations I this is what the data look
like so each dot is an RNA sequencing
experiment so it's a single cell and
essentially just like I showed on that
star that heat map plot you can now
start to cluster these by by the
transcriptional similarity and then the
biology essentially rather than looking
at the bulk of the entire population you
can start to drill into individual
populations so if you circle out this
population here topmost expressed genes
are all related to the t-cell receptor
complex only expressed by T cells
essentially we infer that these are the
T cell populations in this case a
neutrophil population macrophage
population you can essentially mark
march through each of these populations
essentially using marker genes from
essentially previously published RNA
seek data sets just like I showed with
gtex earlier but now the the challenge
of gtex is its bulk tissue and now we
have a need for single cell reference
sets as well you can do this in cancer
so this is actually the same data just
color it a different way so this is
colored by its transcriptional identity
this is colored by who donated the data
so in this case this is a patient with
multiple myeloma two huge clusters that
are not in the normals and the two
healthy's actually can see all the
single cells are actually really nicely
intermingling but none of the neither of
those on those healthy donors have any
of these two populations from the cancer
patient so of course the punchline here
is these are actually two very large
cancer clones that are essentially
present transcription indistinct in the
same patient and the science question
here was actually what happens these
populations over time while they're on
the clinical trial the caller ID the
caller a question was what not just
happens to the tumor cell populations
but also what happens to the healthy
normal cells as well yes
oh so tis knee is essentially a
graphical representation of essentially
relatedness between gene expression
profiles so essentially the it's not
perfect but sort of at the spatial
representation of describe this it's
just
showing the relatedness between
different gene expression profiles
because if you think of all the
different combinations use a huge table
of 20,000 genes by however many cells be
sequenced so a heat map is virtually
unreadable because in all the
relationships of all those cells and all
those genes this is this a method to
compress all that data into a 2d
representation and there's actually new
methods now that replaced Disney plots
actually the method we used in that more
now is called you map which is
essentially the distance between two
dots is actually a measure of similarity
essentially it's a data visualization
technique for similarity between two
cells I really think we need a whole
workshop on single-cell michelle's
around there's probably I got an entire
week you can spend on the informatics of
single cell analysis are you yes oh good
Francis here yeah I definitely did not
do the Disney plot justice but we'll all
have to be ultra experts in this very
soon and the other sort of call out to a
reference set in terms of single cell
single cell reference the human cell
atlas is a large international
consortium to just like GTX capture all
single cell data from around the world
and put it for free on the internet
without a password this actually has had
some interesting patient consent issues
how do you consent a patient to put all
their single-cell data online but also
enormous Lee enabling because now you
can do a tumor experiment or a tumor
sequencing experiment and then compare
all the all those cells to a large Bank
of a healthy reference healthy reference
cells as well this is also a great
source of funding so founder of Facebook
Mark Zuckerberg and his wife Priscilla
Chan are busily funding pilot projects
in unusual cell types was cancer pilot
that were active in really starting to
build a lot of the infrastructure and
reference sets needed to do single cell
sequencing and I suspect within five
years we'll start to see maybe even
sooner some of the first clinical single
cell readouts just because you really
get this amazing view like we did here
of to cancer clones directly and the
ability to start mapping to be used to
potential treatments as well
okay so I'm getting in the last 30
minutes I'll just give a quick overview
of everything they talked about in
genetics so far or in cancer genomics so
far is influenced by the germline as
well so going back to that same Thompson
Thompson textbook really this idea of
needing two hits and a tumor suppressor
so essentially these are the breaks that
essentially stop cells from cycling
there's actually a large portion of
cancer patients actually upwards of 10%
or into some papers where patients are
actually born with a loss of one of two
copies of the tumor suppressor gene and
what we found we sequencers tumors is
there's almost always a second hit
roughly half of those tumors have a
second hit and DNA
I suspect we don't have data yet that
the other half are likely epigenetic
modifications or structural changes but
what's been really striking is the
manner of that second hit is different
every time
sometimes it's mutation sometimes it's
deletions sometimes rearrangement
sometimes methylation and really the
need specially in that ready for cancer
space for techniques that look at
multiple hits around multiple second
hits especially when you know patients
are already predisposed by one inherited
variant and here's actually a good
example from a pediatric cancer study in
this case here's their normal sequencing
reads this is just from a blood sample
you consider see by I hear every roughly
half the reads have this deletion and
the other half are all intact so there's
cell the normal cells are normal they
still have one copy which allows normal
cell development when you sequence the
tumor first of all we saw huge deletion
all of chromosome ten so they basically
used to have two copies and the antenna
not they deleted the unmuting copy and
then when you sequence the tumor every
single read apart from maybe a few
contaminating normal cells have that
mutations really be able to compare both
the germline state and the tumor state
but also actually using the germline to
sort of guide interpretation of the of
the tumor genome so just to get us into
the the case report I've talked a lot
about finding stuff making lists of
variants but the real challenging
certainly least automated part is still
that active genome interpretation so
it's one thing to call all these parts
but this is still the area where we need
certainly better software better access
to reference sets start helping us
interpret specifically what a mutation
that we've never seen before
maybe maybe doing within those cells and
that's really this act of how do you
annotate a variant how do you interpret
a variant then ultimately how do you
report it out to guide patient care
there many ways to do it
their whole guidelines American College
of medical genetics the College of
American Pathologists their many
guidelines for how to insure for the
variants they work for a good fraction
of them but there's really no one
hotshot piece of software as you can
tell from this this long list that
essentially will be in a mutation as a
driver or not a driver there are a few
tools to do it there's one tool called
angka Tator which will promote a huge
list of all the variants of all the
annotations or things that are nolan
about that variant we also use variant
effect predictor this is actually one I
use more often now there's desktop
software that basically put all that
data into context of all the other
mutations around it this is really still
a pretty manual process basically going
through coming up with a hypothesis
sometimes additional experiment around
what we think an additional of what the
somatic mutation cuff never change or
fusion is actually doing here's like to
one of the guidelines so here's ACMG and
basically their goal is to bin in our
case a German variant as benign or
pathogenic and what's the strength of
the evidence for pathogenic so this is
they're really great paper just to read
through how people are thinking about
interpretation of error of the variant
and all the many different aspects of of
what is known but a variant to try to
link essentially to give that variant
meaning the other challenge okay let's
say we've figured out what we think a
mutation is this is actually a real
clinical report from Princess Margaret
in this case this mutations not overly
convincing it's sort of what we often
call aberrant about knowing significance
it hasn't been seen very often sort of a
big piece of text that describes what we
think we know about the variant the
downside here this really does not scale
very well so she do whole exome
sequencing you've got 40 of these things
you're gonna write them all up probably
not
it's also a communication problem no one
especially conditions running a clinic
wants to just get a book of all your
very interpretations really we need more
dynamic and much clearer ways to
communicate scientific meaning for
specific variants that we've uncovered I
wanted her to do this as a see our
project genie so essentially it's
encouraging clinical labs from around
the world put their molecular results
but also the variant interpretation and
clinical data all into one place just so
we're not interpreting the same variants
over and over but also coming up with
practices for how to interpret and share
variants either tool I'm very keen on as
this Cibao portals is a tool that was
built for the Cancer Genome Atlas just
house all of the data but it's actually
become very powerful now as we start to
interpret individual cases so in this
case is in sort of the dashboards for a
single patient from diagnosis all of
their treatments subsequent tumors
looking at the copy number changes the
mutations and then all the specific
details welcome use mutations including
the allele frequency over time it's
really putting a huge wealth of data
really into an interactive website so
you can really start to look at these
data and really go through that
interpretive process for a single case
okay and that's what we're gonna do now
is essentially go through how a single
case was managed now almost I almost ten
years ago now published if you want to
read it great detail any questions on
the background before we go into this
case here okay so initial present so
this is all just a single patient so
everything we've talked about is basic
context for interpreting this single
case so 78 year-old man fit and active
no real reason to have cancer no family
history pretty large basically started
off with throat discomfort came in
examination actually found a pretty
large mass of basic attack so this is
pretty big for head neck cancer
nonsmoker no non drinker no real reason
for him to have this tumor but this is
sort of how he arrived step one is a PET
CT scan and a biopsy so they're always
starting with the tissue first just to
get a diagnosis and some understanding
of what we're looking at here in this
case
positive the pet was positive for the
lung mass itself also positive for the
draining lymph nodes as well so
essentially this is already poor
prognosis tumors now actually already
started to metastasize or at least move
to to nearby nodes this is usually a
test for the pathologist this is a very
rare a salivary gland tumor
so using this AB no carcinoma very rare
tumor no obvious clinical course or
obvious treatment necessarily for these
beyond surgery so in his case he had
surgery so ladies by section of both the
tumor and the draining nodes primary as
I said this micro papillary or ethnic
arsenal of micro papillary mucinous
features three of twenty one of the
notes I took out multiple notes three of
them are positive so this tumor is
mobile head neck very common to have
surgery and radiation so I got directed
therapy completed in February pretty
good quality of life for four months but
then most concern me for him you know
there's already hint that tumors mobile
he returned with numerous small on the
past Aziz in both lines so this is very
serious really trying to think of you
can't do surgery Pinklon pick out each
of these nodes individually what
systemic therapy might be appropriate
for him so they're thinking clinical
trial at that point metastatic disease
both lungs are involved in this case
they're looking for a clinical trial
this is the age where EGFR had EGFR
mutations have just been described there
each of our clinical trial each of our
inhibitors rather at the BC Cancer
Agency available so I want to ask the
question is EGFR expressed and it was
kind of so we're looking for here our
brown spots so there's some tumor cells
or expressing EGFR so what treatments
are possible target EGFR therapy is
maybe maybe warranted there wasn't sort
of a EGFR mutation service at that time
so really just going purely on
expression he was put on an EGFR
inhibitor so in this case or a lot nib
Tarceva
and it really didn't work at all so each
if our expression alone was not enough
to respond to this so in this case all
the lung Mets grew while on the tumor
the largest lesion really grew this is
really looking pretty serious they got
them off that drug right away there's
reason for it not to work but now
they're really thinking palliative care
what next like this really rare tumor
there's no obvious molecular like test
to order for these tumors so here's sort
of his timeline down here
sort of really thinking or a lot and it
was failed what do we do next so this
goes back to that other slide it's great
to have the landscape of tumors what are
the targets in an individual case
so exhaustion standard of care turned to
the GSC for new leads they had a special
re B and this is really something I do
for every single project is specialist
come bring samples what has the patients
have the patient's consented to can they
be shared can they be analyzed in a
specific way in this case they had a an
N of 1 re B meeting will do X on when I
our whole genome and RNA sequencing with
the goal to nominate essentially
potential treatments so it's not a
diagnostic test but really make sure the
re B and the patient is really on board
and the patient consented the for
genomic sequencing really convened it
came to him that it's not a diagnostic
test essentially this is an animal on
research project I mean Vancouver has
done nearly a thousand cases this is
essentially pod zero so the very first
case that they ever did I don't know if
it's scalable in its current form that
interpretive process really needs to be
quasi on made it or just needs a big
skilled team to work and in a
coordinated way around so I think
actually it is it's just gotta be big
big scale for it to be real uh I think
that every patient is not especially in
today's landscape is not something you
would do I think now there are many
molecular profiling programs like this
that sequence thousands of patients and
now they're just like a protocols to do
this so I think now you know that was
almost ten years ago I'm not sure
profiling the whole culture and
landscape has really changed
so really a central re be to do large
high-throughput profiling an
interpretation is it's it's being done
already
I think it's still a challenge for
communicator the patient your data will
be shared and how so it's opened up all
these new interesting nuances not so
much for the individual patient but for
Sir data sharing more broadly yeah that
would be great okay so we also took that
so her latinum had failed
let's try comprehensive profiling so in
this case a fresh frozen biopsy was
taken specifically for RNA sequencing
and the whole genome sequencing so
here's the CT scan a pretty big mass
pathology review again very high tumor
content so pathologist reviewed all the
cells 80% tumor content great so we know
the vast or the the gene expression
profiles will be highly enriched for
cancer cells good news and we also had
this formalin-fixed paraffin-embedded
DNA for the whole genome sequencing
works so here's what the whole genome
sequencing analysis found p53 very
famous tumor suppressor mutated in half
of all tumors that surprising RB loss of
function mutation very interesting in
this patients case because loss of RB
results in EGFR inhibitor resistance so
had we known this mutation was there
previously he would have never gone on
that erlotinib trial and this is now
actually an excluder for patients to go
on those trials it's really the need to
get profiling early and of course like
you're always gonna get with broad
profiling mutations in two genes I've
never seen before I know if I've seen
them since variants of unknown
significance very helpful as you start
to pile up thousands of these patients
because you can ask the question do we
see these mutations mutated and preach
or these genes mutated in appreciable
frequency or not not overly relevant to
drugs at least at that point in time and
and both essentially all four of these
mutations were confirmed by a different
sequencing method I showed PacBio
earlier Sanger sequencing for this study
essentially showing that these mutations
who are truly there in the DNA so
essentially not a lot they're
therapeutically beyond explaining the
treatment failure
so it's a mutation that introduces an
artificial stop codon so essentially it
tells the transcript or the essentially
a the transcript tells the protein
basically not to continue beyond that
that site so essentially it stops at
2:34 it should be much much longer for
IV and we infer that as loss of function
because you've lost power for some large
chunk of the protein just like before
here's circo's your the the chromosomes
around the outside in this case the this
little track here colors copy number
changes so greens are lost Reds are
gained so you can see EGFR amplification
perhaps linked to the over expression
they saw by IHC so it's over expressed
but also had this undermining RB
mutation loss of p10 also associated
with resistance to EGFR inhibitors so
you have this double whammy
EGFR was not ever gonna work very
interesting amplification of ret
actually highly how you focal very hard
to see here but full complications very
interesting because the thinking is
they're focused on and relatively few
genes read also interesting druggable
target map case that pathways likely
likely over expressed loss of p53 so in
this case is a mutation and the deletion
of p53 helpful for understanding a
biology but it's not really a direct
clinical path at least at that point for
p53 mutant tumors there's no I'm just
like permutation using fish to confirm
those copy number changes so lhasa p10
that focal rat amplification many many
copies of ret in these cells really
showing the genomics being cross
validated by a cell based method and
then the gene expression how do we
compare RNA sequencing especially at
that time we didn't have gtex there
weren't a lot of reference sets so
essentially the GSC they just took a
mixed bag of fifty tumors and they
actually I happen to have a blood sample
and they just said what is unusual in
this RNA sequencing profile are their
genes that are abnormally expressed to
an extraordinarily high level that could
be after the pond or could be could be
inhibited therapeutically
so in this case they saw a deletion of
CeMAT for totally consistent with under
expression specifically of that gene
sense
rat had that
amplification and it was enormous Lehigh
so cross that entire compendium of
tumors it was 34 times higher than the
next highest the next highest specimen
and was the most highly expressed uncle
gene very interesting in this case
because this is something that could
potentially be acted upon and p10 was
deleted and it was one of the lowest
across the entire compendium so really
they're very powerful having that
reference set and mapping the individual
patients profile to that reference
GSU's now become famous for mapping or
basically communicating biology using
these these pathway diagrams so
essentially here's the rat pathway
annotated with copy number changes and
gene expression changes rat both
amplified and overexpressed resulting in
over expression of the downstream
pathway and as you'd expect and then not
a lot of action necessarily here in this
in this parallel path way beyond loss
and down regulation of p10 so P dens a
negative regulator of this pathway so
clearly this pathway is very important
to the specific tumor really only
evident because you've measured both
mutation copy number and expression for
every every member in this pathway so
you're not just dependent on a single
gene test you're able to see the whole
constellation of things that are
essentially converging on this one
pathway so here's the list so here's
sort of biology over here upregulation
map k rat is important so on and so
forth and what drugs are these map to in
this case actually came up with four
potential for potential drugs its total
hypothesis hypothesis being at K and
ranch are the drivers of this tumor to
test it there's basically four potential
treatments and really it was up to the
oncologist here it's really provide
using genomics as a tool to help guide
clinical care and ultimately was up to
her to to choose so genome sequencing
and RNA sequencing still doesn't happen
overnight this took a whole month so
here's basically the day the biopsy was
taken two not two masses pretty large
took a whole month tumor continued to
grow from 22 to 27 24 28 from that list
the oncologist essentially chose Sinitta
nib mostly because the the side effects
were at least the worst side effect
reported first met in a mess
with just the skin rash sort of felt
that was tolerable in the context of a
research protocol so started on October
29th and actually worked dramatically
well so four weeks later significant
shrinkage of this tumor actually above
both legions 27 to 22 and 28 down to 21
and it's actually stabilized for seven
months there was a relatively robust
response there was some side-effects I
reduced the dose continued to have
stabilization of disease most
importantly no new nodules and the
nodules aren't growing at least during
those seven months but as I foreshadowed
on one of the first slides of the entire
talk monotherapy works for only a short
period of time there's really the
likelihood for resistance exactly the
same story here you sorta kept the
stabilization you're beating back the
tumour but then these Mets again begin
to grow either due to us a sub clonal
selection some ships specifically in the
existing clones many possible molecular
ways that this could have happened but
since but they did have other options
they didn't switch to the combination of
two of the other drugs at wrong on that
list and again the Z stabilized now
fitting that those pathways from a
different angle resulted in disease
stabilization and again another
continuation for three months like you
know the punchline really cancers are
dynamic and changing over time the exact
same story here recurrent disease again
after those seven months and most
currently most concerning the recurrent
disease at the yep evasive tongue so
essentially that primary has come back
potentially either and that metastatic
disease have traveled back to that a
permissive microbiome mental niche or
potentially just residual disease
remaining after surgery potentially more
likely especially now that the tumor has
now grown at the tongue a new meso skin
nodule is now growing progressive and
new metastases in life so really by
forcing these tumors through the
bottleneck they've essentially become
resistance to treatment against this the
red pathway quality of life is getting
worse of course the question is what
changed and again what can you do about
it
so there's large neck mass this is now a
chance to very easily accesible disease
you know essentially
to that site you can see many more
mutations and we saw the first time so
you saw all the mutations you saw
previously
but these additional mutations none of
which really are hotshot clinical trial
is not really a kinase that you could
really go after I've never seen these
mutations before none of these are
evidence in the pretreatment biopsy the
by tree treatment was a sequence - of
gigantic depth but really not even one
reads supporting the presence of these
mutations doing the exact same analysis
I just showed earlier you can see
there's a lot more red on this slide so
essentially the tumors way to to
overcome this treatment was just to amp
up ret signaling and to turn up this
this parallel pathway as well so p10
still lost but you can see over
expression of additional pathway members
but also this parallel pathway also
responding by due to increased copy
number state but also increased gene
expression level as well and this is
really where it gets extraordinarily
experimental is it now cocktail drugs
against all these pathway members the
disease is very advanced of course at a
major risk of adverse side effects you
can't just go grabbing three or four
drugs and deliver them to patients could
we have found these resistance
mechanisms pretreatment perhaps in
today's environment could cell free DNA
have been used to detect resistance
earlier than it was and could we have
actually modeled and monitored these
over time so especially to get long
additional longitudinal data there's a
real potential now to start learning
from metastatic disease and then go back
to the primaries unless four mechanisms
of resistance early on and unfortunately
yeah he actually passed away soon after
that just all the alike continue to to
decline here sort of his entire timeline
so essentially buying him just over an
additional year of good quality of life
but really that that problem that still
stands today is very challenging to
interpret deliver and act upon the
clinical genome and RNA seek yeah I mean
this is one certain path I'm very
interested in this area from the
single-cell approach as well doing some
of that pre post treatment modeling both
of my
I earn mint tumor clones I think this is
sort of the next big data boom
especially is ranked comprehensive data
become available on more and more tumors
but yeah when I say modeling there are
many ways there's patient-derived
xenograft there's cell lines whose brain
tumor stem cells
I think certainly infrastructure is much
better now getting serial samples like
this and this now really are those
experiments that can be done using real
patient-derived yeah I mean there's been
a lot of that work I haven't seen like a
prospective clinical trial that's shown
this beautiful can't-miss kind of test
but it's certainly an area of intense
research for sure and that's pretty much
the end of my talk so I'm